SearchConsider a goal-based agent which uses an atomic representation. The world will be represented as set of (atomic) states.The agent has a fixed set of actions.Each action will take the agent from one state to another state.If the agent knows the effects of its actions, it can keep track of the current state, without referring to the percept sequence.
Goal FormationGoal formation, based on the current situation (state) and the agent's performance measure, is the first step.In an atomic representation, the goal is a state or a set of states.Problem formation is the process of deciding which actions and states to consider,given a goal.
ExampleThe agent is in the city of Arad, Romania, and its goal is to get to Bucharest, Romania, by car.We assume that the agent has a road map of Romania. The actions are to drive from one city to another.The states are the city that the agent is in.We ignore all other details for this problem.Different levels of detail – levels of abstraction – lead to different problems.
Problem CharacteristicsThe problem as formulated is:Observable (agent knows the current state)Discrete (finite set of actions at any point)Known (agent knows the result of its actions)Deterministic (each action has only one outcome) u  Single Agent (we ignore other cars)
Well-defined ProblemA problem can be defined by five components:An initial state, s ε S,A set of possible actions, Actions(s) : S → Powerset(S),A transition model, Result(s,a): s x A → S,A goal test, Goal-Test(s): S → bool,A path cost, c(s, a, s'): S x A x S → R or S x A x S → N .
ExampleAIncitiaolnst:aFteo:rTehaechagceitnyt,itsheinaActroadfdrivingtoanothercitybyadirectroad uco  nnection, as given by the mapTransition model: For each city and connection, the destination city, as given by tuh emapGoal test: The agent is in BucharetPGaotahlCteosst:t:TFhoeraegaecnht issoiunrcBeucihtya,rectonnection, and destination, the road mileage, as ug iven by the mapgiven by the map
Solutionsolution is a sequence of actions leading from the initial state to a goal state. is a sequence of actions leading from the initial state to a goal state.In this example, it would be the series of actions (driving from city to city) that take the agent from Arad to Bucharest.The goal might also be to take no more than a given amount of time (assuming a
Abstractionreal-world problem.The problem, as formulated, is a model, an abstract mathematical description, of the real-world problem.The abstraction is valid if we can expand any solution of the problem into in a Unnecessary details are not included in the model (abstraction.)
Vacuum Cleaner WorldStates: Determined by the agent location and the dirt locationsAIncitiaolnSs:taTthe:reAenayctsitoantes:cLaneftb,eRdigeshitg, naantdedSuacskthe initial stateActions: Three actions: Left, Right, and Suck u Transition Model: Moves do as expected, except that moving left (right) from the lfeofltlmowosintg(rdigiahgtmraomst) square does nothing, as does Suck in a clean space. See theGoal test: All squares are clean
Transition Diagram
Eight Queens PuzzleStates: Any arrangement of 0 to 8 queens on the boardInitial state: No queens on the boardActions: Add a queen to any empty squareTransition model: Returns the board with a queen added to the specified square u  Goal test: 8 queens are on the board, none attacked
Real World ProblemsTouring problems: Visit each city at least onceTraveling Salesman problem: Visit each city exactly onceVLSI Layout: Position components and connections on a chip to minimize area,circuit delay, stray capacitances, and maximize manufacturing yield Robot Navigation: Get robot from point A to point B avoiding obstacles Protein Design
DefinitionsState: An non-divisible object in the abstract representation.Node (vertex): Data structure that contains a state – may have other information as well. Different nodes may contain the same state.Branch (edge): The application of an action taking the agent from one state to another.State space (graph) : The entire set of states and branches – may be finite or infinite
Definitions (cont'd)Expansion: The result of applying all applicable actions to a given state – gives a set of states. We also can expand a node, i.e., expand the state represented by the node, and encapsulate the resulting states in new nodesParent node: The node that was expanded.Child nodes: The nodes that are the result of an expansion.Leaf node: A node with no child node (may not have been yet expanded.) Frontier : Set of all leaf nodes available for expansionComplete: A search strategy will find a goal in finite time, if possible.
Search TreeThe possible action sequences starting at the initial state form a search tree with the initial state at the root of the tree.Each node is expanded (by taking all possible actions on the state of the node) to give the children of that node.Which node to expand next depends on the particular search algorithm. The search usually stops when a node containing a goal state is found.CaveatThe same state may be created more than once, i.e., there may be more than one sequences of actions that leads to a particular state.But each node (other than the root) has exactly one parent node, and so the search tree is a true tree.Actions that are reversible can lead to infinite branches!
General Tree Search Algorithmfunction Tree-Search(problem) returns a solution or failure initialize the frontier using the initial state of problemloop doif the frontier is empty then return failurechoose a leaf node and remove it from the frontier if the node contains a goal state then return theexpand the chosen node, adding the resulting nodes to thecorresponding solution frontier
Redundant PathsReversible moves create loops in the tree (actually, infinite branches with repeated states), called loopy paths.There could also be multiple action sequences that result in the same state, called redundant paths.Consider route-finding on a rectangular grid: There are four actions, so there are 4d sequences of actions of length d, leading to 4d nodes, but the number of distinct states reachable in d steps from any given node is bounded above by (2d)2.
Search GraphThis redundancy may cause a tractable problem to become intractable.To avoid redundant paths, we could use a data structure which stores all states thathave been created, checks if a newly created state is in that set, and then returnsthe node associated with that state.So, nodes would have unique states, but there could be multiple paths to a node. We record only the best path to the node, resulting in a tree.
General Graph Search Algorithmfunction Graph-Search(problem) returns a solution or failure initialize the frontier using the initial state of probleminitialize the explored set to be emptyloop doif the frontier is empty then return failurechoose a leaf node and remove it from the frontierif the node contains a goal state then return the corresponding solutionadd the node's state to the explored setexpand the chosen node, adding the resulting nodes to the frontier only if not in thefrontier or explored set.
Separation PropertyThe search tree constructed by the Graph-Search algorithm contains at most one copy of each state.The frontier separates the state-space graph into the explored region and the unexplored region.Every path from the start state to an unexplored state must pass through a node in the frontier.
NodeA node is a data structure containing the following fields:n.State: the state in the state space to which the node correponds.n.Parent: the node in the search tree that generated this node (the parent may changeas a better path is found).n.Action: The action that was applied to the parent to generate the node.n.Path-Cost: the cost, g(n), of the path from the start node to the node, as indicated bythe parent pointers.
Child-Node functionfunction Child-Node(problem, parent, action) returns a node return a node withState = problem.Result(parent.State, action), Parent = parent,Action = action,Path-Cost = parent.Path-Cost +problem.c(parent.State, action, State)
FrontierThe frontier is a list of nodes available for expansion.Initially, it contains just the initial state.A node is chosen from the frontier, then expanded, and its children may be put in thefrontier.In the Tree-Search algorithm, the children are always put in the frontier.In the Graph-Search algorithm, if the node is in the explored set it is not put into thefrontier. If the node is already in the frontier, and a better path to it has been found,then its parent and cost fields will be updated.The frontier may be implemented by a stack, queue, or priority queue depending onthe specific search algorithm.
Uninformed Search StrategiesUninformed search strategies use only the information available in the problem definitionBreadth-first searchUniform-cost searchDepth-first searchDepth-limited searchIterative deepening search
Breadth-First SearchExpand the root node, then the children of the root node, then the children of the children of the root node, and so on.All nodes at a given depth (length of the sequence of actions to create that node) are expanded before any nodes at a greater depth are expanded.Implementation: Use a (FIFO) queue to implement the frontier. New nodes go to the back of the queue, thus the oldest nodes (created first) are expanded first.
Breadth-First Search Algorithmfunction Breadth-First-Search(problem) returns a solution or failure node ← a node with State = problem.InitialState, Path-Cost = 0frontier ← a (FIFO) queue with node as the only elementexplored ← an empty setloop doif the Empty?(frontier) then return failurenode ← Pop(frontier) /* chooses the shallowest node */ add node.State to exploredfor each action in problem.Action(node.State) dochild ← Child-Node(problem, node, action)if child.State is not in explored or frontier thenif problem.Goal-Test(child.State) then return Solution(child) frontier ← Insert(child, frontier)
Properties of Breadth-First SearchComplete? Yes (if b, the branching factor, is finite) u  Time? 1+b+b2+b3+... +bd + b(bd-1) = O(bd+1)Space? O(bd+1) (keeps every node in memory)Optimal? Yes (if cost = 1 per step)Space is the bigger problem (more than time)
Uniform-Cost SearchInstead of expanding the shallowest node, uniform-cost search expands the node, n, with the lowest Path-Cost, g(n).Implementation: Use a min priority queue to implement the frontier. The priority is g(n).There are two other differences from breadth-first search:1. The goal test is applied when a node is selected for expansion, rather than when itis generated.2. A test is added to check whether a better path has been found to a node on thefrontier.
Uniform-Cost Search Algorithmfunction Uniform-First-Search(problem) returns a solution or failure node ← a node with State = problem.InitialState, Path-Cost = 0frontier ← a priority queue with node as the only elementexplored ← an empty setloop doif the Empty?(frontier) then return failurenode ← Pop(frontier) /* chooses the lowest-cost node */if problem.Goal-Test(child.State) then return Solution(child) add node.State to exploredfor each action in problem.Action(node.State) dochild ← Child-Node(problem, node, action)if child.State is not in explored nor in a node in frontier thenfrontier ← Insert(child, frontier)else if child.State is in a node in frontier with higher Path-Cost thenreplace that frontier node with child
Properties of Uniform-Cost SearchEquivalent to breadth-first if step costs all equalComplete? Yes, if step cost ≥ ε, where ε is a small, positive constantTime? # of nodes with g ≤ cost of optimal solution, where C* is the cost of the optimal solutionSpace? # of nodes with g ≤ cost of optimal solution,Optimal? Yes – nodes expanded in increasing order of g(n)
Depth-First SearchDepth-First Search always expands the deepest node in the current frontier.The search proceeds immediately to the deepest level of the search tree, where thenodes have no successors.As those nodes are expanded they are dropped from the frontier.Then search then “backs up” to the next deepest node that still has unexploredsuccessors.Implementation: Use a stack to implement the frontier, or use recursion, and avoidusing an explicit stack.
Depth-First Search Algorithmfunction Depth-First-Search(problem) returns a solution, or failure return Recursive-DFS(Make-Node(problem.InitialState), problem)function Recursive-DFS(node, problem) returns a solution, or failure if problem.Goal-Test(node.State) then return Solution(node)elsefor each action in problem.Action(node.State) do child ← Child-Node(problem, node, action) result ← Recursive-DFS(child, problem,)if result ≠ failure then return resultreturn failure
DFS PropertiesComplete? No: fails in infinite-depth spaces, spaces with loops. However, DFS can be modified to avoid repeated states along path (just keep track of the states on the path) in order to assure completeness in finite spacesTime? O(bm), where m is the length of the longest branch: terrible if m is much larger than d but if solutions are dense, may be much faster than breadth-firstSpace? O(bm), i.e., linear space!Optimal? No
Depth-Limited SearchDepth-Limited Search is similar to Depth-First Search, but with a cutoff, limit. When depth limit is reached, the search is cut off, i.e., nodes at that depth are treated as having no children.The algorithm will note when cutoff, as opposed to outright failure, occurs.The algorithm is implemented very easily using recursion. The implicit control stack (storing the recursive function calls) is used instead of an explicit stack.
Depth-Limited Search Algorithmfunction Depth-Limited-Search(problem, limit) returns a solution, or failure/ cutoffreturn Recursive-DLS(Make-Node(problem.InitialState), problem, limit)function Recursive-DLS(node, problem, limit) returns a solution, or failure/cutoff if problem.Goal-Test(node.State) then return Solution(node)else if limit = 0 then return cutoffelsecutoff_occurred? ← falsefor each action in problem.Action(node.State) dochild ← Child-Node(problem, node, action)result ← Recursive-DLS(child, problem, limit – 1) if result = cutoff then cutoff_occurred? ← trueelse if result ≠ failure then return resultif cutoff_occurred? then return cutoff else return failure
Iterative Deepening DFSDo Depth-Limited Search with an increasing depth limit, i.e., set the limit to 0, then 1, then 2, ..., until a goal is reached.function Iterative-Deepening-Search(problem) returns a solution, or failurefor depth = 0 to ∞ doresult ← Depth-Limited-Search(problem, depth) if result ≠ cutoff then return result
Iterative Deepening PropertiesIterative Deepening does do extra work, because each time the depth bound is increased, the previous search tree is thrown away, and the new search redoes all the work in generating it (and then goes to another level).However, given a branching factor b, the next level as approximate b times as many nodes as the previous tree, thus extra work is not excessive.In general, iterative deepening is the preferred uninformed search method when the search space is large and the depth of the solution is not known.
Properties (cont'd)Complete? YesTime? (d+1)b0 + d b1 + (d-1)b2 + ... + bd = O(bd) u  Space? O(bd)Optimal? Yes, if step cost = 1
Summary of AlgorithmsCriterion Breadth- Uniform- Depth-First Depth- Iterative First Cost Limited DeepeningComplete? Yesa Yesa,b No No YesaTime O(bd) O(bm) O(bl) O(bd)Space O(bd) O(bm) O(bl) O(bd)Optimal? Yesc Yes No No Yesc,dis the branching factor; d is the depth of the shallowest solution; l is the depth limit. Superscript caveats are as follows: a complete if b is finite; b complete if step costs ≥ ε, for positive ε, c optimal if all step costs are identical.
Bidirectional SearchBidirectional Search operates by running two simultaneous searches, one from the initial state to a goal, and one from a goal to the initial state, and hoping that the two searches meet in the middle.The motivation comes from the fact that bd/2 + bd/2 is much smaller than bd.It is implemented by replacing the goal test with a check to see if the two frontiersintersect.May not get an optimal solution.Must be able to compute predecessors of actions.