 Local SearchIn local search algorithms, instead of systematically exploring all paths from the start state, we evaluate one (or more) current states to yield the next state(s):u  These algorithms are useful when the object is to find a goal, and not find the path to the goal.We operate on a single, current node (or set of nodes) and move only to the neighbors of that node.This is useful for solving optimization problems, where the goal is to find the beststate according to some objective function.  
 Hill-climbingIn Hill-climbing, we continually move in the direction of increasing value. Terminates when it reaches a peak with no higher neighbors.Finds local maximum.Also known as steepest ascent, or greedy local search.May do random local restarts to try to find a global maximum.  
 Hill-Climbing (cont'd)   
 Simulated AnnealingProblem with hill-climbing – you never go down.You may have to go down if stuck on a local maximum. In simulated annealing, try moving in a random direction:l  If the new position is better, go there.l  If the new position is worse, flip a coin to decide if you should go there. l  However, the coin is weighted so that the worse the move is, the lesslikely you are to go there:l  If the new position is worse, but only slightly so, you could have a49% chance.  
 Simulated Annealing (cont'd)To be precise, the probability decreases exponentially with the “badness” of the move.In addition, there is also a temperature factor in the probability calculation.When the temperature is high, you are more likely to accept bad moves.When the temperature “cools” you are less likely to accept a bad move, and tend tostay in the area.This is based on metallurgy, where metals are heated to a high temperature and thencooled slowly in order to reach a low-energy crystalline state.  
 Local Beam SearchBeam Search is a technique for searching a tree.It is similar to best-first search, but instead of keeping track of the best state, we keeptrack of the best k states.Generate all their successors and then pick the best k states from the set of allsuccessors.Useful information is passed along the parallel search threads.Stochastic beam search – instead of choosing best, randomly select the successorswith the probability of being selected based on its fitness.  
 Genetic Algorithms (GA)A genetic algorithm is a variant of local beam search.Genetic algorithms simulate evolution in the real world.GAs begin with a set of k randomly generated states, called the population. Each state, or individual, is represented as a string over a finite alphabet. At each state, individuals are chosen according to a fitness function:l  Those individuals can reproduce and/or mutate to produce the next generation.  
 Example : 8 Queens ProblemConsider the 8-Queens problem.The string is the row position for each of the 8 queens (moving the column from leftto right).The fitness function is the number of non-attacking pairs of queens.The random mutation is to choose a queen at random and move it to a random squarein its column.  
 Genetic Algorithms (cont'd)First, each individual is rated by a fitness function.The probability for being chosen to reproduce is directly related to an individual'sscore.Pairs of individuals are selected at random.A crossover point is choosen randomly from the positions in the string.The parent strings are divided at the crossover point and the tails are switched tocreate new individuals.Each location in a new individual is subject to mutation.  
 Example: 8 Queens (cont'd)   
 8-Queens: Codefor(int j=0; j<1000; j++) {    Ind[] newFolks = new Ind[folks.length];    int total = 0;    for(int i=0; i<folks.length; i++)        total += folks[i].getFitness();    for(int k=0; k<folks.length; k++) {        newFolks[k] = new Ind(choose(folks, total),}    folks = newFolks;}                  choose(folks, total));newFolks[k].mutate();if(Math.random()<.05)  
 8-Queens : Code (Ind class)public int calcFitness() {    int count = 28;    for(int i=0; i<8; i++)        for(int j=i+1; j<8; j++)            if(row[i] == row[j]               || j-i == Math.abs(row[i]-row[j]))                count--;    return count;}public Ind() {    row = new int[8];    for(int i=0; i<8; i++)        row[i] = random.nextInt(8);    fitness = calcFitness();}  
 8-Queens: Code (Ind class, cont'd)public Ind (Ind a, Ind b) { // cross a with b    row = new int[8];    int point = random.nextInt(9);    for(int i=0; i<point; i++)        row[i] = a.row[i];    for(int i=point; i<8; i++)        row[i] = b.row[i];    fitness = calcFitness();}public int getFitness() {    return fitness;}public void mutate() {    row[random.nextInt(8)] = random.nextInt(8);    fitness = calcFitness();}  
 8-Queens: OutputInitial Population:  Min = 16, Max = 25, Ave = 20.1200008.3After 1,000 Generations:  Min = 21, Max = 28, Ave = 26.3500008.3  
 Non-Deterministic ActionsIn a fully observable and deterministic environment, the percept sequence is unimportant:l  The agent can always calculate which state it is in given the initial state. In a partially observable environment, the percepts narrow down the possible statesthe agent is in.In a non-deterministic environment, the percepts tell the agent which of the possibleoutcomes of its action occurred.The solution will be a contingency plan.  
 Example: Erratic Vacuum WorldWe change the results of the actions in the vacuum cleaner world as follows:u  Suck, when applied to a dirty square will sometimes clean the adjacentsquare as well.u  Suck, when applied to a clean square will sometimes leave dirt.In the transition model, the RESULTS function will return a set of states instead of a single state.The contingency plan may contain IF statements: [Suck, if State = 5 then [Right,Suck] else []].  
 And-Or Search TreesWe extend our notation of trees to allow for non-deterministic actions.In a deterministic environment, the agent always chooses the path in the tree.In a non-deterministic environment, the environment will sometimes determine thenext state – the agent must find a path to a goal for all the possible alternatives. An And-Or search tree has two types of nodes:u  OR-nodes (agent's choice of action) andu  AND-nodes (environment's choice of result).  
 And-Or Search Tree: Example   
 And-Or Search Tree SolutionA solution for an And-Or Search Tree is a subtree that: 1) has goal node at every leaf,2) specifies an action at each of its Or nodes, and3) includes every branch below an And node.The plan may include conditional statements (if, switch).A recursive, depth-first algorithm can be used to search And-Or Search Trees.  
 And-Or Search Graph Algorithmfunction And-Or-Graph-Search(problem) returns a conditional plan, or failure Or-Search(problem.Initial-State, problem, [])function Or-Search(state, problem, path) returns a conditional plan, or failure if problem.Goal-Test(state) then return the empty planif state is on path then return failurefor each action in problem.Actions(state) doplan ← And-Search(Results(state,action), problem, [state | path])if plan ≠ failure then return [action | plan] return failure  
 And-Or Search Graph Algorithmfunction And-Search(states, problem, path) returns a conditional plan, or failure for each si in states doplani ← Or-Search(si, problem, path)if plani = failure then return failurereturn [if si then plan1 else if s2 then plan2 else ... if sn-1 then plann-1 else plann]  
 Cyclic PlansA plan may be cyclic, but should eventually halt, assuming that each possible outcome of a non-deterministic will occur eventually.Thus, plans may contain loops.  
 Search with No ObservationsAn agent's percepts may return only partial information about the environment or no information at all.We will make two simplifying assumptions:1) Illegal actions will have no effect on the environment. 2) The cost of an action is the same in all states.The agent must maintain a belief state – the set of states that the agent believes it could be in.  
 Belief-State Searchu  u u  u  u  u Belief states: Every possible set of physical states, size 2N.Initial State: Usually the set of all physical states, though the agent might have prior knowledge that restricts the set.Actions: Us Є b Actionsp(s)Transition model: U Results (s,a)sЄb pGoal test: All physical states in the set must be goals.Path cost: The cost of the physical action.  
 Vacuum Cleaner (sensorless)   
 Incremental Belief-State SearchIncrementally find a plan that works for each state in the belief state:Find a plan that works for the first state in the belief state, then check if it works forthe next state, and so on.One plan must work for each state in the belief state. Note: There is one plan that works for each state.u  For a non-deterministic environment, there could be a different plan that works for each state.  
 Searching with Partial InformationAn agent searching with partial information will still need to maintain a belief state which is a set of physical states.However, the percept received constrains which states can be in the belief state. The new belief state, b' is given by:b' = Update(Predict(b, a), o)Where b is the initial belief state, a the action, o the percept, and Update is defined as:Update(b'', o) = { s : o ε Percept(s) and s ε b'' }. The And-Or Search algorithm can be used here.  
 Online SearchOffline Search: The agent computes the entire plan first and then executes it. Online Search: The agent interleaves computation with action:u  The plan may change as the agent executes it.u  This is better of dynamic or semi-dynamic environments.Online search is necessary for unknown environments – where the agent mustdiscover the states and the effects of its actions (exploration problems).  
 ExplorationWe assume that the agent knows its Actions, the step-cost function, and the Goal- Test, but does not (initially) know the Results(s,a) function.That is, the agent can only discover what the results of its actions are by performing the actions themselves.We will assume that the agent has a heuristic function, h(s) that estimates the distance to a goal.The agent wants to reach a goal by a path of minimal cost.The competitive ratio is the cost of the path found to the path an agent with fullinformation would take.  
 RestrictionsNote that an agent in exploring the state space cannot jump from one state to another, non-adjoining, state.The agent would have to physically backtrack to the previous state.The A* algorithm which picks the next state to expand from the frontier is notsuitable:u  It is better to expand nodes locally.Depth-First Search is one possibility, but requires actions to be reversible.  
 Other ApproachesHill climbingRandom walk: Can be exponential.Markov Chain Monte Carlo (Metropolis Algorithm)Hill climbing with memory: Store the best current estimate, H(s), with each node.Initially this is h(s), but is updated as the agent gains experience.Learning real-time A* (LRTA*): Similar to hill climbing with memory, but uses, thefunction c(s,a,s') + H(s'), where c(s,a,s') is the cost to return to s', and the H function is updated when moving.  
 LRTA* Example   