COSC 410: Artificial IntelligenceSpring 2016Dr. Donald SimonOffice / Phone: 416 College Hall / 396-6472Class Hours: M 6:00 PM - 8:40 PMOffice Hours: MWF 1:00 PM - 3:00 PM, M 5:00 PM - 6:00 PM, or by AppointmentE-mail: simond@duq.eduHome Page: www.mathcs.duq.edu/profs/simon.html
Course ObjectivesThis course is a survey of the area of artificial intelligence (AI). We will discuss what AI is, We will focus on various domains of AI, specifically, natural language processing, automate In addition, we will study the common sub-problems of these domains, such as knowledge The course will also cover neural nets.As part of the work in the course, students should expect to become proficient in the Prolog
GradingAssignments & Programs 40%Project 15%Mid-term 20%Final 30%Assignments and programs are due at class time. Tests are in-class and closed book. Grading Scale: 100-90 = A, 89-80 = B, 79-70 = C, 69-60 = D, below 60 = F. Plus-minus grading will not be used.
Honor PolicyStudents in this class fall under the mandate of the University's academic integrity policy. Any student guilty of plagiarism will receive a grade of 'F' for the course and will be repor Work done in this course is to be by the individual, not a group.You may not share (copy, give, show) your homework with other students in the course Any code not your own that is included in your programs must be properly cited. This includes code from the book and that given by the professor.Submitted work must be your own work, although you may include code from the book (or book's website) and that given out by the instruction.If the code is not your own, it must be properly attributed.
ProjectA project addressing a problem in artificial intelligence is required.The project should be the equivalent of three weeks of homework in terms of effort.The topic is of the student's own choosing, with the consent of the professor.The project should involve programming, mathematical analysis, and/or statistical analysis in a significant way.If the program contains code, source code must be included with the project.A write-up of 5-10 pages is also required.Examples of projects are: An expert system for tree identification, a spam filter, a chess program, a sudoku solver, a simple, domain specific question and answering system, or a neural net to solve a classification problem.The project could solve a problem in a new way, or could be an implementation of a known approach to a new problem.

Late WorkA homework or program assignment will lose 5 points per day that it is late. Weekends are counted as one day.Homework assignments and programs may not be turned in after they are discussed in class.All programs and homework must be turned in by 4/26/16. Work turned in after that time will not be accepted.
Students with DisabilitiesStudents with documented disabilities are entitled to reasonable accommodations if needed.If you need accommodations, please contact the Office of Freshman Development and Special Student Services in 309 Duquesne University (412-397-6657) as soon as possible.Accommodations will not be granted retrospectively.  
Tentative ScheduleDate Topic(s) Readings1. 1/11 Introduction, Search Chap. 1-31/18 MLK Day – No Class2. 1/25 Informed Search Chap. 4,53. 2/1 CSP, Logical Agents Chap. 6,74. 2/8 First-Order Logic Chap. 85. 2/15 Automated Reasoning Chap. 9, Prover9 home page, Prover9 manual Prover9 examples, Prolog Manual6. 2/22 Mid-term; Planning Chap. 10, 112/29 Spring Break: No class7. 3/7 Knowledge Representation Chap. 128. 3/14 Uncertain Knowledge & Reasoning Chap. 13, 149. 3/21 Learning from Examples Chap. 183/28 Easter Break – No Class10. 3/30 Knowledge in Learning, Reinforcement Chap. 19, 21 (Wed.)11. 4/4 Natural Language Processing Chap. 2212. 4/11 More NLP Chap. 2313. 4/18 Perception Chap. 2414. 4/25 Project Presentations5/2 Final – 6:00 pm to 8:00 pm
IntroductionWhat is Artificial Intelligence? How about we look at some quotes first:The theory and development of computer systems able to perform tasks that normally require human intelligence, such as visual perception, speech recognition, decision-making, and translation between languages. [Google]Artificial intelligence is the study of how to make real computers act like the ones in the movies. [Anonymous]The question of whether a computer can think is no more interesting than the question of whether a submarine can swim. [Edsger Dijkstra]Machines will be capable, within twenty years, of doing any work that a man can do. [Herbert Simon, 1965]A year spent in artificial intelligence is enough to make one believe in God. [A. J. Perlis]
Areas(From Wikipedia):Deduction, reasoning, problem solving u  Knowledge representationPlanningLearningNatural language processingMotion and manipulationPerceptionSocial intelligenceCreativityGeneral intelligence
Four ViewsThinking HumanlyThinking RationallyActing HumanlyActing Rationally
Thinking Humanly: Cognitive ModelingDetermine how humans thinkReproduce thought process in machinesTestable theories of how the mind worksCarbon-based vs. silicon-based processingExamples: General Problem Solver (Newell & Simon), Neural Nets (McCulloch & Pitts), Transferring Consciousness (Moravec)
Acting Humanly: SimulationProgram need not simulate human thought, but rather human behaviorPerform tasks that require human intelligence: Natural language, Reasoning, Planning, Learning, Knowledge representation, VisionTuring Test (Turing, 1950), Loebner PrizeThinking Rationally: Logicist ApproachLogical, rigorous reasoningFormal logicSystematize all necessary knowledgeInference is keyMay out-perform humans
Acting Rationally: Rational Agent ApproachOperate autonomously: Perceive environment, React to stimuli, Create and pursue goals, Adapt to changeAchieve the “best” outcome according to some external measureSimilar skills to acting humanlyInternal mechanism may differ from humansBook's approachAI ApproachesAutomatons dreamed of – lack of prerequisite technology to make it happen (Mechanical Turk) Creation of computers provided needed technology (40s-50s)Machines were not just number-crunchers, but could manipulate concepts (50s-60s): LISP (McCarthy), Logical Theorist, GPS (Simon & Newell), Perceptrons (McCarthy), Resolution Theorem Proving (Robinson), Syntactic NLPEarly approaches emphasized general reasoning – inference was key, knowledge secondaryKnowledge-based systems (60s-70s)Use of domain specific knowledge (Buchanan)Expert systems (Feigenbaum)Uncertainty in data and rule applications (Shortliffe)Focus on knowledge representation (60s-80s)Natural language semantics (Schank, Chomsky)CYC (Lenat)Neural Networks, Back-propagation (Rumelhart & McClelland)
Stochastic approaches (90s-)Hidden Markov Models (Baum)Bayesian Networks (Pearl)Statistical techniques for NLPModern approaches:Intelligent agentsVery large data setsSkimming the web, social media
State of the ArtAutonomous Vehicles (Google, CMU-GM) u  Speech Recognition (Siri, Google Now)Autonomous Planning (MAGPEN)Games (Deep Blue)Machine Translation (Google Translate)Question-Answering (Siri, Wolfram Alpha, IBM Watson, Mitsuku) u  Robotics (Roomba, Drones, Atlas)
The FutureTerminator Colossus Samantha DataCP30 & R2D2 HAL
Intelligent AgentsPerceives environment through sensorsPercept – input at a particular timePercept sequence – complete history of inputs u  Sensors could be real – microphone, cameraSensors could be virtual (simulated)Acts upon environment through actuators u  Agent changes environmentActuators can be real – robotics, voiceActuators can be simulatedAgent function maps percept sequence to an action Could be implemented as an agent program
Agents and environmentsThe agent function maps from percept histories to action:[f: P*àA]The agent program runs on the physical architecture to produce f u  Agent = Architecture + Program
Vacuum-cleaner worldPercepts: location and contents: A, B, Dirty, CleanActions: Left, Right, Suck, NoOp
Rational agentsAn agent should strive to “do the right thing,” based on what it can perceive and the actions it can perform. The right action is the one that will cause the agent to be most successful.Performance measure: An objective criterion for success of an agent's behaviorExample: Performance measure of a vacuum-cleaner agent could be amount of dirt cleaned up, amount of time taken, amount of electricity consumed, amount of noise generated, etc.For each possible percept sequence, a rational agent should select an action that is expected to maximize its performance measure, given the evidence provided bythe percept sequence and whatever built-in knowledge the agent has.
Rationality is distinct from omniscience (all-knowing with infinite knowledge)Agents can perform actions in order to modify future percepts so as to obtain useful information (information gathering, exploration)An agent is autonomous if its behavior is determined by its own experience (with ability to learn and adapt)
Specifying the Task EnvironmentPEAS: Performance measure, Environment, Actuators, SensorsMust first specify the setting for intelligent agent designConsider the task of designing an automated taxi driver:Performance measure: Safe, fast, legal, comfortable trip, maximize profitsEnvironment: Roads, other traffic, pedestrians, customersActuators: Steering, accelerator, brake, signal, horn, displaySensors: Cameras, radar, sonar, speedometer, GPS, odometer, accelerometer, engine sensors, keyboard
Properties of Task EnvironmentsFully observable vs. partially observable: An agent's sensors give it access to the complete state of the environment at each point in time.Deterministic vs. stochastic: The next state of the environment is completely determined by the current state and the action executed by the agent (If the environment is deterministic except for the actions of other agents, then the environment is strategic).Episodic vs. sequential: The agent's experience is divided into atomic “episodes.” Each episode consists of the agent perceiving and then performing a single action. The choice of action in each episode depends only on the episode itself.Static vs. dynamic: The environment is unchanged while an agent is deliberating. The environemtn is semidynamic if the environment itself does not change with the passage of time, but the agent's performance score does.Discrete vs. continuous: A limited number of distinct, clearly defined percepts and actions.Single agent vs. multi-agent: An agent operating by itself in an environment.Known vs. unknown: Whether or not the agent knows the results of its action. If unknown, the agent will have to learn the results. Strictly speaking, this is a property of the agent, not the environment.ExamplesChess with a clock Crossword puzzle Taxi drivingObservable Fully Fully PartiallyDeterministic Deterministic Deterministic StochasticEpisodic Sequential Sequential SequentialStatic Semi Static DynamicDiscrete Discrete Discrete ContinuousSingle Agent Multi Single Multi
EnvironmentsThe environment type largely determines the agent design.The real world is partially observable, stochastic, sequential, dynamic, continuous, multi-agent.
Four Basic TypesThere are four basic kinds of agent programs: u  Simple reflex agents,Model-based reflex agents,Goal-based agents, andUtility-based agents.
Simple Reflex AgentsSimplest kind of programSelects actions on the basis of the current percept u  Ignores rest of percept historyCould be thought of as “instinct”Often implemented bySimple table look-upPattern matchingSet of condition action rules
Simple Reflex Agent
Simple Reflex Agent Programfunction SIMPLE-REFLEX-AGENT(percept) returns an action persistent: rules, a set of condition-action rulesstate ← INTERPRET-INPUT(percept) rule ← RULE-MATCH(state, rules) action ← rule.ACTIONreturn action
Model-based Reflex AgentKeeps track of the part of the world it can't seeMaintains an internal state (model) the depends on the percept history Needs to know:How world evolves independently of the agent u  How the agent's own actions affect the worldModel doesn't have to describe “what the world is like now” in a literal sense – can have additional information.Example: taxi driver agent has rule "when driving home with half a tank of gas, get gas." "Driving home" includes goal information.MODEL-BASED-REFLEX-AGENT(percept) returns an action persistent:state, the agent's current conception of the world statemodel, a description of how the next state depends on current state and action rules, a set of condition-action rulesaction, the most recent action, initially nonestate ← UPDATE-STATE(state, action, percept, model) rule ← RULE-MATCH(state, rules)action ← rule.ACTIONreturn action
Goal-based AgentHas specific goal information that describes situations that are desirableCombines goal with model to choose actionsMay require search or planning if a sequence of actions is needed to reach goalCan have single or multiple goalsJustifications of actions to achieve goals may be represented explicitly, and so may be examined or modified.
Utility-based AgentsAgent asks “what will make me happy?”Has a utility function that measures happinessUtility function is an internalization of the external performance measureIn partially observable or stochastic environment, decision making may be uncertain, so agent could maximize expected utility.If the utility function is explicit, then the agent can use a general purpose algorithm to maximize utility.

Learning AgentsIf the agent program can be modified, then the agent can learn.The agent can being in an initially unknown environmentMust take feedback to evaluate its performance and use that information to change its program.Can experiment in the environment and try out new things – learn how its actions affect the environment.The parts of the a learning agent are:Critic: Evaluates percepts, figures out how well agents is doing, and provides feedbackLearning element: Takes feedback from critic and makes changes to the performance element.Performance element: Selects actions based on percepts, can be modified, and can be examined by the learning element. This was considered to be the entire agent in previous slides.Problem generator: Suggests actions that could lead to new and informative experiences.
Internal RepresentationThree kinds of representations (increasing in complexity and expressive power):Atomic: State is a black box with no internal structureFactored: State consists of a vector with attribute valuesStructured: State is comprised of internal objects, each which may have attributes of their own. The relationship between objects is represented as well.Representation ExampleAtomic: inPittsburgh, Fido, 1234, xyzzy Factored: Balrog:Hit Dice: 55d20+520 (1,100 hp)Initiative: +17Speed: 20 ftArmor Class: 48 (+13 dexterity, -3 size, +28 natural armor), touch 21, flat footed 26 u  Base Attack/Grapple: +40/+56
Structured Representation