 Graph Separation TheoremThe frontier separates the state-space graph into the explored region, and the unexplored region, so that every path from an explored state to an unexplored state has to pass through a state in the frontier.  
 Graph Separation   
 General Graph Search Algorithmfunction Graph-Search(problem) returns a solution or failureinitialize the frontier using the initial state of problem initialize the explored set to be emptyloop doif the frontier is empty then return failurechoose a leaf node and remove it from the frontier if the node contains a goal state then return thecorresponding solutionadd the node's state to the explored setexpand the chosen node, adding the resulting nodes to the frontier only if not in the frontier or explored set.  
 Proof of the Graph Separation ThmProof by induction on the number of iterations of the main loop of the graph search algorithm.Base Case: 0 iterations. The explored set is empty and the frontier is just the initial state. There are no paths from an explored state to an unexplored state, and the theorem is vacuously true.  
 Induction StepSuppose that the graph separation theorem is true after i iterations of the main loop (Induction hypothesis).We must show that it is true after i+1 iterations (assuming that the algorithm has not halted by finding a goal).We do a proof by contradiction. We suppose that the theorem is not true after i+1 iterations, i.e., there is an explored state a, and an unexplored state b, and a path between a and b that doesn't go through the frontier. We must show this leads to a contradiction.  
 Assumption (after i+1 iteration)   
 Induction HypothesisHowever, the theorem holds before the i+1 iteration, by the induction hypothesis. So, before the i+1 iteration, the path from a to b must have passed through a state in the frontier, or state a must not have been an explored state. In the latter case, a must have become an explored state in the i+1 iteration, which means that a had to have been in the frontier before the i+1 iteration.  
 Case 1 (before i+1 iteration)   
 Case 2 (before i+1 iteration)   
 Case 1So, before the i+1 iteration, the path from a to b passes through z, a state in the frontier. But after the i+1 iteration, that path doesn't pass through the frontier (but still passes through z). Therefore z, must have been chosen and removed from the frontier in the i+1 iteration. Consider the next state on the path from z to b, and call it w. w must be an explored state, in the frontier, or an unexplored state.  
 Case 1 (cont'd)   
 Case 1 (cont'd)If w is an explored state, then there must be another state in the frontier on the path from w to b, by the induction hypothesis. That state is still on the path after the i+1 iteration. XIf w is in the frontier, it still is in the frontier after the i+1 iteration, and is on the path from a to b. XIf w is an unexplored state, then when z is removed from the frontier in iteration i+1, w will be put in the frontier by the algorithm, and so there will be a state in the frontier on the path from a to b. XIn all three cases, the path from a to b passes through a state in the frontier after the i+1 iteration. X  
 Case 2Clearly, a is that state that was chosen and removed from the frontier in the i+1 iteration of the algorithm. Consider the next state on the path from a to b and call it w. w must be an explored state, in the frontier, or an unexplored state. All three possibilities lead to contradictions.  
 Case 2 (cont'd)   
 QEDIn both Case 1 and Case 2 we find a contradiction. Therefore our supposition that after i+1 iterations there is an explored state and an unexplored state which has a path between them that doesn't pass through the frontier is incorrect. Thus, by induction, the theorem is true.  
 Informed (Heuristic) SearchThe search strategies we've discussed so far are all general strategies.Informed, or heuristic, search uses problem-specific knowledge to guide the search process in the hopes of finding a goal state more quickly.These strategies are a form of priority-first search where a priority queue is used to implement the frontier.An evaluation function, f(n), is used as the priority of node n.  
 HeuristicsHeuristics are:u  u  u  u u  u Rules of thumbsEducated guessesWays to use outside knowledge when searching Rules for a simplified (relaxed) version of theproblemRules derived by studying subproblems Rules learned from experience  
 Heuristic FunctionThe evaluation function, f(n), may have a heuristic component, h(n).h(n) = estimated cost of the cheapest path from the state at node n to a goal state.One constraint: h(n) must be 0 for a goal node.  
 Greedy Best-First SearchGreedy Best-First Search tries to expand the node that is closest to the goal. For this search we take f(n) = h(n), the heuristic measure of closeness to the goal.For example, for the route-finding problem in Romania, we could take f(n) = h(n) to be the straight-line distance (hSLD) from n to Bucharest, the goal.  
 Values of hSLD Arad 366 Mehadia 241 Bucharest 0 Neamt 234 Craiova 160 Oradea 380 Drobeta 242 Pitesti 100 Eforie 161 Rimnicu Vilcea 193 Fagaras 176 Sibiu 253 Giurgui 77 Timisoara 329 Hirsova 151 Urziceni 80 Iasi 226 Vaslui 199 Lugoj 244 Zerind 374  
   
 Properties of Greedy BFSu u Complete? No, not even in finite spaces, but the graph search version is complete in finite spacesTime? O(bm), where m is the maximum depth of the search spaceSpace? O(bm)u u With a good heuristic function, the complexity can beOptimal? No reduced substantially.  
 A* SearchA* Search combines the cost to reach to the node, g(n), with the cost of going from the node to the goal, h(n), i.e., f(n) = g(n) + h(n).f(n) is the cost of the best known path from the start node to a goal node that passes through n.It is equivalent to Uniform-Cost Search except that A* uses g+h instead of g.  
 A* Algorithmfunction Graph-Search(problem) returns a solution or failure initialize the frontier using the initial state of probleminitialize the explored set to be emptyloop doif the frontier is empty then return failurechoose a node with smallest f-value and remove it from the frontier if the node contains a goal state then return thecorresponding solutionadd the node's state to the explored setexpand the chosen node, adding the resulting nodes to the frontieronly if not in the frontier or explored set, updating f-value if smaller  
   
 Additional DefinitionsIf P is the pathn0 →a0 n1 →a1 n2 →a2 ...→ak-2 nk-1→ak-1 nk then we definePcost(P) = c(n0,a0,n1) + c(n1,a1,n2) + ... + c(nk-1,ak-1,nk)andsubPath(P,ni,nj), where 0 ≤ i ≤ j ≤ k, to be the pathni →ai ni+1 → ai+1 ...→aj-2 nj-1 ->aj-1 → nj.  
 Additional DefinitionsWe say that the path P is optimal, if there is no other path Q, from n0 to nk, such that Pcost(Q) < Pcost(P).We note that if P is optimal, and x and y are nodes on P, then subPath(P,x,y) is also optimal – if there were a less costly path from x to y, substitute that path in P, to get a less costly path than P.If we say that a path to a node x is optimal, we mean that the path from the start node, s, to x is optimal.  
 Proof of OptimalityWe prove that A* for graph-search is optimal given that h is consistent by the following steps. We show:1. h(x) ≤ Pcost(P) + h(y) whenever P is a path from x to y.2. When a node is selected and removed from the frontier, the path to that node in the search graph is optimal.3. Nodes are removed from the frontier in non- decreasing order by f.  
 1. h(x) ≤ Pcost(P) + h(y)If P isx=n0 →a0 n1 →a1 n2 →a2 ...→ak-2 nk-1→ak-1 nk =Then, by the definition of consistency:h(n0)≤ c(n0,a0,n1) + h(n1)≤ c(n0,a0,n1) + c(n1,a1,n2) + h(n2)≤ c(n0,a0,n1) + c(n1,a1,n2) + ... + c(nk-1,ak-1,nk) + h(nk)So h(x) = h(n0) ≤ Pcost(P) + h(nk) = Pcost(P) + h(y). Technically, this is a proof by induction.y  
 2. Path to Chosen Node is OptimalWe show, by course-of-values induction on the number of iterations of the main loop for the graph- search algorithm, that whenever a node is removed from the frontier, the path (in the search tree) to that node is optimal.We assume that we are about to do iteration i, and that for all previous iterations, the proposition holds.Case 1: In the first iteration, the node removed is the start node, s, and the path to itself is empty.  
 2. Path to Node Optimal (cont'd)Case 2: Suppose that during some iteration after the first, the proposition becomes false, i.e., that the path to the selected frontier node, say x, is not optimal. Call the (non-optimal) path to x in the search tree, Q, and let P be an optimal path to x. We first show that there must be another frontier node in P preceding x. x cannot be the start state, so there must be some node, y, that immediately precedes x in P.  
 2. Path to Node Optimal (cont'd)   
 2. Path to Node Optimal (cont'd)y cannot be an explored node: it would have been removed previously from the frontier, and so, by induction, the path to y would be optimal. When y was selected, the path to x, its successor, would have been updated, so the path to x would also be optimal, which contradicts the definition of x.Therefore y is either a frontier node, or y is an unexplored node. In the latter case, the Graph Separation Theorem says that there must be a frontier node in P between s and y, hence before x.  
 2. Path to Node Optimal (cont'd)Hence, there is another frontier node in P preceding x. Call the first frontier node in P, z. z cannot be the start node, so there is a node in P immediately preceding z. Call this node w. w is not a frontier node, as z is the first frontier node in P. w is not an unexplored node, because the Graph Separation Theorem says that there would be a frontier node in P before w, hence before z. w must be an explored node. By induction, the path to w is optimal. When w was selected, the path to z would be updated to be optimal as well.  
 2. Path to Node Optimal (cont'd)   
 2. Path to Node Optimal (cont'd)Thus, z is a frontier node in P that precedes x and the path to z is optimal. Because Q, the path to x, is not optimal, we have:g(z) + Pcost(SubPath(P,z,x))= Pcost(subPath(P,s,z)) + Pcost(subPath(P,z,x)) = Pcost(P) < Pcost(Q) = g(x).From Step 1, we have:h(z) ≤ Pcost(subPath(P,z,x)) + h(x).  
 2. Path to Node Optimal (cont'd)Adding these two inequalities together, yields: g(z) + Pcost(SubPath(P,z,x)) + h(z)< g(x) + Pcost(subPath(P,z,x)) + h(x), or f(z) = g(z) + h(z) < g(x) +h(x) = f(x).Thus, z is a frontier node with f(z) < f(x), so x would not have been removed in iteration i, a contradiction.  
 3. Nodes Removed in OrderWe next show that the frontier nodes are removed in non-decreasing order by their f-values. Suppose that this was not the case, i.e., in iteration i, x was removed from the frontier with f-value fx, and in iteration i+1, y was removed with f-value fy, and fx > fy. That means that in iteration i, when x was selected, y must have either been an unexplored node, or in the frontier, but its f-value at that time was greater than or equal to fx.  
 3. Nodes Removed in Order (cont'd)Since the f-value of y changed when x was removed from the frontier, y must be a successor of x, and when x was removed, g(y) was set to g(x) + c(x,a,y) for some action a. Since h is consistent, h(x) ≤ c(x,a,y) + h(y). So, after x is removed and y updated,fy = g(y) + h(y)= g(x) + c(x,a,y) + h(y) ≥ g(x) + h (x) = fx.This contradicts the fact that fx > fy.  
 QEDFor a goal z, h(z) = 0, so f(z) = g(z). Since nodes are removed from the frontier in non-decreasing order by f-value, and when a node is removed, its g-value is optimal (so a goal's f-value is optimal), the goal closest to the start node must be removed before any farther goals, and when it is removed, an optimal path to that goal has been found. If the space is finite, then sooner or later, a goal must be reached.Thus, A* using graph-search is optimal.  
 Properties of A*A* is optimally efficient for any given consistent heuristic, that is, no other algorithm is guaranteed to expand fewer nodes than A* (except possibly for tie-breaking).However, A* is exponential in the length of the solution, and the graph-search form of A* keeps all generated nodes in memory, also exponential.  
 AlternativesIterative Deepening A* (IDA*): The same as IDA, but uses the f-cost (g+h) instead of depth for the cut-off.Recursive Best-First Search (RBFS): Has a f_limit variable to keep track of the f-value of the best alternative path available from any ancestor of the current node. When the limit is exceeded, the algorithm goes back to the alternative path, replacing the f-value of each node of the path with a backed-up value – the best f-value of its children.  
 Alternatives (cont'd)Simplified Memory-Bounded A* (SMA*): Like A*, but with limited memory. When memory is full, it most drop a node for each node added. It always drops the worst leaf – the one with the highest f- value, but it backs up that value to the node's parent. SMA* regenerates the subtree only when all other paths have been shown to be worse than the forgotten path.  
 Heuristic Functions - Example8-puzzle:Average solution for a randomly generated problemis 22 steps.The branching factor is about 3.An exhaustive search to depth 22 would take about3.1 x 1010 states.Graph search cuts this down to 181,440 because onlythat number of distinct states are reachable.  
 8-puzzle Heuristic Measuresh1 = the number of misplaced tilesh2 = the Manhattan distance – the sum of thedistances of the tiles from their goal positions,allowing only horizontal and vertical moves Both of these heuristics are admissible.The book's simulation shows that even with smallproblems, A* with h2 is 50,000 times moreefficient than uninformed iterative deepening. Also, A* with h2 outperforms A* with h1.  
 Dominant Heuristicsh2 dominates h1, that is, h2(n) ≥ h1(n) (but is still optimistic). A* will expand every node whose f- value is less than C* (the cost to the optimal goal). So, A* will expand every node with h(n) < C* - g(n). If h2(n) < C* - g(n), then h1(n) < C* - g(n), so that A* with h1 will expand the same number or more nodes than A* with h2.  
 Relaxed ProblemsThese heuristics are exact measures for variants of the 8- puzzle. If the rules were changed so that a tile could move anywhere instead of to an adjacent empty square, then h1 would give the exact number of steps in the solution. Similarly, if a tile could move one square in any direction, even if there's already a tile there, then h2 would give the right number.A simplification of the original is called a relaxed problem. In general, relaxed problems can be used to generateheuristics.  
 Pattern DatabasesSolutions to subproblems can be used to generate heuristics. For example, in the 8-puzzle, a sub- problem could be to get tiles 1, 2, 3, and 4 in their proper places. The cost of solving the subproblem is a lower bound on the cost of solving the whole problem.A pattern database would store the exact solution costs for every subproblem. When a subproblem occurs, look it up, and use that value as h.  