 Knowledge-Based AgentsA knowledge-based agent will do explicit reasoning about the environment and about its actions.It will maintain an explicit, internal representation about what it knows – a knowledge base.The agent will be able to add information to the knowledge base (Tell) and be able to ask the knowledge base (Ask) for information.  
 InferenceInference is reasoning from known facts and deriving new facts.Both Ask and Tell may involve inference.When information is added, additional facts may be derived (forward inference). When the agent asks for information, the information may have to be derived fromexisting knowledge (backward inference).  
 Knowledge RepresentationThe information in the knowledge base will be represented in some formal language – the knowledge representation language.The knowledge base may initially contain some information, called background knowledge.The process of keeping the information in the knowledge base consistent when new facts are added (or existing facts deleted) is called truth maintenance.  
 Generic Knowledge-Based Agentfunction KB-Agent(percept) returns an action persistent: KB, a knowledge baset, a counter, initially 0, indicating time tell(KB, Make-Percept-Sentence(percept, t))action ← Ask(KB, Make-Action-Query(t)) tell(KB, Make-Action-Sentence(action, t)) t← t+ 1return action  
 Declarative vs. Procedural Know.Sometimes knowledge is represented declaratively, i.e., as a set of statements that describe the information. It is easier to update declarative knowledge.Sometimes knowledge is represented procedurally, as methods that may be invoked, and store knowledge as behavior. It is easier to apply procedural knowledge.A knowledge base may contain both types of knowledge.  
 Wumpus WorldHunt the Wumpus was originally written by Gregory Yob in BASIC while attending the Dartmouth campus of the University of Massachusetts in 1972 or 1973. (Wikipedia)The wumpus world is a cave consisting of rooms connected by passagesways. Lurking somewhere in the cave is the wumpus, who eats anyone who enters its room. The wumpus can be shot by the agent.The agent has only one arrow.  
 Wumpus World (con'td)Some rooms contain bottomless pits which trap anyone who enters the room. Some rooms contain gold.The agent moves around the wumpus world, collecting gold and avoid the wumpusand the pits.The game ends when the agent is killed or the agent climbs out of the cave.  
 PEAS Descriptionu  +1000 for climbing out of the cave with the goldu  -1000 for falling into a pit or being eaten by the wumpus u  -1 for each action taken-10 for using up the arrow  
 PEAS Description (con'td)u  A 4x4 grid of rooms.u  The agent begins in the square labeled [1,1], facing to the right.u  The locations of the gold and the wumpus are chosen randomly, with a uniformdistribution, from squares other than the start square.u  Squares, other than the start square, have a 20% chance of containing a pit.  
 Actuators: uA  ctuators:oou  u  u ITfhaegaegnetntrtiecsantommoovveeFionrtwoarwd,aTllu,rthneLeafgtebnyt9d0oe,sonr'tTmuorvneR.ightby90 . If agent tries to move into a wall, the agent doesn't move.The agent can also Grab to pick up the gold in the room, if any.The agent can Shoot the arrow in a straight line in the direction in which the uag entisfacing.The arrow continues to move until it hits (and kills) the wumpus, or until iut  hits a wall.The agent has only one arrow.u   
 PEAS Description (con'td)Sensors: The agent has five sensors, each of which gives a single bit of information: uS  ensors: The agent has five sensors, each of which gives a single bit of information:u squares, the agent will perceive a Stench.u  u  u In the squares directly adjacent to a pit, the agent will perceive a Breeze. In the square where the gold is, the agent will perceive a Glitter.When the agent walks into a wall, it will perceive a Bump.u   
 Properties of Wumpus WorldWumpus World is partially observable, deterministic, sequential (reward may come after several actions have been taken), static, discrete, single-agent, and may be considered known or unknown (the agent knows the result of its actions in theory, but not in practice. ;)).  
 Wumpus World The image cannot be displayed. Your computer may not have enough memory to open the image, or the image may have been corrupted. Restart your computer, and then open the file again. If the red x still appears, you may have to delete the image and then insert it again.   
 Wumpus World: Sample Run   
 Wumpus World: Sample Run   