 Adversarial SearchWe begin with a two-player game, where the players are adversaries, e.g,. a zero-sum game.We also assume that the game is deterministic, perfect information, and that the players take turns.The two players will be called MAX and MIN.  
 Game: DefinitionA game can be defined as a search problem with the following components:So: Initial StatePlayer(s) : the player whose turn it is in state su u u  Actions(s)u  Results(s,a)u  Terminal-Test(s): True when the game is overu  Utility(s,p): Payoff function – numeric value for a game that ends in terminalstate s for player p.u  In a zero-sum game the total is always the same.  
 Game TreeThe Actions function and the Result function define a game tree – a tree where the nodes are states of the game and the edges represent moves.Play alternates between MAX and MIN.Each level of the tree (one player's move) is called a ply:u  Two levels make up a move.The terminal nodes are marked with value of the utility function.  
 Example: Tic-Tac-Toe   
 Game TreeWe note that in the game tree, the moves alternate between players, so each player only has control for his/her ply.At each ply, a player will choose a move that leads to an optimal terminal node considering all possible next moves by the opponent.The game tree resembles the And-Or search tree for non-deterministic environments, except that instead of the environment determining the response, the other player determines the response.  
 Contingency PlansEach player will create a contingency plan, where the move selected depends on the choices of the opponent.An optimal strategy is one that leads to an outcome that is at least as good as any other strategy when one if playing an infallible opponent.  
 Strategy – 1 ply to goClearly, if MAX has a move that leads directly to a move that wins for MAX, MAX will take that move.If MIN has a move the leads directly to a win for MIN, MIN will take that move.In general, if all of MAX's moves go to terminal states, MAX will make the move to the state with highest value as measured by the utility function.If all of MIN's moves go to terminal states, MIN will move to the state with lowest value.  
 Strategy – 2 Plies to goSuppose it is MAX's turn, and all moves (two plies) end in terminal states.MAX knows that MIN will respond with whatever move is best for MIN.For each of MAX's moves, MAX can assign a value to the resulting state based onMIN's move, namely the minimum value of all of that state's successors (whichare terminal states).MAX will then choose to move to the successor state with highest value.  
 General StrategyWe can generalize this by working from the bottom of the tree up to the root.Each state, s, will be assigned a value, Minimax(s):u  Minimax of a terminal state is Utility(s).u  If it is MAX's turn at a given state, MAX will always choose the child with thelargest Minimax value:u  The Minimax value of MAX's state is the maximum value of the Minimaxvalues of the children.u  MIN will choose the child with the smallest Minimax value:u  The Minimax value for Min's states is the minimum value of its children.  
 MinimaxMinmax(s) =Utility(s) if Terminal-Test(s)maxa ε Actions(s) Minimax(Result(s,a)) if Player(s) = MAXmina ε Actions(s) Minimax(Result(s,a)) if Player(s) = MIN  
 Minimax Example   
 Minimax AlgorithmRecursively assign Minimax values to all the states.MAX chooses the successor with highest Minimax value.MIN chooses the successor with lowest Minimax value.Time: O(bm) where m is the maximum depth of the tree, and there are b moves at eachlevel.Space: O(bm) for the full tree.This is impractical for real games.  
 Multiplayer GamesIf there are more than two players, the Minimax algorithm is easily modified. The utility function would return a vector of values, one value for each player. The Minimax function also returns a vector.Each player seeks to maximize his/her own value, so will choose the move to thesuccessor state with highest value for that player:u  Minimax for a state is the Minimax value for the successor state withhighest value for the player. This assumes no collusion between players.  
 Alpha-beta PruningWe can prune the search, eliminating large subtrees with a little extra bookkeeping. Suppose that MAX has evaluated its first move and knows that the first child has avalue of 3.While MAX is evaluating its second move, suppose it finds that one of MIN's moveleads MIN to a state with value 2.If MAX chooses the second move, then clearly MIN can do no worse than 2, and, forMAX, choosing the first move leads to a better result.Once MAX sees that MIN has a 2, it can stop looking further in the tree.  
 Alpha-Beta Pruning (cont'd)u any choice point along the path for MAX (α) andchoiceThpeoivnatlauleonogf thebpeastht (florwMesItN-va(βlu)e.) choice we have found so far at anychoice point along the path for MIN (β).When MAX evaluates a move and finds it results in a value greater ≥ β, it can stopevaluating the remaining successors because MIN would not allow MAX to get tothat node (as it already has a path to obtain β).When MIN evaluates a move and finds it results in a value greater ≤ α, it can stopevaluating the remaining successors because MAX would not allow MIN to get to that node (as it already has a path to obtain α).   u
 Alpha-Beta Pruningchoice of moving to that node.cGheoniecIrefaotlhfPemripnolcaviyipnelgre:htoCasothanasbtiednteotredreac. hnoidce,nmso, meitehwehr eartethine tphaeretrnetensoudcehotfhantothr eatpalanyer hasuch  oice point further up, then n will never be reached in actual play. Once we discover enough about n (by examining some of its descendants) to reach If the player has a better choice, m, either at the parent node of n or at any  a
 Alpha-Beta Pruning   
 Alpha-Beta Pruning Algorithmfunction Alpha-Beta-Search(state) returns an action v ← Max-Value(state, -∞, +∞)return the action in Actions(state) with value vfunction Max-Value(state, α, β) returns a utility value if Terminal-Test(state) then return Utility(state)v ← -∞for each a in Actions(state) dov ← Max(v, Min-Value(Result(s,a), α, β) if v ≥ β then return vα← Max(α,v)return v  
 Alpha-Beta Pruning Algorithmfunction Min-Value(state, α, β) returns a utility value if Terminal-Test(state) then return Utility(state)v ← +∞for each a in Actions(state) dov ← Min(v, Max-Value(Result(s,a), α, β) if v ≤ α then return vβ← Min(β,v)return v  
 Move OrderThe efficiency of alpha-beta pruning strongly depends on the order in which moves are evaluated, i.e., if we do the best moves first, the search is pruned a great deal. If the moves are ordered properly, alpha-beta pruning requires O(bm/2) nodes insteadof O(bm) for Minimax:u  The branching factor is effectively sqrt(b) instead of b, and the searchcan be twice as deep.Possibilities: Simple ordering functions, use moves that worked well before, analyzesub-games.  
 Imperfect DecisionsEven Minimax with alpha-beta pruning is impractical for real games, i.e., chess. Because time is limited, we need to cut off search at some point.One strategy is that when search is cut off at a node, use a heuristic evaluationfunction to estimate the utility at that node, and use its value in the Minimax algorithm.We may also replace the terminal test by a heuristic cut-off test.In some states it is better to look deeper in the search tree than from other states.  
 Evaluation FunctionsThe evaluation function should order the terminal states in the same way as does the utility function, wins are better than draws, draws are better than losses.They should be fast.For non-terminal states, they should be correlated with the actual chances of winning. They are often based on features of the game:u  Example – chess – Material values of pieces, analysis of positions. Could be a weighted sum.  
 Cut-off FunctionPossibilities:u  u u Do Iterative Deepening until time runs out.Cut-off search when the positions become quiescent – not much difference in values of successor states.Singular extension – if one move seems better than the others, allow a deeper search from that move.Watch out for horizon effect – temporary delaying tactics may push a bad move's effect past the horizon – after the cut-off, so the causal move looks better.  
 Look-up TablesFor certain limited situations in a game it's possible to pre-compute the best path and just look it up in a table and avoid any searching.Examples:u  Opening moves in chess (book moves) u  End games in chess  
 Stochastic GamesStochastic games are ones that include an element of chance – a dice roll, shuffled card deck, coin flips.Backgammon is a common example.The game tree in a stochastic games includes Chance nodes in addition to MAX and MIN nodes.The branches leading from a chance node denote the various possible random outcomes and are labeled with the corresponding probabilities.  
 Backgammon   
 Backgammon Search Tree   
 Expecti-MinimaxWe can use Minimax to search for optimal moves.MAX and MIN nodes work the same way.The difference is that the Minimax value for a Chance node is the sum of the valuesfor all outcomes, weighted by the probabilities – the expected outcome for the choice.  
 Evaluation FunctionsAs the search tree may be too large, we can cut off the search at some point and apply an evaluation function to the cut-off nodes.However, the Minimax algorithm is sensitive to the scale of the values given by the evaluation function.If f is an evaluation function, f and 10 * f, may give different results!The evaluation function must be positive linear transformation of the probability of winning from a position.  
 Example   
 Alpha-beta PruningSince the search space is even larger (due to the Chance nodes), we could use alpha- beta pruning, but there must be a way to put bounds on the possible value of the utility function for the cut-off nodes.Then, we can place an upper bound on the value of a Chance node without looking at all its children.An alternative is to do a Monte-Carlo simulation to evaluate a position. Do alpha-beta search.When it needs to evaluate a position, run many simulations.  
 Partially Observable GamesWhen a player only has partial information about the state of the game, e.g., he knows where his pieces are, but not his opponents, he can search for a solution by using a belief state.The belief state would represent all logically possible board sequences based on the percept sequence.To check for win, there must be a winning node for every possible legal future percept sequence.The general And-Or search algorithm can be applied to belief states.  
 Card GamesIn card games, all the randomness occurs up front, when the cards are shuffled.The game tree would begin with a Chance node with a huge number of children (onefor each possible ordering), making most algorithms intractable.An alternative is to take a random sample of N deals, evaluate them, and take the average of their values (or a weighted average if more information is known) – Averaging over clairvoyance.argmax 1∑N Minimax(Result(s,a)) aN i=1 i   