 Constraint Satisfaction ProblemsStates are represented by a factored representation, not an atomic representation. Each state has a state of variables.Each variable can take on one value.There is a set of constraints that restricts the values that the variables may take on. Constraints may involve a single variable, multiple variables, or all the variables inthe problem.Can be thought of as a search problem – the solution is the set of assignments, and theinitial state is empty set.  
 DefinitionA constraint satisfaction problem consists of three components, X, D, and C:X is a set of variables {X1, ..., Xn}.D is a set of domains, {D , ..., D }, one for each variable.C is a set of constraints that specify allowable combinations of values.u  u  u 1n  
 ExamplesMap Coloring:l  No two adjoining states can be colored with the same colorJob Scheduling:l  A series of tasks must be done.l  Each tasks takes a certain amount of time.l  There is a partial ordering to the tasks.l  There may be a number of workers available.Airport Gate Scheduling:l  Flights arrive at an airport at different times.l  Variables include number of passengers, turn-around time, schedules.Cryptarithmetic problems.  
 Map Coloring: Australia   
 Map Coloring: AustraliaSuppose that you have three colors: red, green, and blue.Color the regions of Australia so that no two adjoining regions are the same color.X = { WA, NT, Q, NSW, V, SA, T }Di = { red, green, blue }C = { SA ≠ WA, SA ≠ NT, SA ≠ Q, SA ≠ NSW, SA ≠ V, WA ≠ NT, NT ≠ Q, Q ≠ NSW,NSW ≠ V }.  
 Constraint Graph   
 ConstraintsConstraints are (mathematically) a relation among the variables.Constraints may be listed explicitly, as tuples, or defined by a mathematical function,e.g., < for numbers.A unary constraint restricts the values of one variable.A binary constraint relates two variables.A global constraint relates an arbitrary number of variables.  
 AssignmentsEach state in a CSP is denoted by an assignment of values to the variables.An assignment is consistent if it does not violate any constraints.A complete assignment is one in which every variable is given a value, otherwise it isa partial assignment.  
 VariationsSimple CSP problems have discrete, finite domains. A discrete domain could be infinite:l  This would require a constraint language to specify constraints,l  Simply listing tuples would not work.Common problems involve linear constraints on integer variables.No algorithm exists for solving general nonlinear constraints on integer variables. Other real-world CSPs have continuous domains.Linear programming may be effective for these.  
 Cryptarithmetic  TWO+ TWO----- FOUREach letter represents a distinct number, so that the addition works properly. There are three carries in addition to the letter variables:O + O = R + 10 * C1C1 +W+W=U+10*C2 C2 +T+T=O+10*C3 C3 = F  
 Constraint Hypergraph   
 Alldiff ConstraintThe Alldiff constraint is a common constraint in CSPs:l  It simply means that all variables must have distinct values. l  It is a global constraint.The hypergraph for the cryparithmetic problem shows the Alldiff constraint reduced to a set of binary constraints.  
 Preference ConstraintsMany CSPs also contain preference constraints indicating which solutions are preferred:l  Example: A professor prefers to teach afternoon classes.Constraint optimization methods are used to find optimal solutions for CSP withpreference constraints.  
 Constraint PropagationWe assume that we represent the CSP as a graph:l  All constraints (other than unary constraints) have been reduced to binaryconstraints by the addition of auxiliary variables.A single variable is node-consistent if all values in the variable's domain satisfy thevariable's unary constraints.Two variables, xi and xj, are arc-consistent if for every value in the current domain Dithere is some value in Dj that satisfies the binary constraint on the arc (Xi, Xj). A network is arc-consistent if every variable is arc-consistent with every othervariable.  
 AC-3 Algorithminputs: csp, a binary CSP with components (X, D, C)while queue is not empty do(Xi, Xj) ← Remove-First(queue) (Xi, Xj) ← Remove-First(queue) if Revise(csp, Xi, Xj) thenif size of Di = 0 then return falsefor each Xk in Xi.Neighbors – {Xj} doadd (Xk, Xi) to queue  psc ni scra eht lla yllaitini ,scra fo eueuq a ,eueuq :selbairav lacol
 AC-3 Algorithm (cont'd)revised ← falsefunction Revise(csp, Xi, Xj) returns true iff we revise the domain of Xirevised ← false delete x from Difor each x in Di doif no value y in Dj allows (x,y) to satisfy the constraint between Xi and Xj thendelete x from Di  
 Checking the consistency of an arc requires O(d2) time where d is the maximum sizeComplexity of AC-3Checking the consistency of an arc requires O(d2) time where d is the maximum size of a domain.The running time for AC-3 is O(cd3) where c is the number of constraints as each arc  3-CA fo ytixelpmoC
 Example: Arc ConsistencyWe can write the constraint explicitly as:We can write the constraint explicitly as:<(X,Y), {(0,0), (1,1), (2,4), (3,9)}>To make X arc-consistent with respect to Y, we reduce X's domain to {0,1,2,3}. To make Y arc-consistent with respect to X, we reduce Y's domain to {0,1,4,9}.  
 Constraint Propagation (cont'd)A two variable set {Xi, Xj} is path-consistent with respect to a third variable,Xj Xmthere is an assignment to X that s=atbi}sfcieosntshisetecnotnwstritahintthseocno{nXstr,aXint}s aond{{XX, X }, m imimjThink of looking at the path from Xi to Xj , Xj}. Xjassignment to those variable, a consistent wasistihgnment may be made to anyXmA CSP is strongly k-consistent if it is k-consistent, k-1 consistent, k-2 consistent, ...  ,fi ,
 Example: Path Consistencyl { WA = red, SA = blue }, andl  { WA = blue, SA = red }.BNeocwa{ucsoWenAtshide=reebr licusoenl,oSriAvnag=liNdreTcdhw}oh.icicehfoisr aNdTja, cweentetloimbiontaht.e both possible assignments andNow consider coloring NT which is adjacent to both. end up with no assignments.end up with no assignments. Hence there is no solution.  
 Global Constraintsefficient than the general-purpose ones:l RFeomr eoxvaemanpyle,vtaoridabealel winitheAcloldnisftfra(ainllt vthaaritahbalessahsaivnegldeitsotnindcot mvaliunes):l Remove any variable in the constraint that has a singleton domain avnardiadbellest.e that variable's value from the domains of the otherl  Whenever a variable becomes single-valued, do the same thing.l   
 Atmost constraintAtmost constraint: The sum of the values of a set of variables is at most a certain value, e.g,. number of workers available for all tasks.value, e.g,. number of workers available for all tasks. May be handled with bounds propagation.  
 We could do a standard search such as depth-first search:Backtracking Search for CSPsnumber of choices for each variable. We still may have to do search.lW  e could do a standard search such as depth-first search:l valueEsafcrhomoitvsedwomoualidn ctohoaossiegan vtoartihaabtlevarniadbwleo.uld then choose one of the l  The start state is the empty assignment.  .hcraes od ot evah yam llits eW
 Backtracking (cont'd)on for n levels, yielding a tree with n! * dn leaves, even though there are only dnpossible complete assignments.pTohsesipbrloebcleompislettheaatsassisgingmnmenetnst. is commutative – it doesn't matter what order inwhich the assignments are done:The pTrhoebltermeeihsatshatbarsasnigchnmfoernetvisercyopmomssuibtalteivoerd–eirtidnoweshnic'thmthatetearsswighnamt oerndtesrtionwhich the assignments are done:l To prevent this, we consider only a single variable at each node.The tree has a branch for every possible order in which the assignments to the variables are done.  
 function Backtracking-Search(csp) returns a solution, or failure return Backtrack({}, csp)function Backtracking-Search(csp) returns a solution, or failure return Backtrack({}, csp)  
 Backtracking Search (cont'd)function Backtrack(assignment, csp) returns a solution, or failure if assignment is complete then return assignmentfunction Backtrack(assignment, csp) returns a solution, or failure if assignment is complete then return assignmentvar ← Select-Unassigned-Variable(assignment,csp)for each value in Order-Domain-Values(var,assignment,csp) doif value is consistent with assignment then add {var = value } to assignment inferences ← Inference(csp, var, value) if inferences ≠ failure thenadd inferences to assignmentresult ← Backtrack(assignment, csp) if result ≠ failure thenreturn result  
 Heuristicsl The one with the fewest number of legal values (minimum-remaining- lv alues heuristic.)When all have the same MRV, choose the variable subject to the most number of constraints (degree heuristic.)lW  hich value should be selected?Prefer the value that rules out the fewest choices for the neighboring  
 Forward Checkingvariable's neighbors.This is useful when combined with the MRV heuristic. We can do more:l  When a variable is assigned a value, the Inference procedure calls AC-3,but instead of starting with a queue with all arcs, it starts with only thela rcs from the variable to its unassigned neighbors.  
 Intelligent BacktrackingWhen you get to a variable that has an empty domain and have to backtrack, it's best tlo  backtrack to a state which can actually fix the problem:l This may not be the same as the last assignment done, but rather furtherTo do so, keep track of the set of variables that when taken together failed because  
 Local SearchLocal search algorithms (hill-climbing, simulated annealing) are effective for many CSPs.The initial state assigns values to all variables, but may not be consistent.Each move changes the state some way, in the hopes of violating fewer constraints. When no constraints are violated, a solution is found.When no constraints are violated, a solution is found.  
 Local Search: Example: 8-QueensConsider the 8-Queens problem as a CSP:l  The constraints are that no queen may be in a position to take anotherqueen.Place the queens randomly on the board (but one per column):l  Usually there are conflicts.Randomly choose a queen and move it to another space in the column – the one withthe fewest conflicts.Do this many times until a bound is reached or a solution is found.  
 Min-Conflicts Algorithmfunction Min-Conflicts(csp, max_steps) returns a solution or failure inputs: csp, a constraint satisfaction problemmax_steps, the number of steps allowed before giving up current ← an initial complete assignment for cspfor i = 1 to max_steps doif current is a solution for csp then return currentvar ← randomly chosen conflicted variable from csp.Variablesvalue ← the value v for var that minimizes Conflicts(var, v, current, csp) set var = value in currentreturn failure  
 Decomposing ProblemsOften the search space can be made much smaller by decomposing the problem into sub-problems.Ideally, the sub-problems could be solved independently:l  For example, Tasmania is separate from the mainland in Australia.Find connected components in the search graph and solve them independently.  
 Tree-Structured CSPsIf the constraint graph is a tree, it can be solved in time linear with the number of variables.Pick a node to be the root.Orient all the arcs so they point down from the root.Find a topological ordering of the nodes (a total ordering consistent with the directedarcs – each node is listed after its parent).Make the tree direct arc consistent (every node X that occurs in the ordering beforeevery node Y is arc-consistent), working backward. Choose the values in topological order.There are n arcs in a tree, so the total time is O(nd2).  
 Example   
 General CSPsIf the CSP is not tree-structured, we can still use the Tree-CSP-Solver. Consider the map of Australia:l  The constraint graph is not tree-structure, but if you delete one node, SA, along with its constraints, it becomes a tree.Therefore, fix a value for SA, and solve the remaining problem (if possible) using Tree-CSP-Solver:l  Since the choice for SA may not be correct, you must try all values for SA until a solution is found.  
 General CSPs (cont'd)We can generalize this procedure:1. Choose a subset S of the CSP's variables such that the constraint graph becomes atree after removing S and the associated constraints. S is called a cycle cutset. 2. For each possible consistent assignment to the variables in S:a. remove from the domains of the remaining variables any values that are inconsistent with the assignment.b. If the remaining CSP has a solution, return its solution combined with the assignment for the cycle cutset.If the cycle cutset has size c, the total running time is: O(dc * (n-c)d2).  
 Tree DecompositionAnother approach is to decompose the problem into a set of connected subproblems. Solve the subproblems independently and somehow combine their solutions in asolution for the original problem.A decomposition must satisfy the following conditions:u  Every variable in the original problem occurs in at least one of the subproblems.u  If two variables are connected by a constraint in the original problem, they must occur together in at least one of the subproblems.u  If a variable appears in two subproblems, it must appear in every subproblem along the path between the two.  
 Tree Decomposition (cont'd)If some subproblem has no solution, then there is no solution to the original problem. Otherwise we stitch together the solutions:l  View each subproblem as a “mega-variable” whose domain is the set of all solutions for the subproblem.l  Solve the constraints connecting the subproblems together using the Tree- CSP-Solver algorithm.  