 Bayesian Networksυ Syntaxυ Semanticsυ Parameterized Distributions  
 Bayesian NetworksA simple, graphical notation for independence assertions and hence for compact specification of full joint distributionsSyntax:λ A set of nodes, one per variableλ A directed, acyclic graph (DAG) (edges indicate direct influence) λ A conditional distribution for each node given its parents:λ P(Xi | Parents(Xi))In the simplest case, the conditional distribution is represented as a conditional probability table (CPT) given the distribution over Xi for each combination of parents.  
 ExampleThe topology of the network encodes the conditional independence assertions:  WeatherCavity    ToothacheCatchWeather is independent of the other variables.Toothache and Catch are conditionally independent given Cavity.  
 ExampleIf I'm at work, neighbor John calls to say my alarm is ringing, but neighbor Mary doesn't call. Sometimes the alarm is set off by minor earthquakes. Is the a burglary?Variables: Burglar, Earthquake, Alarm, JohnCalls, MaryCalls Network topology represents “casual” knowledge:υ A burglar can set the alarm offυ An earthquake can set the alarm off υ The alarm can cause Mary to call υ The alarm can cause John to call  
 Example (cont'd) P(B) .001 P(E) .002    BurglaryEarthquake   BE P(A|B,E) TT TF FT FF .95 .94 .29 .001   Alarm    A P(J|A) T F .90 .05  A P(M|A) T F .70 .01  JohnCallsMaryCalls    
 CompactnessA CPT for Boolean Xi with k Boolean parents has 2k rows for the combination of parent values.Each row requires one number p for Xi = true (the number for Xi = false is 1 – p)If each variable has no more then k parentsThe complete network requires O(n 2k) numbersBE AJM         i.e., grows linearly with n, vs. O(2n) for the full joint distribution For burglary net, 1 + 1 + 4 + 2 + 2 = 10 numbers (vs. 25 – 1 = 31).  
 Global SemanticsGlobal semantics define the full joint distribution as the product of the local conditional distributions:P(x1,...,xn) = Πi=1n P(xi | Parents(Xi)) e.g., P(j ^ m ^ a ^ ¬b ^ ¬e)BE AJM           
 Global SemanticsGlobal semantics define the full joint distribution as the product of the local conditional distributions:P(x1,...,xn) = Πi=1n P(xi | Parents(Xi)) e.g.,P(j^ m^a^¬b^¬e)= P(j|a) P(m|a) P(a|¬b,¬e) P(¬b) P(¬e) = 0.9 x 0.7 x 0.001 x 0.999 x 0.098BE AJM           
 Local SemanticsEach node is conditionally independent of its non-descendants given its parents:U1 UmEach node is conditionally independent of its non-descendants given its parents:            x Z1jYn Theorem: Local semantics <=> global semanticsZnj            Y1      
 Markov BlanketEach node is conditionally independent of all others given its Markov blanket: parents + children + children's parents.       U1x Z1jY1Um       Znj      Yn      
 Constructing Bayesian Networksindependence guarantees global semantics1. Choose an ordering of variables, X1,...,XnNeed a method such that a series of locally testable assertions of conditional independence guarantees global semantics1. Choose an ordering of variables, X1,...,Xn2. For i = 1 to n3.  add Xi to the network4.  select parents from X1 to Xi-1 such that P(X1| Parents(Xi)) = P(Xi|X1,...,Xi-1)  
 Example  MaryCalls JohnCalls  
 Example   P(J|M) = P(J)? No P(J|M) = P(J)?MaryCallsJohnCalls Alarm  
 Example   MaryCallsJohnCalls   BurglaryP(A|J,M) = P(A|J)? P(A|J,M) = P(A)? P(B|A,J,M) = P(B)?NoAlarm   
 Example   MaryCallsJohnCalls   Alarm   BurglaryEarthquakeP(J|M) = P(J)?P(A|J,M) = P(A|NJ)o? P(A|J,M) = P(A)? P(B|A,J,M) = P(B|A)? No P(B|A,J,M) = P(B)? NoYesP(B|A,J,M) = P(B)?P(E|B,A,J,M) = P(E|A,B)?  
 Example   MaryCallsJohnCalls   Alarm     BurglaryEarthquakeP(J|M) = P(J)? NoP(A|J,M) = P(A|NJ)o? P(A|J,M) = P(A)? P(B|A,J,M) = P(B|A)? No P(B|A,J,M) = P(B)? YesP(E|B,A,J,M) = P(E|NA)o?P(E|B,A,J,M) = P(E|A,B)N? o  
 Example (cont'd)   MaryCallsJohnCalls   Alarm     BurglaryEarthquakeAddressing conditional probabilities is hard in noncausal directions Network is less compact: 1 + 2 + 4 + 2 + 4 = 13 numbers needed  
 Example Car DiagnosisInitial evidence: car won't start.Testable variables (green), “broken, so fix it” variables (orange) Hidden variables (grey) ensure sparse structure, reduce parameters   battery agealternator brokenfanbelt broken    battery deadbatteryflatno charging         battery meterlightsno oilno gasgas gaugefuel line blockedcar won't startstarter brokendipstick       oil light  
 Compact Conditional DistributionsCPT becomes infinite with continuous-valued parent or childCPT grows exponentially with number of parentsCPT becomes infinite with continuous-valued parent or childSolution: canonical distributions that are defined compactly e.g., Boolean functionsDeterministic nodes are the simplest case: λ X = f(Parents(X)) for some function fe.g., Boolean functions  
 Noisy-Or RelationThe noisy-OR allows for uncertainty about the ability of each parent to cause the A noisy-OR relation is a generalization of the logical OR.υT Thheencoaisuya-lOrRelatlilonwsshifporbuentwceretnaitnhtey paabroeuntt tahnedacbhiliiltdy mofayeabceh ipnahriebnitetdo. cause the We make two assumptions:1) All possible causes are list (if not, use a leak node.)υ The casual relationship between the parent and child may be inhibited.We make two assumptions:1) All possible causes are list (if not, use a leak node.)  
 Compact Conditional DistributionsNoisy-Or distributions model multiple noninteracting causes 1)  Parents U1 ... Uk include all cases (can add leak node) Noisy-Or distributions model multiple noninteracting causes1)  Parents U1 ... Uk include all cases (can add leak node)       Cold Flu2) Independent failure FFMalaria P(¬Fever) probability qi for each cause aloneF 0.0P(¬Fever)1.0j F– => P(X|FU ... U , ¬U T... ¬U ) = 1 – Π 0.q91jj+1k i=1i0.1FTF0.80.2FTT0.980.02 = 0.2 x 0.1TFF0.40.6TFT0.940.06 = 0.6 x 0.1TTF0.880.12 = 0.6 x 0.2TTT0.9880.012 = 0.6 x 0.2 x 0.1           
 Hybrid (Discrete + Cont.) Networks  Subsidy?Harvest   CostBuys?  Option 2: finely parameterize canonical familiesOption 1: discretization – possible large errors, large CPTs  
 Continuous Child VariablesNeed one continuous density variable for child variable given continuous parents, for eNaecehdponsesicbolentaisnsuiogunsmdeenntstiotydvisacrrieatbelepaforerncthsild variable given continuous parents, foreach possible assignment to discrete parentsλt t,tP(oCstocstom=mco|nHiasrtvheestli=neha,rSGuabussidsiya?n=mtorduel),=e.Ng.(,ah+b σ)(c)M – = 1/(σt √2p) exp(-1/2 (c – (ath + bt))/σt)2)λ P(Cost = c | Harvest = h, Subsidy? = true) = N(ath + bt, σt)(c) – = 1/(σt √2p) exp(-1/2 (c – (ath + bt))/σt)2)  
 Discrete Variable w/ Cont. Parents– P(Buys? = true | Cost = c) = F(()((-c + m)/s)  
 Why the Probit?It's the right sort of shape.Can be viewed as a hard threshold whose location is subject to noise.The sigmoid (or logit) distribution has a similar shape but has much longer tails. ITt'hsethsiegrmigohitdsiosrut soefdshinapne.ural networks:Can be viewed as a hard threshold whose location is subject to noise.  
 SummaryBayes nets provide a natural representation for (casually induced) conditional independence.independence.Topology + CPTs = compact representation of the joint distribution. Generally easy for (non)experts to construct.Canonical distributions (e.g., noisy-OR) = compact representations of CPTs.  