 Expert SystemsAn alternative to more traditional, inference-based AI, is the notion of expert systems. Expert systems:υ Value the domain knowledge imbedded in the system over the inference procedure. υ Are often written as production systemsυ May contain probabilistic rulesυ Can use an explanation facility to explicate the reasoning usedυ Rely on expert knowledge and may involve rules, models, and cases.  
 Production Systemsυ Set of production rules – condition/action statementsυ Working memory – set of current factsυ Recognize-act cycle – Match conditions of the rules against the working memory. Those that match make up the conflict set. A conflict resolution procedure selects a rule which is fired.  
 BacktrackingA pure production does not recover from dead ends. If no production rules are enable, the system quits.Other systems allow for backtracking from previous states – restore the working memory and select a different production rule to fire.  
 Conflict ResolutionThere are different conflict resolution strategies that range from simple to complex: υ Don't allow a rule to fire again unless some fact in working memory that met the condition of the rule is changed.υ Choose the least recently used ruleυ Choose the rule whose condition most recently became true υ Choose the more specific rule  
 Examples: Haunt (Laird)Haunt was a text-based interactive adventure. It was inspired by Advent, although Haunt was a bit over-the-top, and quirky (and a bit buggy).Haunt was developed by me while I was a graduate student at Carnegie Mellon around 1980-1981.At that time, I was involved in research on rule-based systems (working with Allen Newell), and decided that I wanted to use rule-based systems to create a game (inspired by Adventure).Haunt was written in OPS-4, which in turn was written in Interlisp and it was never ported to any other machines, so I'm afraid that Haunt is really dead.I started to port Haunt to OPS-5, but quickly gave up. Haunt was the first rule-based system to have over 1000 rules and it topped out at around 1500. Because of its size, it served as an important data point in early research on building large rule-based systems.Jon Laird  
 Rete Algorithm (Forgy)The Rete algorithm is a pattern matching algorithm for implementing production rule systems:υ A network of nodes – each node (except the root) corresponds to a pattern in the condition of a ruleυ The path of the root to a leaf specifies the entire conditionυ Essentially the network is a search trieυ When facts are asserted or modified, they are propagated along the trieυ When a leaf is reached, the rule is triggered υ wikipedia.org  
 Rete Algorithm (cont'd)υ Advantages:υ Eliminates or reduces redundancy through the use of node-sharing υ Stores partial matchesυ Avoids complete re-evaluation of all facts when changes madeυ Allows for efficient retrieval of memory elements when facts are remove  
 Example - OPS5υ Production system used in the R1/Xcon expert system to configure VAXen (1970s) υ Written in LISP, then BLISSυ Uses forward-chaining algorithmυ Uses the RETE algorithm  
 OPS5 Example Rule(p Holds::Object-Ceiling{(goal ^status active ^type holds ^objid <O1>) <goal>} {(physical-object^id <O1>^weight light^at <p>^on ceiling) <object-1>}{(physical-object ^id ladder ^at <p> ^on floor) <object-2>} {(monkey ^on ladder ^holds NIL) <monkey>} -(physical-object ^on <O1>)-->(write (crlf) Grab <O1> (crlf)) (modify <object-1> ^on NIL) (modify <monkey> ^holds <O1>) (modify <goal> ^status satisfied))  
 Simple ExampleRules: υ ba -> ab υ ca -> ac υ cb -> bcWorking memory: cbaca will sort to aabcc.  
 Example – Bankruptcy and DefaultIf Earnings Trend is Negative Then there will be a loan default Else If Earnings Trend is PositiveThen there will be no loan default Else If Earnings Trend is stableThen If Current Ratio Trend is up Then there will be no loan defaultElse If Current Ratio Trend is down Then there will be loan default  
 Example - LogicForward chaining:υ If p and q, then assert(p ^ q)υ If p and p -> q, then assert(q)υ If p -> r and q -> r and p v q, then assert(r) υ Backward chaining:υ If goal(p ^ q), then add goal(p) and goal(q) υ If goal(p v q), then add goal(p)Question: What do we do about boxes?  
 Advantages of Production Systemsυ Separation of knowledge and control υ Natural mapping for certain problems υ Modularity of rulesυ Pattern-directed controlυ Possibility of heuristic control of search υ Tracing and explanationυ Possible randomnessυ Plausible model of human behavior  
 ARPA ChallengeThe ARPA Speech Understanding Research (SUR) (1971) challenge:Accept connected speech, from many cooperative speakers, in a quiet room, using a good microphone, with slight tuning/speaker, accepting 1000 words, using an artificial syntax, in a constrained task, yielding < 10% semantic error, in a few times real time, on a 100 MIPS machine.  
 Harpy (Lowerre)υ Conventional segmentation and labeling approachυ Compiled acoustic models with the lexical representation of words, syntactic production rules for sentences, and set of word boundaries into one large network (finite state machine)υ Used beam search to find the best match  
 Hearsay-II (Erman, Reddy)υ Parallel and synchronous processing for word hypothesesυ Blackboard architecture for coordinating informationυ KS: waveform analysis, extract acoustic parameters, classify acoustic segments into phonetic classes, recognize words, parse phrases, hypothesize about unknown words of syllables  
 Blackboard Architectureυ Coordinates multiple processes or knowledge sources (KS)υ Global data base of partial results, accessible by all KS.υ Each KS gets data from the blackboard, processes it, and returns the result to the blackboardυ Each KS works independently, asynchronouslyυ Possibly has a scheduler to decide who goes next  
 Expert Systemsυ Type of knowledge-intensive or strong method problem-solving υ “Knowledge is king” - Inference engine of lesser importanceυ Model of human problem solvingυ Gather knowledge from human sources – experts, books, articles, manuals  
 Advantages of Expert Systemsυ Rules sets can be modularυ Can combine knowledge from difference sources (be wary of differences) υ Can inspect reasoning process, explanation facilityυ Easy to add/delete/modify rulesυ Reason heuristicallyυ Reason stochastically  
 Use of Expert Systemsυ Interpretation – form conclusions from dataυ Prediction – give probable consequences in a give situationυ Diagnosis – determine the cause given the symptomsυ Design/Planning – find a configuration or list of steps to accomplish a goal υ Monitoring – compare current behavior to expected behavior  
 Components of an Expert Systemυ Knowledge base – set of production rules υ General knowledgeυ Case specific informationυ Inference engineυ User interface υ Knowledge base editor υ Explanation subsystem  
 Roles in Creating an Expert Systemυ Knowledge engineer υ Domain expertυ End User  
 When to Create an Expert Systemυ Expert systems are expensive to create – a considerable investment of human time and money – but relatively inexpensive to use  
 Criteriaυ The need justifies the costυ Human expertise may not be available in the field υ The problem may be solved using symbolic reasoning υ The problem domain is well-structuredυ No common sense reasoning neededυ Human experts existυ Traditional methods don't work  
 Development CycleSimilar to program development cycle: υ Define problemυ Construct prototypeυ Test/use systemυ Debug/ModifyIf necessary, start over againυ Final evaluation, alpha-testing, beta-testing, release υ Maintenance  
 Conceptual ModelsOne difference between an expert and a novice is that the expert has conceptual model(s) for organizing information and rules, that is a set of concepts that are not apparent in the data, but are a way to group together different elements and reason about them.For example, aerobic vs. anaerobic bacteria, the electrical system of a car, leaf classification for trees.  
 Expert Systems – Classic Exs.υ Mycin υ Prospector υ Dendral υ OPS5  
 Expert System ShellsAn advantage of expert systems is that one can segregate the knowledge base for a specific problem from the general system.Removing the knowledge base leaves an expert system shell that can be used for other domains, e.g., MYCIN -> EMYCIN.  
 Expert System Shells - Examplesυ EMYCIN: Shell taken from MYCIN, backward chaining, uncertainty factors, explanation facilityυ CLIPS: Public doman ESS from NASA, combines three paradigms: rule-base, object-oriented, proceduralυ JESS: Successor to CLIPS, entirely in Java, can execute Java code  
 JESSυ LISP-like notation – expressions are written as whitespace separated lists delimited by parentheses, e.g., (a b c), (+ 2 3)υ Variables are identifiers that begin with a question mark, e.g., ?colorυ Every fact has a template (something like a Java class). Fields are called slots and are unordered.  
 Template ExampleThe template construct creates templates:(deftemplate automobile  “a specific car”  (slot make)  (slot model)  (slot year (type INTEGER))  (slot color (default white)))  
 Jess (cont'd)υ To add a fact to working memory, we assert it, e.g., (assert (spicy chili)) υ To assert several facts at once, we can use the deffacts construct:(deffacts my-fact  (spicy chili)  (spicy thai)  (sweet candy))  
 Defining RulesThe defrule constructs creates a new rule:(defrule   (spicy ?x)(sweet ?x) =>   (assert (delicious ?x)))Note that the if-part is not executed, but is a pattern that is matched against the working memory.  
 Special Functionsυ The printout function is used to print out information: (printout t “I chose “ ?x “.” crlf)υ  The “t” means standard output.υ The reset function re-initializes the working memory.υ The run function cause the inference engine to start. υ (watch all) traces rule execution.  
 Forward Chaining – Data DrivenIn a forward chaining, or data driven, expert system, inference starts with the know facts, and then uses the rules to derive new facts, in the hope of reaching a particular conclusion.The search may be haphazard.Once the search finishes, the path from the start to the goal may be listed and other paths ignored.  
 Forward Chaining (cont'd)Search may be undirected if care is not taken.To direct the search along a particular set of inferences, we can put markers in the working memory along the way. Rules could be of the form:(= ?stage 1)  <other facts>=>  <stage 1 deduction>  (assert (stage 2)))which would restrict the firing of this rule to a particular stage in the inference.  
 Heuristic ControlSimilarly, heuristic control of the rules could be built in. Rules can be grouped, and only certain rules fired under given conditions by asserting the appropriate facts in the working memory (and retracting them when necessary).  
 UncertainlySome expert systems allow for uncertainty in their deductions.Both evidence and rules have uncertainly factors.The uncertainty of the facts that trigger a rule is combine with the uncertainty of the rule itself to derive the uncertainty of the conclusion.See MYCIN.  
 Model-Based ReasoningAn alternative to rule-based reasoning is model-based reasoning.Here, a model or simulation is used to test hypotheses under different conditions. The model is using a computer program whose parameters are accessible and changeable by the expert system.An example might be a computer simulation of a logic device where a faulty component may be creating an error.  
 Model-Based Reasoning (cont'd)If the observations differ from the expectations that the model provides, the parameters may be changed until the two coincide.Models may have different levels of granularity.A problem is that it must be decided beforehand what features are salient to the model and which are ignored by the model (abstraction).Models are based on a theoretical understanding of the problem.  
 Model-Based Reasoning - Exampleυ Livingstone is a model-based expert system developed at NASA to detect and isolate failures in space systems.υ It uses a hierarchical model of components.υ Each component is modelled using a finite-state machine.υ Used to model the Deep Space One spacecraft, the X-37 spaceplane, and the EO-1 satellite.  
 Case-Based Reasoningυ An alternative approach to both rule- and model-based reasoning in case-based reasoning.υ A library, or database, of previously solved cases is kept.υ The current problem is compared to the database by matching salient features. The best match or matches are used.υ The previous solution is adapted to the present case.  
 CBR (cont'd)The steps in case-bases reasoning are:υ Retrieve appropriate cases from memoryυ Modify a retrieved case to apply to the current problem υ Apply the transformed caseυ Save the new solution along with a record of success or failure  
 CBR (cont'd)Difficulties include:υ How do you match cases?υ Do the features have to be identified beforehand and indexed? υ What does similarity mean?υ Slows down past a point when cases are added.  
 CBR - ExampleARCHIE is an interactive design-aiding system for architectural design.It supports construction and evaluation of solutions.Users specify their problem descriptions and/or solution descriptions; the system retrieves and displays past designs and provides suggestions and warnings. (Kolodner)  