Knowledge RepresentationFormalization of facts about the real world l Used for reasoningAd-hoc or systematic? l ComprehensivenessCompleteness l Ease of use l Abstraction?  
CategoriesCategories and Objects (like classes in Java) l Can an object be in multiple categories? l How is the category specified?Strict definitionNatural Kind l Hierarchy of CategoriesSingle or Multiple InheritanceAbstract Categories l Abstract vs. Concrete Things  
ExamplesDefine a “triangle” l Define a “chair” l Define a “thought”  
Ways to Categorize an ObjectIdeal forms (Plato) l List of propertiesIntrinsic vs. Extrinsic l Formal definition (mathematics) l Examples  
Taxonomic HierarchyHow to categorize everything possible in an organized manner l Systematize all knowledgeExamples:Biology (Linnaeus) - Dewey Decimal System - CYC (Lenat)  
Upper Ontology of the World   
PurposeShould be applicable in any special-purpose domain l Should unify different areas of knowledgeShould handle exceptionsIs there one general purpose ontology?  
Categories (Revisited)Categories can be: - DisjointExhaustivePartition (Disjoint & Exhaustive) l Relations between CategoriesSubcategory (IsA) - PartOfPropertiesTime, Color, Size, Position  
MeasurementsProperties of ObjectsQuantitative or Qualitative (3.51 cm or “short”) l Absolute or RelativePrecise or FuzzyFix or Changable  
GroupsStructured Group (PartOf) - leg is part of a bodyUnstructured Group (BunchOf) - bunch of applesCount nouns vs. Mass nouns - aamory of aardvarks vs. butterExample:b ε Butter ^ PartOf(p,b) -> p ε Butter  
EventsSituational CalculusDiscrete Time IntervalsPredicates augment with additional argument (time)Event CalculusEvents are objects (instances of event categories) - Events are represented by fluents (propositions) - Fluents may be true at a particular timeEvents have properties: Agent, Object, Location  
Event CalculusT(f,t) – Fluent f is true at time tHappens(c,i) – Event e happens over the time interval iInitiates(e,f,t) – Event e causes fluent f to start to hold at time t l Terminates(e,f,t) – Event e causes fluent f to cease at time tClipped(f,i) – Fluent f ceases to be true at some point during time interval i l Restored(f,i) – Fluent f becomes true sometime during time interval i  
Discrete Events vs. ProcessesDiscrete events have a definite structure (sub-events)Processes or liquid events don't – a sub-event is similar to the whole event, i.e., “Flying”Similar to objects: count vs. mass nouns  
Time IntervalsMoment vs. Extended Intervals l Set of Relations between Intervals   
IdentityWhat does it mean for an object to be the same as itself?If x and y are identical (are the same thing), must they always be identical? Are they necessarily identical?What does it mean for an object to be the same, if it changes over time? (Is applet the same as applet+1?)If an object's parts are entirely replaced over time, as in the Ship of Theseus example, in what way is it the same?(From Wikipedia)  
RepresentationPropositional LogicPredicate LogicSome other logicSemantic NetworksAd-hoc Representational Schemes  
Propositional LogicIncomplete for most uses, but the simplest l Decidable  
Predicate CalculusCan represent most things easily l Semi-decidableEfficient procedures for some tasks l NP-complete in generalExamples: Many from what we've done so far  
Other LogicsModal Logic (Belief Systems)Temporal Logic (Time)Description Logics (Taxonomic Structure) l Circumscription and Default Logic (Nonmonotonicity) l Informal Reasoning- Naive Physics  
Early WorkPeirce: Existential Graphs (1909)Masterman: 100 primitive concepts, 15,000 concepts υ Wilks: Natural Language system using semantic networks υ Shapiro: Propositional calculus based semantic network υ Reference: http://www.jfsowa.com/pubs/semnet.htm  
Quillian's networkNodes correspond to word concepts with links to other concepts used to define it. υ Organized into planes, each plane a graph that defines a single meaning of a word. υ Links are associative and named, and may be multi-arcs (ors)Use to find relationships between pairs of words through graph search.  
Simple Semantic Network   
Schank's Conceptual DependencyFour primitive conceptualizations: ACT (actions), PP (objects – picture producers), AA (action modifiers or aiders), PA (picture modifiers or aiders)Fixed set of primitive actions: ATRANS, PTRANS, PROPEL, MOVE, GRASP, INGEST, EXPEL, INGEST, MTRANS, MBUILD, CONC, SPEAK, ATTEND.  
Schank (cont'd)Different kind of links (multi-arcs): actor (agent), attribute, object, recipient, donor, direction, instrumental conceptualization, causality, state of change, possessor, part υ Claim is that all knowledge can be broken down into this primitive concepts.Used to create canonical forms of natural language expressions.  
Simmon's Case Based Represent.Based on Filmore's case structure of verbs. υ Verbs are the main nodesHave actor, object, instrument, location, and time υ Captures deep structure of sentence  
Semantic Networks   
Scripts (Schank and Abelson)Used to incorporate real-world, common-sense default knowledge and to organize large amounts of information.Incorporates expected actions and elements. The actual situation may differ.Scripts have the following components: Entry conditions, Results, Props, Roles, and Scenes.Each element is represented by conceptual dep.  
Easy ExampleAmy went out to lunch. She sat at a table and called a waitress, who brought her a menu. She ordered a sandwich.  
Hard ExampleJohn visited his favorite restaurant on the way to the concert. he was pleased by the bill because he liked Mozart.  
Frames (Minsky)Frames are structured entities with named slots and attached values. Values may be procedural (think objects).Frames are related to one another.Example slots: ID, relationship to other frames, description of requirements, procedural information, default information, new instance information.Frames support class inheritance.  
Conceptual Graphs (Sowa)Two types of nodes: concepts and conceptual relations.Arcs are not labeled – a conceptual relation node appears between two concept nodes instead.Concept nodes may be concrete or abstract objects.Each graph represents a single proposition.A graph may be boxed and used as a node in another graph.  
Conceptual Graphs (cont'd)Every concept is of a unique individual of a give type.Each concept box is labeled with a type label. (:)A concept could be a specific, but unnamed individual. (#)A name is different from the object (name conceptual relation) υ A concept may be an unspecified individual (*).There is a type hierarchy.  
Conceptual Graphs: RulesThe following rules may be used to modify graphs:An exact copy may be made (copy rule).A generic marker may be replaced by an individual marker (restrict).A type may be replaced by a subtype as long as the subtype is consistent with the referent (restrict).Two graphs may be joined by a common concept (join).  
Semantic Networks as LogicSemantic Networks can be converted into logic υ Not necessarily first-order logicIf they reason about beliefsThe claim is that it is easier to manipulate semantic networksMore intuitiveOperations include join, restrict, specialize  
Belief SystemsExample:Lois Lane knows that Superman can fly. υ Superman is Clark Kent.Does Lois Lane know that Clark Kent can fly?How do we represent beliefs and mental states? υ How can we reason about beliefs?  
Modal LogicPredicate calculus is concerned with a single modality, the modality of truth υ Modal logics contain operators that take sentences as objects and can reason about themExample: KA P means “A knows P” where P is a sentence.The syntax is the same as predicate calculus except that sentences can be formedwith K  
Modal Logic SemanticsPossible World SemanticsInstead of one universe (world), there are manyWorlds are related by an accessibility relationw1 is accessible from w0 wrt modal operation KA if everything in w1 is consistent with what A knows in w0.K P is true in world w iff P is true in every world accessible from w. AExample: K [K (Superman=Clark) v K (Superman != Clark)]. Lois Clark Clark  
Example   
Example - KeySolid Arrows: K Superman Dotted Arrows: K LoisR: “The weather for tomorrow is rain.”I: “Superman's secret identity is Clark Kent.”   
Believe vs. KnowKnow = Belief + Truth  
Descriptive LogicsEvolved from semantic networks υ Retain emphasis on taxonomic structure υ Principal inference tasks:Subsumption: checking if one category is a subset of another by comparing their definitionsClassification: checking whether an object belongs to a categoryMay also check if category definitions are consistent – membership criteria are logically satisfiable  
Default LogicsNormally logic is monotonic – the addition of new facts does not invalidate existing facts.Belief systems may be nonmonotonic.Example:Birds can fly.Squeaky is a bird. υ Therefore, Squeaky can fly. υ Squeaky is a penguin. υ Penguins can't fly.  
CircumscriptionSome predicates are specified to be “as false as possible,” i.e., false for every object except for those that they are know to be true.Bird(x) and ~Abnormal1(x) -> Flies(X).Abnormal is circumscribed. 1Type of model preference logic – a sentence is entailed if it is true in all preferred models.   
Default LogicRules are given in the form:Prerequisite : Justification / ConclusionExample: Bird(x) : Flies(x) / Flies(x)which means that if Bird(x) is true and Flies(x) is consistent with the KB, then we may derived Flies(x).An extension of a default theory is the maximum set of consequences of the theory υ There can be more than one extension of the theory and they may be inconsistent with one another.  
ExampleExample:Republicans are not Pacifists. υ Quakers are Pacifists.Richard Nixon was a Republican. υ Richard Nixon was a Quaker.In Circumscription both rules are augmented with Abnormal conditions. There are two preferred models.In Default Logic, the appropriate Justification must be true. There are two extensions.  
Truth Maintenance SystemA Truth Maintenance Systems (TMS) is a KB where sentences may be retracted as well as established.If a sentence is retracted it may have a cascading effect on other sentences.The TMS needs to keep track of which sentences rely on other sentences.Just because one justification is removed, others may still remain.  