 Markov ChainFrom wikipedia.org:A Markov chain (discrete-time Markov chain or DTMC) named after Andrey Markov, is a mathematical system that undergoes transitions from one state to another on a state space. It is a random process usually characterized as memoryless: the next state depends only on the current state and not on the sequence of events that preceded it. This specific kind of “memorylessness” is called the Markov property.  
 Markov Chain: Example   
 Markov Chain: Computer ScienceIn computer science terms, a Markov Chain is a Finite State Automata (FSM) with probabilities on the edges. The nodes represent states and the edge represent transitions. There is usually a distinguished start state and there may be multiple final states.The book uses the term “first-order” Markov chain for a Markov chain in which the current state depends only on the previous state and “n-order” Markov chain where the current state depends on the previous n states.  
 Language: Definitionυ There are a number of ways to define precisely what a language is. A language may be specified by:υ  A set (possibly infinite) of sentencesυ  A set of rules called a grammar that delineates the sentencesυ  A probability distribution over a set of sentences.υ Formal languages may be defined precisely.υ A natural language (English, Spanish) may not be as definite, e.g., what sentences are grammatical?  
 N-gram Character ModelConsider text as a sequence of characters.A simple language model would be a probability distribution over the sequence of characters.For example, in one Web collection:P(“the”) = 0.027 and P(“zgq”) = 0.000000002.A sequence of length 1 is called a unigram, 2, a bigram, 3, a trigram, and n, an n- gram.A n-gram language model is defined as a Markov chain of order n-1.  
 N-gram Character Model (cont'd)For example, in a trigram model, the character would depend on the two previous characters, soP(ci | c1:i-1) = P(ci | ci-2:i-1).  
 N-Gram Character Model: UsageWe could use a trigram character model to recognize what language a piece of text is in. To do so:υ  Read in a large corpus of text in each languageυ  Count the trigrams in each textυ  Compute P(Text|Language)υ  Use Bayes' Rule to find P(Language|Text)υ  Given an unknown text, compute P(Language|Text) for all languages and choose the language with highest probability.Note that we we need P(Language) but we can fake that.  
 N-gram Word ModelsWe can do the same thing using words instead of characters, i.e., build a model of trigram words.There is a problem with using words rather than characters – what happens if a word occurs in the new text that doesn't occur in the training corpus?Its probability is zero, and so the probability for the text is also zero.A solution is to add the word '<UNK>' and use it for any unknown words. <UNK> will be given a small probability. You can estimate the probability by counting the first occurrences of words in the training corpus.  
 Text ClassificationGiven a text of some kind, decide to which predefined set of classes it belongs. Example: spam vs. non-spam, authorship attribution.This can be seen as a supervised learning problem – train on a corpus of text, test on another corpus.Decide upon a set of relevant features:υ  N-grams that are indicative of spamυ  Character level features (misspelling, use of hyphens, numbers for letters.)Use Bayes' rule.  
 Classification: Data CompressionA common technique in data compression is to build a dictionary of common subsequences and then look up a subsequence in the text. If it is in the dictionary it is replaced by its index in the dictionary.This, in effect, creates a language model.Example: Concatenate all the spam messages in the training set and compress the result. Do the same for non-spam. Given a test text, append it to the spam and compress it, and append it to the non-spam and compress it. Whichever is smaller is the right category.  
 Information RetrievalOlder systems used the Boolean keyword model. Evaluate a Boolean expression where the atoms are true if the word is in the text and false otherwise. Return the text if the value is true.Newer systems calculate a score based on selected features using a scoring function and return the texts with highest scores.  
 BM25 Scoring FunctionThe score is a linear weighted combination of scores for each word in the query. The scores are based on:υ  The frequency in which the word appears in the document (TF for term frequency), υ  The inverse document frequency (IDF) – low for words that occur in lots of texts such as 'in.'υ  The length of the document.  
 BM25 Scoring Function (cont'd)BM25(dj, q1:n)= ∑i=1,n IDF(qi) * TF(qi,dj) * (k+1)TF(qi,dj) + k*(1 – b + b * |dj|/L)Where |dj| is the length of the document, and L is the average document length. K and b are tuning parameters that are estimated by cross-validation.IDF(qi) = log( N-DF(qi) + 0.5) / (DF(qi) + 0.5))N is the number of documents.   
 Parts of Speech TaggingWe can use Markov chains, in particular, Hidden Markov Models (HMM) for parts of speech tagging. That is, given a sentence mark all the words as to which part of speech they belong to.  
 Hidden Markov ModelFrom wikipedia.org:In simpler Markov models (like a Markov chain), the state is directly visible to the observer, and therefore the state transition probabilities are the only parameters. In a hidden Markov model, the state is not directly visible, but output, dependent on the state, is visible. Each state has a probability distribution over the possible output tokens. Therefore the sequence of tokens generated by an HMM gives some information about the sequence of states.  
 Urn ProblemIn its discrete form, a hidden Markov process can be visualized as a generalization of the Urn problem (where each item from the urn is returned to the original urn before the next step). Consider this example, in a room that is not visible to an observer there is a genie. The room contains urns X1, X2, X3, ... each of which contains a known mix of balls, each ball labeled y1, y2, y3, ... . The genie chooses an urn in that room and randomly draws a ball from that urn.  
 Urn Problem (cont'd)It then puts the ball onto a conveyor belt, where the observer can observe the sequence of the balls but not the sequence of urns from which they were drawn. The genie has some procedure to choose urns; the choice of the urn for the nth ball depends only upon a random number and the choice of the urn for the (n − 1)th ball. The choice of urn does not directly depend on the urns chosen before this single previous urn.  
 Urn Problem (cont'd)The Markov process itself cannot be observed, and only the sequence of labeled balls can be observed, thus this arrangement is called a "hidden Markov process". This is illustrated by the lower part of the next diagram, where one can see that balls y1, y2, y3, y4 can be drawn at each state. Even if the observer knows the composition of the urns and has just observed a sequence of three balls, e.g. y1, y2 and y3 on the conveyor belt, the observer still cannot be sure which urn (i.e., at which state) the genie has drawn the third ball from. However, the observer can work out other information, such as the likelihood that the third ball came from each of the urns.  
 HMM Diagram x — statesy — possible observationsa — state transition probabilities b — output probabilities  
 Viterbi AlgorithmGiven a sequence of observations, the Viterbi algorithm will find the most likely sequence of states that could generate the sequence of observations.It is a dynamic programming algorithm. It maintains two 2-dimensional arrays:υ  T1[j][i] is the probability of the most likely path (from the start state) of length j that ends with state i and generates the sequence of observations up to the jth observation. υ  T2[j][i] is the state previous to state i on the most likely path of length j that ends with state i and generates the sequence of observations up to the jth observation.  
 Viterbi Algorithm (cont'd)INPUT:The observation space O={o1,o2,...,oN},The state space S={s1,s2,...,sK},A sequence of observations Y={y1,y2,...,yT} such that yt = i if theobservation at time t is oi,A transition matrix A of size K * K such that A[i][j] stores the transitionprobability of transiting from state si to state sj,An emission matrix B of size K * N such that B[i][j] stores the probability ofobserving oj from state si,An array of initial probabilities π of size K such that πi stores the probabilitythat x1 = si.OUTPUT:The most likely hidden state sequence X={x1,x2,...,xT}  
 Viterbi Algorithm (cont'd)State[] VITERBI( O, S, π, Y, A, B ) { for each state si do {T1[i,1] = πi * B[i][y1] T2[i,1] = 0}for i = 2,3,...,T do { for each state sj doT1[j,i] = maxk{(T1[k][i-1] * A[k][j] * B[j][yi])}T2[j,i] = argmaxk{(T1[k][i-1] * A[k][j] *B[j][yi])} }}zT = argmaxk{(T1[k][T])} X[T] = szTfor i = T,T-1,...,2 do {zi-1 = T2[zi][i]X[i-1] = szi-1 }return X }  
 Parts of Speech TaggingWe create a Markov Model where the states are the parts of speech, and the transitions represent the probability of one part of speech immediately following another part of speech. For example “det noun” has a high probability, and “det adv” has a very low probability.The emission matrix contains the probability that a part of speech emitted a particular word. For example “noun → dog” is much higher than “verb → dog.”  
 Finding the ProbabilitiesWe train the HMM by using a training corpus of text – sentences where the words are marked by the parts of speech. We then count:υ  The number of times a part of speech occurs at the start of a sentence,υ  The number of times one part of speech follows another part of speech,υ  The number of times a word is marked as a particular part of speech.These counts give us the initial probabilities, π, the transition matrix, A, and the emission matrix, B.  
 Parts of Speech TaggingWe then run the Viterbi algorithm on a test sentence (the sequence of observations, Y.)The result is the most likely sequence of parts of speech that can emit the sentence.There is a problem with unknown words – words that appear in the test corpus but not the training corpus.  
 Speech RecognitionFrom wikipedia.org:Modern general-purpose speech recognition systems are based on Hidden Markov Models. These are statistical models that output a sequence of symbols or quantities. HMMs are used in speech recognition because a speech signal can be viewed as a piecewise stationary signal or a short-time stationary signal. In a short time-scale (e.g., 10 milliseconds), speech can be approximated as a stationary process. Speech can be thought of as a Markov model for many stochastic purposes.  
 Speech Recognition (cont'd)Another reason why HMMs are popular is because they can be trained automatically and are simple and computationally feasible to use. In speech recognition, the hidden Markov model would output a sequence of n-dimensional real-valued vectors (with n being a small integer, such as 10), outputting one of these every 10 milliseconds. The vectors would consist of cepstral coefficients, which are obtained by taking a Fourier transform of a short time window of speech and decorrelating the spectrum using a cosine transform, then taking the first (most significant) coefficients.  
 Speech Recognition (cont'd)The hidden Markov model will tend to have in each state a statistical distribution that is a mixture of diagonal covariance Gaussians, which will give a likelihood for each observed vector. Each word, or (for more general speech recognition systems), each phoneme, will have a different output distribution; a hidden Markov model for a sequence of words or phonemes is made by concatenating the individual trained hidden Markov models for the separate words and phonemes.  