 ID3 Algorithmfunction induce_tree(example_set, Properties) beginif all entries in example_set are in the same classthen return a leaf node labeled with that class else if Properties is emptythen return leaf node labeled with disjunction of all classes in example_set else beginselect a property, P, and make it the root of the current tree; delete P from Properties;for each value, V, of P,begincreate a branch of the tree labeled with V;let partitioni be elements of example_set with values V for property P; call induce_tree(partitionv, Properties), attach result to branch Vendend end
 Watson: Overview 
 Watson: NLPWatson utilizes Natural Language Processing (NLP) technology:λ to interpret the question and extract key elements such as the answer type and relationships between entities.λ to analyze (prior to the competition) the vast amounts of unstructured text (encyclopedias, dictionaries, news articles, etc.) that may provide evidence in support of the answers to the questions.
 Watson: ParsingWatson’s NLP begins by applying a parser that converts each text sentence into a more structured form:λ a tree that shows both surface structure and deep, logical structure.For example, in the following example Jeopardy! question:λ POETS & POETRY: He was a bank clerk in the Yukon before he published “Songs of a Sourdough” in 1907The output of the parser includes, among many other things, that “published” is a verb with base form (or lemma) “publish”, subject “he”, and object “Songs of a Sourdough”.
 Watson: Feature ExtractionNext, Watson applies numerous detection rules that match patterns in the parse. These rules detect elements such as the focus of the question (the words that refer to the answer, in this case “he”), the lexical answer types (terms in the question or category that indicate what type of entity is being asked for, in this case “poet”), and the relationships between entities in either a question or a potential supporting passage.The rules for feature extraction are written in Prolog.
 Watson: Examplelemma(1, "he"). partOfSpeech(1,pronoun). lemma(2, "publish"). partOfSpeech(2,verb).lemma(3, "Songs of a Sourdough"). partOfSpeech(3,noun). subject(2,1).object(2,3).
 Watson: Rule ExampleA simplified rule for detecting the authorOf relation can be written in Prolog as follows:authorOf(Author,Composition) :-createVerb(Verb), subject(Verb,Author), author(Author), object(Verb,Composition), composition(Composition).createVerb(Verb) :-partOfSpeech(Verb,verb), lemma(Verb,VerbLemma),member(VerbLemma, ["write", "publish",...]).
 Statistical Machine TranslationThe idea behind statistical machine translation comes from information theory.A document is translated according to the probability distribution p(e|f) that a string e in the target language (for example, English) is the translation of a string f in the source language (for example, French).One approach which lends itself well to computer implementation is to apply Bayes Theorem, that is p(e|f) a p(f|e) p(e), where:λ the translation model p(f|e) is the probability that the source string is the translation of the target string,λ the language model p(e) is the probability of seeing that target language string.Finding the best translation ê is done by picking up the one that gives the highest probability:ê=argmaxeƼee* p(e|f)=argmaxeƼee* p(f|e)p(e).
 Google TranslateThe exact process is a secret, yet there are two methods commonly used in SMT that may be used by Google. One is a Bayesian algorithm that calculates the probability of a translation given a source text. Based on Bayes' theorem, the process calculates this probability considering the likelihood that the source string is the translation of the target string, and the probability of seeing the text in the language you wish to translate to. Another likely algorithm is based on a hidden Markov Model, a Markov Process with unobserved states. Hidden Markov models are especially known for their application in speech, handwriting and gesture recognition. The model itself was created by Franz Josef Och, a German computer scientist, who was the chief architect of Google Translate. He headed Google's translation effort up until last year, after his research won the DARPA contest for speed machine translation in 2003 .http://www.statisticsviews.com/details/feature/8065581/The-statistics-behind-Google-Translate.html