 Grammars and Rewrite RulesA sentence will be defined as a sequence of symbols.We have two types of symbols: Terminal symbols and non-terminal symbols.A non-terminal symbol may be replaced by a sequence of symbols. The sequence could be empty, one symbol, or more.A terminal symbol may not be replaced.A ground sentence consists of one in which all the symbols are terminals.A grammar is a set of rewrite rules that specifies what sequences may be replaced by other sequences.  
 ExampleNon-terminal symbols will be represented by upper-case letters and terminal symbols by lowercase letters.A → BCDB → bBB→bC → cCC→CD → ε (the empty string) BC → e  
 Chomsky Hierarchyυ Chomsky (1957) describes four class of grammatic formalisms that differ only in the form of rewrite rule:υ  Recursively enumerable grammars: unrestricted rules. Turing equivalentυ  Context-sensitive grammars: RHS must contain as many symbols as the LHS. Can represent anbncnυ  Context-free grammars: LHS is a single non-terminal symbol. Can represent anbn but not anbncnυ  Regular grammars: Each rule has a single non-terminal on the LHS and a terminal symbol, optionally followed by a non-terminal on the RHS. Equivalent to FSMs.  
 CYK AlgorithmThe CYK Algorithm is an algorithm for parsing probabilistic context-free grammars. It requires the grammar to be in Chomsky Normal Form: all rules are either X → word or X →Y Z.It is a dynamic programming form of a chart parser.It takes time O(n3m) and space O(n2m).  
 CYK Algorithmfunction CYK-Parse(words, grammar) returns P, a table of probabilities N ← Length(words)M ← the number of nonterminal symbols in grammarP ← an array of size [M, N, N],initially all 0/* Insert lexical rules for each word */ for i = 0 to N dofor each rule of the form (X → wordsi [p]) do P[X, i, 1] ← p  
 CYK Algorithmfor length = 2 to N dofor start = 1 to N – length + 1 do for len1 = 1 to N -1 dolen2 ← length – len1for each rule of the form(X → Y Z [p]) doP[X, start, length]← MAX(P[X, start, length]), P[Y, start, len] x P(Z, start+len1, len2] x preturn P  