 Stochastic Methods for NLPυ Probabilistic Context-Free Parsers υ Probabilistic Lexicalized Context-Free Parsers υ Hidden Markov Models – Viterbi Algorithm υ Statistical Decision-Tree Models  
 Probabilistic CFGυ 1. sent <- np, vp.υ  p(sent) = p(r1) * p(np) * p(vp). υ 2. np <- noun.υ  p(np) = p(r2) * p(noun).υ ....υ 9. noun <- dog.υ  p(noun) = p(dog).υ The probabilities are taken from a particular corpus of text.  
 Probabilistic Lexicalized CFGυ 1. sent <- np(noun), vp(verb).p(sent) = p(r1) * p(np) * p(vp) * p(verb|noun).υ υ υ 2. np <- noun.υ  p(np) = p(r2) * p(noun). υ ....υ 9. noun <- dog.υ  p(noun) = p(dog).υ Note that we've introduced the probability of a particular verb given a particular noun.  
 Markov Chainυ Discrete random process: The system is in various states and we move from state to state. The probability of moving to a particular next state (a transition) depends solely on the current state and not previous states (the Markov property).υ May be modeled by a finite state machine with probabilities on the edges.  
 Hidden Markov Modelυ Each state (or transition) may produce an output.υ The outputs are visible to the viewer, but the underlying Markov model is not.υ The problem is often to infer the path through the model given a sequence of outputs. υ The probabilities associated with the transitions are known a priori.υ There may be more than one start state. The probability of each start state may also be known.  
 Uses of HMMυ Parts of speech (POS) tagging υ Speech recognition υ Handwriting recognition υ Machine Translation υ Cryptanalysisυ Many other non-NLP applications  
 Viterbi Algorithmυ Used to find the mostly likely sequence of states (the Viterbi path) in a HMM that leads to a given sequence of observed events.υ Runs in time proportional to (number of observations) * (number of states)2.υ Can be modified if the state depends on the last n states (instead of just the last state). Take time (number of observations) * (number of states)n  
 Viterbi Algorithm - Assumptionsυ The system at any given time is in one particular state.υ There are a finite number of states.υ Transitions have an associated incremental metric.υ Events are cumulative over a path, i.e., additive in some sense.  
 Viterbi Algorithm - CodeSee: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viterbi_algorithm.  
 Uses in NLPυ Parts of speech (POS) tagging: The observations are the words of the sentences. The HMM nodes are the parts of speech.υ Speech recognition: The observations are the sound waves (after some processing). The HMM may contain the words in the text sentence, or the phonemes.  
 Statistical Decision-Tree Model SPATTER (Magerman)υ Alternative approach to CFGs.υ Uses statistical measures generated by hand annotation of large corpus of text. υ Automatically discovers disambiguation criteria for parsingυ Uses a stack decoding algorithmυ Finds one tree then uses branch-and-bound  
 Stack Decoding Algorithmυ Similar to beam search, but claims to use a stack, instead of a priority queue. υ The n best nodes (partial solutions) are kept.υ The best node is expanded and its children are put on the stack.υ The stack is then trimmed back to n nodes.  