 Learning From Examplesυ  Any component of a rational agent can be improved by learning from data.υ  The improvements and techniques used to make them depend on four factors: υ  Which component is to be improved.υ  What prior knowledge the agent already has.υ  What representation is used for the data and the component.υ  What feedback is available to learn from.  
 Example: Wumpus Worldυ  Which component?υ  What prior knowledge?υ  What representation is used for the data? The component? υ  What feedback is available?  
 Components to be Learnedυ The components of an agent include:υ  Mapping from conditions of the current state to actions.υ  Means to infer relevant properties of the world from the percept sequence.υ  Information about how the world evolves and the results of possible actions. υ  Utility information – desirability of statesυ  Desirability of actionsυ  Goals  
 Representationυ  Atomic υ  Factoredυ Feature Vectors υ  Structuredυ Propositional υ First-Order υ Semantic Networks  
 Prior Knowledgeυ Prior knowledge can have many forms:υ  World Model: automobile, computer, Wumpus world υ  Case Knowledge: medical cases, legal casesυ  Prior probability distributionυ  Set of theoriesυ  Partial semantic networkυ  Concept set  
 Types of Feedbackυ Types of learning, depending on the available feedback are:υ  Unsupervised learning: find patterns in the input, clusteringυ  Reinforcement learning: receive rewards and/or punishmentsυ  Supervised learning: Set of examples, positive and/or negativeυ  Semi-supervised learning: A few labeled examples, and a large set of unlabeled ones. Stochastic sets.  
 Ways to Learnυ  Inductive learning: Learn a general rule from a set of examples (may not logically follow.)υ  Analytic or deductive learning: Logically entail a new rule from a set of given rules. May not increase knowledge, but may speed up processing.  
 Supervised LearningSuppose that there is a function, f, that generates output y, given input x. Further suppose that we have a set of examples of f:(x1, y1), (x2, y2), ..., (xN, yN)where each yj is f(xj). Discover a function h that approximates the true function f.x and y need not be numbers.The function h is a hypothesis.The set of examples is called the training set.  
 Supervised Learning (con't)Learning is a search through the set of possible hypotheses for one that will perform well, even on new examples.To measure the accuracy of a hypothesis we try it on a test set of examples that are distinct from the training set.If f is stochastic, we may have to learn a conditional probability distribution.  
 Classification vs. RegressionIf the output is a set of finite values, e.g., sunny, cloudy, or rainy, the learning problem is called classification.It there are only two values, it Is called Boolean or binary classification.If the output is a number, e.g., tomorrow's temperature, the learning problem is called regression.  
 Complexity of Hypothesesυ Hypotheses may be simple or complex:υ  Polynomials – lower order are simplerυ  Boolean expressions – in CNF, fewer literals or variables υ  Semantic networks – graph sizeυ  Concept space – few, more abstract conceptsυ We assume we have a measure of complexity.υ We prefer the simpler hypothesis among multiple consistent ones (Ockham's razor).  
 Underfitting and OverfittingHypotheses that are too simple may underfit the data – not be very accurate. Hypotheses that are too complex may overfit the data – may be very accurate for the training set, but may not generalize well to other data.  
 Example   
 Supervised LearningSupervised learning can be done by choosing the hypothesis h* that is most probable given the data:where H is the set of hypotheses.Note that there is a trade-off between the expressiveness of a hypothesis space and the complexity of finding a good hypothesis within that space.  
 Complexity vs. FitIn general, there is a trade-off between complex hypotheses that fit the training data well and simpler hypothesis that may generalize better.How we represent hypothesis affects the space of hypothesis.Ideally, the space of hypothesis contains the true function. Such a learning problem is called realizable.  
 Learning Decision TreesA decision tree represents a function that takes as input a vector of attribute values and returns a “decision” - a single output value.We begin with a Boolean classification problem.A decision tree reaches its decision by performing a sequence of tests. Each internal node in the tree corresponds to a test of the value of one of the input attributes. Each branch is labeled with one of the possible values of that attribute.Each leaf specifies a return value.  
 Decision Tree: Example   
 Expressiveness of Dec. TreesA path from the root to a leaf can be written out as a Boolean expression (a conjunction): attr1 = val1 ^ attr2 = val2 ^ ... ^ attrn = valn.Any path that leads to a leaf with value true is a positive example.The disjunction of path expressions leading to true leaves represents all positive values of the function.Similarly, any Boolean formula (in DNF) can be expressed as a decision tree.  
 Efficiency of Decision TreesThe smaller the tree, the better.However, some problems require an exponentially large tree, e.g., the majority function where the inputs are Boolean variables and the function is true iff at least half of the variables are true.There are distinct Boolean functions, so the space of decision trees is at least that large.Searching the space for good hypothesis may be difficult.Finding the optimal decision tree is NP-complete.  
 ID3 Decision Tree AlgorithmID3 is an algorithm for constructing decision trees. It picks one attribute of the problem, divides the set of examples into subsets based on the value of that property, and recursively builds subtrees.  
 ID3υ Problem: Classify a set of instances based on their values of given properties. υ Symbolistυ Supervised learningυ Each instance is classified to a finite typeυ All instances must be known in advance (non-iterative)  
 Simple Tree Formationυ Choose a property.υ The property divides the set of examples up into subsets depending on their value of that property.υ Recursively create a sub-tree for each subset.υ Make all the sub-trees be children of the root which tests the given property.  
 Example   
 CaveatThe tree that is formed is highly dependent on the order in which the properties are chosen. The idea is to chose the most informative property first, and use that to sub- divide the space of examples. This leads to the best (smallest) tree.  
 Information TheoryEntropy is the measure of the uncertainty of a random variable. Acquisition of information corresponds to a reduction in entropy.Entropy is measured in 'bits.'A random variable with only one value has no uncertainty. Its entropy is 0. A flip of a fair coin is equally likely to be heads or tails. Its entropy is 1 bit. A fair four-sided die has 2 bits of entropy.  
 Information Theory (cont'd)If a random variable V has values vk, each with probability P(vk), its entropy is defined as:H(V) = - ∑k P(vk) log2 P(vk).We can define B(q) as the entropy of a Boolean random variable that is true with probability q:B(q) = - (q log2 q + (1-q) log2 (1-q)).  
 Information Theory (cont'd)If a training set contains p positive examples and n negative examples, the entropy of the goal attribute of the set is:H(Goal) = B(p/(p+n)).An attribute A with d distinct values divides the training set E into subsets E1, E2, ..., Ed. Each subset has pk positive examples and nk negative examples. If we choose that branch, we need an additional B(pk/(pk+nk)) bits of information to solve the problem.  
 Information Theory (cont'd)A randomly chosen example from the training set has the kth value for the attribute with probability (pk+nk)/(p+n), so the expected entropy remaining after testing attribute A is:The information gain from the attribute test of A is: Gain(A) = B(p/(p+n)) – Remainder(A).Pick the attribute with the largest information gain.  
 Decision Tree PruningOverfitting in this representation occurs when attributes that don't really contribute much to the decision are included in the tree.One technique for making the tree smaller is decision tree pruning.We create the tree and then look for tests which appear to be irrelevant – they detect noise in the data.  
 Decision Tree Pruning (cont'd)If a node splits the set into p positive and n negative examples, and p/(p+n) is about the same as for the entire set of examples, the information gain is close to 0.We can use a statistical significance test such as chi-squared to check for this (chi- squared pruning.)Irrelevant nodes are pruned from the tree.  
 Evaluating a HypothesisWe employ the stationary assumption:There is a probability distribution over examples that remains stationary over time. Each example data point (before we see it) is a random variable whose observed Each example data point (before we see it) is a random variable whose observed vSaulcuhe eisxasmamplpelse afreomindtheaptednidsetrnitbauntidonidaendticisailnlyddepisetnridbeunttedof(previous examples.  
 Evaluating a Hypothesis (cont'd)The error rate of a hypothesis is the proportion of mistakes it makes.To evaluate the error rate of a hypothesis, we test it on a set of unseen examples. One technique, called holdout cross-validation, is to split the available data into two sets: the training set and the test set.sets: the training set and the test set.The training set is used to construct or train the agent – it is the input to the learning algorithm.The test set is used to find the error rate of the agent.  
 LossIt's better to have a false negative (let spam message slip through) than to have a false positive (reject a legitimate message.)Loss, L(x,y,ŷ), is defined as the amount of utility lost by predicting h(x) = ŷL(x,y,ŷcorrect answer is f(x) = y.- Utility(result of using ŷ, when the  
 Loss (cont'd)If L(y,ŷL(spaym,ŷ), nisoisnpdaempendent of x, we can drop the x.) = 1, L( nospam, spam) = 10.This requires a probability distribution over all examples in order to compute.  