 Marriage ProblemYour the sovereign in a small kingdom.One of your jobs is to marry off the people in kingdom. There are three rules that apply.  
 Marriage RuleOnly a male and female with corresponding names, e.g., Robert and Roberta, may marry:υ Assume a one-to-one correspondence of male/female names.Marriages are between two families.The married couple leaves (town) and the remaining members of the two families are joined into big, new family:υ If the families are {Robert, Sam, Josephine} and {Roberta, John, Jack} and Robert and Roberta marry, the new family is {Sam, Josephine, John, Jack}.  
 Clone RuleYou may clone a family at any time.This creates an identical copy of the family:υ In case the family is used in a later marriage, a copy is kept intact.  
 Murder RuleThe night before a wedding, one person in a family with the same name as some one else in that family may murder the other person, i.e., remove him or her from the family.So, {Robert, Joe, Robert, Robert, Sam} may become {Robert, Joe, Sam}. Essentially this rule means that you can treat families as set.  
 GoalSince marriage is an honorable and esteemed state, the goal is to marry off everyone in a family.Thus the perfect family is the empty family.Your goal as sovereign is to create a perfect family by using the three rules.You don't need to marry off everybody in town, just create one perfect family.  
 ExampleNick, Victoria, Patricia DanielOlga, Victor, Patricia Patrick, Leo, Nick Danielle, OlegLenore, Nick Nicole  
 Social ClubA social club is really an anti-marriage club.υ There are two rules:υ Only one member of each marriageable pair are eligible members of the social club and all that are eligible are members:υ If “Patrick”s may join the club, “Patricia”s may not. υ Each family must have one member in the social club.  
 ExampleNick, Victoria, Patricia DanielOlga, Victor, Patricia Patrick, Leo, Nick Danielle, OlegLenore, Nick  
 TheoremA town has a social club if and only if the perfect family cannot be created.  
 Proof: SC → no perfect familySuppose a town has a social club.Then every family has at least one member who is in the social club.Each of the rules, marriage, clone, and murder, creates a new family which also has a member in the social club:υ Clone – obvious.υ Murder – must leave at least one person with the given name. υ Marriage – think about it.  
 Proof (cont'd)Suppose we marry, say Robert and Roberta, from two families. There are two cases:υ If Robert is not in the social club, then some other member of Robert's family must be.υ That member is in the new, joined family, so the new family has a member in the social club.υ If Robert is in the social club, then Roberta can't be, and so another member of her family is – and that person is in the new family.  
 Proof (cont'd)No matter what rule is used, the new family has a member in the social club.By induction, after n applications of the rules, the resulting family must have a member in the social club.If we could create the perfect family, then we would have a family without a member in the social club, which is a contradiction.So, we cannot create the perfect family.  
 Proof: No SC → Perfect familyThis is the hard direction.Suppose that we have a town and that it doesn't have a social club.We prove by induction on the number of excess people that we can create the perfect family.  
 Number of Excess Peopleυ If a family has zero or one members, it has 0 excess people.υ If a family has n people, where n > 1, then it has n-1 excess people.υ The number of excess people in a town is the sum of the number of excess people in all the families of the town.υ We use this as a measure in our induction proof.  
 Course-of-Values InductionWe prove the theorem by course-of-values induction.We assume that the theorem is true for all towns which have fewer than n excess people and then show it is true for a town with exactly n excess people.We begin by assuming the theorem (No Social Club → Can find the perfect family) for any town with fewer than n excess people.  
 Case 1We assume that we have a town with 0 excess people.That means that all the families have 0 excess people, and hence each family consists of zero or one person.If we have a family with zero people, that's the perfect family, and we don't have to do anything.If no family has zero people, then all families must have exactly one person.If there is a social club, everyone would have to be in it (one member of each family is everyone).Why doesn't this work?υ The town must contain a marriageable pair. υ So, marry off those two folks:υ they are the only people in their respective families and you have the perfect family.  
 Case 2We must show that the theorem is true if the town has n > 0 excess people.We have assumed that:If we have a town with fewer than n excess people, and there is no social club, we can always create the perfect family.Since there is at least one excess person (n > 0) in town, there must be a family with an excess person:υ Call him Sam.We do the following thought experiment:We create a new town, a duplicate of the first, but we remove all Sams, and we delete any families with Samanthas:υ Families with Samanthas are useless since there aren't any Sams to marry.  
 Inductive Case (cont'd)Since Sam was an excess person in at least one family, killing off all Sams lowers the number of excess people in town.We claim that there isn't a social club in the new town.If there were, adding “Samantha” to that social club would create a social club for the original town.Thus, by induction, we know that we can create the perfect family in the new town.  
 Inductive Case (cont'd)Continuing this thought experiment:We have found a set of marriages (and murders and clonings) that produces a perfect family in the new town.We perform the same acts, using the original families from the first town (all the families in the new town came from the original town, perhaps with Sam killed off). We do exactly the same set of marriages on the original families:υ The only difference is that Sam might be included in the original family.There may or may not be a “Sam” in the new family after the marriage.By induction, on the number of marriages, we end up with exactly the same families the we did in the town with “Sam,” except “Sam” might be in those families.Since we found the perfect family in the Sam-less town, we find either the perfect family, or the family with just Sam in the original town.  
 Inductive Case (cont'd)If we were able to create the perfect family (because Sam was not in any of the families we used), then we're done.Otherwise, we create a family with just Sam.Use that family to marry off all the Samanthas in town.Now consider the new town where all the Samanthas are gone and any families with Sam are deleted.Since the family with Sam has been deleted, the new town has fewer than n excess people and we can apply the induction hypothesis.Again, there's no social club:υ If there were, just add Sam for a social club for the original town.By induction we can find the perfect family.Doing the same marriages in the original town yields the perfect family there.  
 Theorem ProvedThus we can create the perfect family if and only if there's no social club in both cases.  
 Propositional CalculusRemember the resolution rule?¬P, P v Q |- QIt turns out this is an extremely useful rule all by itself.Before letting this rule loose, we need to put our formulas into clause set form.  
 Clause Set FormHere are the sets to put a formula into clause set form:Rewrite the formula into conjunctive normal form (uses only ^, v, and ¬) Push the ¬'s in as far as possible, then use distributivity to move all the v's inside of the ^'s. Propositions and negated propositions are called literals.  
 Clause Set Form (cont'd)Each conjunct becomes a set of literals – just rewrite the literals in set format, dropping the v operator (it is implied).This is called a clause and each clause is an implicit disjunction.The whole formula is taken to be a set of clauses – again, write a set of clauses, dropping the ^ operator.A clause set is an implicit conjunction.  
 Clause Set Form - ExampleConsider the formula:(p → q) v ¬(r → s).Using the rule (A → B) ≡ (¬A v B) yields: (¬p v q) v ¬(¬r v s).Pushing the ¬ inside gives: (¬p v q) v (r ^ ¬s).Using the distributive law to move the ^ outside the v yields: (¬p v q v r) ^ (¬p v q v ¬s).Putting this in clausal form gives us:{ {¬p,q,r}, {¬p,q,¬s} }.  
 Resolution RuleThe resolution for propositional logic in clausal form is straightforward:If we have two clauses, C1 and C2, where P is in C1 and ¬P is in C2, the resolvent is C1\{P} U C2\{¬P}.  
 ResolutionGiven a formula, we negate the formula and then put the result into clausal form.We then choose two clauses from the set which have complementary literals, e.g., P and ¬P, and apply the resolution rule to obtain a new clause which is then added to the set.We repeat this process until the empty clause (or contradiction is obtained).If we can derive the empty clause, the original formula is a tautology.  
 ExampleConsider the clause set:{ {N, ¬V, ¬P}, {D}, {¬O, V, ¬P}, {P, L, N}, {¬D, O}, {¬L, N}, {¬N}} 8. {¬V, ¬P} 1,79. {¬L} 6,710. {P, N} 4, 911. {O} 2, 512. {V, ¬P} 3,1113. {¬P} 8,1214. {N} 10, 1315. {} 7, 14  
 Soundness and CompletenessResolution is both sound (if you can prove it, it's true) and complete (if it's true, you can prove it).How do we know resolution is sound and complete?We proved a theorem showing that.  
 ProofA literal is a person. A positive literal is a male and a negative literal is a female. There is a one-to-one correspondence between literals and their negations.A clause is a family.A clause set is a town.The marriage rule is the resolution rule.The murder rules happens because clauses are sets.The clone rule occurs because we keep copies of old clauses.The perfect family is the empty clause, or false.If we can create the perfect family, then we can derive the empty clause from the clause set.The social club is an interpretation that satisfies the clause set.That is, each literal or its negation is in the set, i.e., is true.Each clause has at least one literal which is true, so each clause is true as a clause is a disjunction. So, the set is satisfiable.  
 Proof (finished)The theorem is “There is a social club if and only if the perfect family cannot be created,” or conversely, “You can create the perfect family iff there is no social club.” Which means “you can derive a contradiction iff the formula is unsatisfiable, hence its negative is a tautology.”Thus resolution is sound and complete.  