 Topics include: υ Visionυ Image Acquistion υ Smoothingυ Edge Detection υ Region Detection υ Object RecognitionPerception
 Perception: Usesυ Robot navigationυ Autonomous vehiclesυ Facial Recognitionυ Object Reconstructionυ Information Acquisition from pictures
 Perception: Difficultiesυ Noisy imagesυ Complicated imagesυ Ambiguous visual cues (lighting, shadows) υ Partial visionυ May require real world knowledgeυ Many contain irrelevant information
 Tasksυ Feature extraction: simple computations applied to sensor observations υ Recognition: draw distinctions among the objects encountered based on visual and other informationυ Reconstruction: build a geometric model of the world from a set of images
 Basic Approachesυ Feature Extractionυ Detect some small number of features in sensory input and pass them to their agent programυ Agent program will combine features with other informationυ “Bottom up”υ Model Basedυ Sensory stimulus is used to reconstruct a model of the worldυ Start with a function that maps from a state of the world to a stimulus υ “Top down”
 Comp. Graphics vs. PerceptionComputer Graphics and Perception are inverses of one another: υ Computer graphics: Generating an image from internal representationυ S = g(W)υ Generating S from g and a real or imaginary world W is accomplished by computer graphicsυ Perception: Discerning the representation given the image. υ W = g-1(S)υ But we cannot recover all aspects of the world from the image (cannot see around corners).Similar to language generation vs. language understanding.
 Image Formation - HumanImage sensors gather light scattered from objects in a scene and create a two- dimensional image.Human Eye:υ Rods are responsible for vision at low light levels (scotopic vision). They do not mediate color vision, and have a low spatial acuity.υ Cones are active at higher light levels (photopic vision), are capable of color vision and are responsible for high spatial acuity. There are 3 types of cones which we will refer to as the short-wavelength sensitive cones, the middle- wavelength sensitive cones and the long-wavelength sensitive cones or S-cone, M-cones, and L-cones for short.https://www.cis.rit.edu/people/faculty/montag/vandplite/pages/chap_9/ch9p1.html
 Image Formation - ArtificialImage plane:υ Film covered with silver halides υ Photosensitive pixels:υ CMOS or CCD devicesυ Produces a signal whose strength depends on the wavelength of the photonυ Output is the sum of all the effects due to photons observed during a time windowυ Pixel values can be: binary, gray scale, color, or multimodal (many different wavelengths: IR, UV, SAR, etc)
 Pinhole CameraPinhole is small so that photons from the same spot in the scene arrive at approximately the same point in the image plane yielding a focused picture. 
 Perspective ProjectionIf f if the distance from the pinhole to the image plane, and (X,Y,Z) are the coordinates of the point,-x/f = X/Z, -y/f = Y/Z → x = -fX/Z, y = -fY/Z.The image is inverted, but left-right and up-down compared to the senece Distant objects look small.Parallel lines converge to a point on the horizon (parallax).A line can be described as (Xo + λU, Y0 + λV, Z0 + λW) with λ varying between -∞ and +∞.The projection of a point P from this line onto the image plane is: (f(Xo +λU/Z0 +λW),f(Y0+λV/Z0 +λW)).As λ→∞ this becomes p∞ = (f U/W, f V/W), the vanishing point.
 LensA small pinhole is need to keep the image in focus.The smaller the pinhole, the fewer photons that get through, leaving a darker image.Keeping the pinhole open a longer time leads to image blur.Alternatively, a lens can be used to gather sufficient light while keeping the image in focus.Lens system have a limited field of depth:υ The can focus light only from points that lie within a range of depths centered around a focal plane.υ Objects outside that range will be out of focus.
 Scaled Orthographic ProjectionSpots on a distant leopard may look small because the leopard is far away. Two spots that are next to each other will have about the same size.This is because the difference in distance to the spots is small compared to the distance to them.We model this effect with scaled orthographic projection:λ If the depth Z of points on the object varies within some range Z0 + Δ Z, with ΔZ << Z0, then the perspective scaling factor f/Z ~ s = f/Z0.
 Light and ShadingThe brightness of a pixel in an image is a function of the brightness of the surface patch in the scene that projects to the pixel.We assume a linear model.There are three main causes of varying brightness in images:υ Overall intensity of the lightυ Different points may reflect more or less of the light (texture and markings) υ Surface patches at different angles to the light reflect differently (shading)A diffuse surface patch illuminated by a distant point light will reflect some fraction of the light it collects. The fraction is called diffuse albedo.Lambert's cosine law states that the brightness of a diffuse patch is given by:I=ρI0 cosΘWhere ρ is the diffuse albedo, I0 is the intensity of the light, and Θ is the angle between the light source direction and the surface normal.
 ColorThe principle of trichromacy states that for any spectral energy density, it is possible to construct another spectral energy density consisting of a mixture of just three colors – usually red, green, and blue – such that a human can't tell the difference between the two.Each surface can be modeled with three albedos with three R/G/B intensities. Each light source can be measured for three intensities.
 Image AcquistionI(x,y,t) is the intensity at (x,y) at time t.A CCD camera has approximately 1,000,000 pixels.Human eyes have approximately 240,000,000 “pixels” i.e. 0.25 terabits / second
 Image Acquistion: Example 
 Image Acquistion: Example 
 Image ProcessingImage processing operations often apply a function to an image and the result is another imageυ “Enhance the image” in some fashionυ Smoothingυ Histogram equalizationυ Edge detectionImage processing operations can be done in either the spatial domain or the frequency domain
 Image Processing: Example 
 Image Processing: Example 
 Image ProcessingImage data can be represented in a spatial domain or a frequency domain. The transformation from the spatial domain to the frequency domain is accomplished by the Fourier Transform.By transforming image data to the frequency domain, it is often less computationally demanding to perform image processing operations. 
 Fourier TransformA wave can be represented as the weighted sum of sine waves of different frequencies: 
 Frequency Filtersυ Low Pass Filter: Allows low frequencies to passυ High Pass Filter: Allows high frequencies to passυ Band Pass Filter: Allows frequencies in a given range to pass υ Notch Filter: Suppresses frequencies in a range (attenuate) υ High frequencies are more noisyυ Similar to the “salt and pepper” fleck on a TVυ Use a low pass filter to remove the high frequencies from an image υ Convert image back to spatial domainυ Result is a “smoothed image”Image enhancement can be done with high pass filters and amplifying the filter function resulting in sharper edges.Transforming images to the frequency domain was (and is still) done to improve computational efficiency.
 Frequency Filter: Example  
 Spatial Transformat'n: SmoothingStatistical fluctuations of measurement create inaccuracies in the image: noise. Noise can be modeled with a Gaussian probability distribution, with each pixel the independent of its neighbors.One way to smooth an image (reduce noise) is assign a value to a pixel which is the average of its neighbors.Closer neighbors should have a stronger effect than more distant neighbors on a pixel.One technique to accomplish this is the Gaussian filter.
 Gaussian FilterThe Gaussian function with standard deviation σ and mean 0 is:The application of the Gaussian filter replaces the intensity I(x0,y0) with the sum, over all (x,y) pixels, of I(x,y) Nσ (d), where d is the distance from (x0,y0) to (x,y). This kind of weighted sum is called a convolution of the two functions f and g (denoted f * g), when we have:The smoothing function is achieved by convolving the image with the Gaussian, I * N σ.
 Gaussian Filter: Example 0-10-14-10-10    5050150505015050150150   -22.2-50 – 50 + 200 – 150 – 150 = -200/9 = -22.2
 Edge DetectionEdges are straight lines or curves across which there is a significant change in image brightness.By finding edges, we can reduce a large, messy image to a more compact, abstract representation.
 Edge Detection: Example  
 Edge Detection: AlgorithmTo find sharp changes in brightness, differentiate the image and look for places where I'(x) is large.We can optimize the computation by combining smoothing with edge detection: It is a theorem that for any functions f and g, the derivative of the convolution (f * g)', is equal to the convolution of the derivative, f * (g').Rather than smoothing the image and then differentiating, we can just convolve the image with the derivative of the smoothing function, N'σ.We mark as edges those peaks in the response that are above some threshold. Technically, in two dimensions, an edge point is one in which the gradient magnitude is a local maximum along the direction of the gradient, and the gradient magnitude is above a suitable threshold.
 Other Useful FeaturesOther useful features in image processing are:υ Texture: A spatially repeating pattern on a surface that can be sensed visually. υ Optical flow: When an object in a video is moving, or when the camera is moving relative to an object, the resulting apparent motion in the image.
 Image SegmentationSegmentation is the process of breaking an image down into regions of similar pixels.Within a region, the attributes of the pixels (brightness, color, texture) should var relatively little.There are three approaches to finding regions:υ Focus on detecting the boundaries of the region (classification) υ Grouping together pixels with similar properties (clustering) υ Contour tracing
 Boundary DetectionWe can compute the probability that there is a boundary curve at a pixel with a given orientation by looking at features of pixels in the local neighborhood. One approach is to denote features based on differences in histograms of brightness, color, and texture values measured in two area, and then training a classifier to recognize a boundary point.Boundaries detected by this technique turn out to be significantly better than those found by simple edge-detection techniques.Problems:υ Boundaries aren't guaranteed to form closed curvesυ Uses only local context and doesn't use global consistency constraints.
 ClusteringCreate a graph where the vertices are the pixels, and the edges connections between pixels.The weight of an edge is based on the similarity of the values of various properties of the pixels.Partitions that minimize a normalized cut criterion are found: mimimize the sum of the weights of connections across the groups of pixels and maximize the sum of the weights of connections within the groups.
 Contour TracingConnected Component AnalysisWhen can we say that 2 pixels are neighbors?In general, a connected component is a set of black pixels, P, such that for every pair of pixels pi and pj in P, there exists a sequence of pixels pi, ..., pj such that:υ All pixels in the sequence are in the set P i.e. are black, and υ Every 2 pixels that are adjacent in the sequence are "neighbors"
 Contour Tracing: Example8-connected regionnot 8-connected region4-connected regions
 Object RecognitionHow do you recognize that the image is a baseball? A person's face? A cat? General technique:υ Sweep a round window of fixed size over the imageυ Compute the features of the image inside the window (often creating a histogram of values)υ Feed the results to a classifier algorithm.Usual problems: υ Orientationυ Shadows υ Illumination changes υ Partial visiblityFeatures can be brightness, color, texture, gradient orientations. Can correct for shadows and illumination changes.Repeat the sweep over larger and smaller versions of the image. Post-process the different responses across scale and locations.
 Appearance ChangesVarious problems can effect feature evaluation:υ Foreshortening: pattern viewed at a slant.υ Aspect: object looks different from different directions.υ Occlusion: parts are hidden from some viewing directions.υ Deformation: internal degrees of freedom of the object change its appearance.
 Local Orientation HistogramLocal orientation histograms are a powerful feature for recognizing even quite complex objects.On the left, an image of a pedestrian.On the center left, local orientation histograms for patches.We then apply a classifier such as a support vector machine to find the weights of each histogram that separate the positive examples of pedestrians from non- pedestrians.We see that the positively weighted components look like the outline of a person.The negative components are less clear; they represent all the patterns that are not pedestrians.Figure from Dalal and Triggs (2005) c IEEE.
 Object Detection
 Object Recognition      
 2-D Image to 3-D ReconstructionThe following algorithm, due to Waltz, based on the work of Huffman and Clowes, can be used to label the edges of an image to denote how the image represents a three dimensional object.Edges are of three types:υ Concave edges are produced by two adjacent touching surfaces which produce a concave (less than 180°) depth change.υ Convex edges are produced by two adjacent touching surfaces which produce a convex (greater than 180°) depth change.υ Occluding edges outline a surface that obstructs another surface.Concave edges in the image will be marked with a minus sign, convex edges with a plus sign ('+'), and occluding or boundary edges with a left ('←') or right ('→') arrow.
 JunctionsWe restrict (arbitrarily) vertices to be the intersection of three object faces. This gives four basic types of junctions: the L, the T, the Fork, and the Arrow. There are eighteen permissible conjunction configurations:      L types:+-+- --Forktypes: + + - - +--T types:Arrowtypes:+ + - - -+           +-     
 Labeling: ExampleA diagram must be labeled consistently, that is, when the junctions are marked, and the label of an edge must be the same for the two adjacent junctions.             ++++ -++                  
 Labeling: Counterexample       ++ ++?         ++   
 Waltz's AlgorithmDavid Waltz developed a constraint propagation algorithm for marking the edges of an image.The algorithm is a special form of relaxation in which constraints are iteratively reduced or eliminated until equilibrium is reached.