 Word ProblemConsider the following problem:υ To register, you will need either a yellow card or a note from the Dean.υ To obtain a note from the Dean you must apply to the Associate Dean.υ Yellow cards can only be obtained if you are current in your payments and are a registered student.υ Registered students are never current with their payments.Therefore, to register you will need to apply to the Associate Dean.  
 SolutionWe will use the following proposition symbols: R = Can registerN = Has note from DeanA = Applied to the Associate DeanY = Has a yellow cardC = Is current in payments S = Is a registered student  
 Problem in Propositional LogicR→YvN N→A Y→C^S S → ¬C --------- R→A  
 Natural Deduction Proof1.R→YvN Hyp. 2. N→A Hyp. 3.Y→C^S Hyp. 4. S→¬C Hyp. 5. A Hyp.  
 Natural Deduction Proof (cont'd) 6. R7. Y v NAssume →e 6,1 8. Y9. C ^ S 10. C11. S12. ¬C 13. ⊥14. A15. NAssume →e 8, 3^e1 9 ^e2 9→e 11, 4 ¬e 10, 12 ⊥e 13 Assume 16. A17. A 18.R→A→e 15,2ve 7, 8-14, 15-16 →i 6-17  
 Resolution ProofAppend negated conclusion to hypotheses:R→YvN ^N→A^Y→C^S ^ S → ¬C^ ¬(R → A)Put into clausal form:{{¬R, Y, N}, {¬N, A}, {¬Y, C}, {¬Y, S}, {¬S, ¬C}, {R}, {¬A}}  
 Resolution Proof (cont'd)1.  {¬R, Y, N}2.  {¬N, A}3.  {¬Y, C}4.  {¬Y, S}5. {¬S, ¬C}6. {R}7. {¬A}8. {¬N} 7,2 9. {Y,N} 6,1 10. {Y} 8,9 11. {C} 10,3 12. {¬S} 11,5 13. {¬Y} 12,4 14. □ 13,10  
 Davis-Putnam ProcedureNote: We want to prove the validity of the proposition.We will use DPLL as a refutation procedure.As in resolution, we add the negated conclusion to the set of hypothesis. We will then show that the result in unsatisfiable.Thus the original formula is valid.  
 Davis-Putnam (cont'd)1.  {¬R, Y, N}2.  {¬N, A}3.  {¬Y, C}4.  {¬Y, S}5.  {¬S, ¬C}6.  {R}7.  {¬A}6 is a unit clause, so R ← true.7 is a unit clause, so A ← false.2 becomes {¬N}, so N ← false.1 becomes {Y}, so Y ← true.4 becomes {S}, so S ← true.3 becomes {C}, so C ← true.5 is unsatisfiable.Thus the clause set is unsatisfiable, and the original formula is valid.  
 Semantic TableauA semantic tableau, 𝓣, is a tree each node of which is labeled with a set of formulas. Initially 𝓣 consists of a single node, the root, labeled with the singleton set {A}. The tableau is built inductively by choosing an unmarked leaf l labeled with a set of formulas U(l), and applying one of the following rules.The construction terminates when all the leaves are marked  ́ or ☉.  
 Semantic Tableau (cont'd)υ  If U(l) is a set of literals, check if there is a complementary pair of literals in U(l). If so, mark the leaf closed  ́; if not, mark the leaf as open ☉.If U(l) is not a set of literals, choose a formula in U(l) which is not a literal:υ If the formula is an α-formula, create a new node l' as a child of l and label l' with U(l') = (U(l) - {α}) ∪ {α1, α2}. (In the case that α is ¬¬A1, there is no α2.)If the formula is a b-formula, create two new nodes l' and l'' as children of l. Label l' with U(l') = (U(l) - {b}) ∪ {b1}, and label l'' with U(l') = (U(l) - {b}) ∪ {b2}.υ υ   
 Semantic Tableau (cont'd)     – bλ b1λ b2¬(B1 ^ B2)¬B1¬B2B1v B2B1B2B→B2¬B1B2B1↑ B2¬B1¬B2¬(B1 ↓ B2)B1B2¬(B1 ↔ B2)¬(B1 → B2)¬(B2 → B1)B1⊕ Β2¬(B1 → B2)¬(B2 → B1)     – αλ α1λ α2¬¬A1A1A1 ^ A2A1A2¬(A1v A2)¬A1¬A2¬(A→A2)A1¬A2¬(A1↑ A2)A1A2A1 ↓ A2¬A1¬A2A1 ↔ A2A1 → A2A2 → A1¬(A1⊕ A2)A1 → A2A2 → A1                    
 Binary Decision DiagramA Binary Decision Diagram (BDD) for a formula A is a rooted directed binary acyclic graph.Each nonterminal is labeled with a proposition symbol and each leaf is labeled with a truth value.No proposition symbol appears more than once in a path from the root to a leaf.One outgoing edge is the false edge and is denoted by a dotted line; the other edge is the true edge and is denoted by a solid line.With each path from the root to a leaf is associated with an assignment to the propositional symbols of A.Assign false to the symbol if the false edge is taken from the node labeled by the symbol and assign true if the true edge is taken.  
 BDD : ReductionsThe BDD can be made more concise by applying reductions, coalescing equivalent subtrees.When no more reductions can be made, the BDD is said to be reduced.The trick is to reduce the BDD as you build it incrementally.  
 Ordered BDDThe ordered sequence of proposition symbols labeling the nodes on a path is call an ordering of the atoms.A set of orderings {O1,...,O2} is compatible iff there are not proposition symbols p, p' such that p comes before p' in O1 and p' comes before p in O2, i not equal to j.An Ordered Binary Decision Diagram (OBDD) is a BDD such that the set of orderings of the atoms of all paths is compatible.We can apply reductions in such a way that the BDD remains ordered.A formula is satisfiable iff True appears in its reduced OBDD.A formula is valid iff its OBDD is simply the node True.A formula is unsatisfiable iff its OBDD is simply the node False. A is equivalent to B if their OBDD's are identical.  
 Predicate CalculusPropositional calculus is not powerful enough to represent all the problems that we may want.Consider the following argument:All men are mortal Socrates is a man ------------------------ Socrates is mortal  
 Using Propositional CalculusRepresenting this as a propositional calculus theorem doesn't work: M: All men are mortalS: Socrates is a manN: Socrates is mortal  
 What's the ProblemThe problem is that we're not adequately representing the fact that all men are mortal. We need to quantify our predicate over a range of objects.For that reason, we need to beef up propositional calculus into a fuller representational system, predicate calculus.  
 Terms: Constants and VariablesFirst, we need to something to represent objects, such as Socrates, in the world under discussion.For that reason, we introduce constants.Constants can be people, places, numbers, concrete objects, concepts, whatever. Examples are Socrates, Bob, MyDog, four, and blue.In addition to constants, we will need variables, such as x, y, and w, which can range over a variety of objects.  
 Terms: Compound TermsConstants can represent objects directly.In predicate calculus, we have the ability to construct more complex terms, such as “Bob's father” or “the sum of 1 and 3”.To do so, we have function symbols which like functions in Java take a number of arguments and return a value.υ Examples would be father, plus.When applied to the appropriate number of arguments, these yield terms: father(Bob), plus(one,three).  
 TermsThe following are terms in predicate calculus:υ Constants, e.g., Socrates, Bob, one, threeυ Variables, e.g., x, y, wυ Function symbols applied to the appropriate number of the arguments which are terms, e.g., father(Bob), plus(one,three), square(seven)These are the only way to form terms in predicate calculus  
 Atomic SentencesIn addition to terms, we will also need predicates – expression that evaluate to true or false.The simplest kind of predicates are atomic sentences.To form an atomic sentence, we apply a predicate symbol to the appropriate number of arguments which are terms.An example of a predicate is loves which takes two arguments: υ loves(Bob,Sally) is true assuming that Bob loves Sally.  
 Examples of Atomic Sentencesυ loves (John, Susan) // John loves Susan υ parent(John, Mary) // a parent of John is Mary υ equals(three,plus(one,two)) // 3 = 1 + 2 υ isPresident(GeorgeWBush) // GWB is the Prez. υ greaterThan(three,two) υ loves(John,father(John))  
 Sentences (or Predicates)We form more complex sentences by using the Boolean operators and by using quantification.The operators are the same as for propositional calculus, ¬, ^, v, →, ↔ , ⊗. Atomic sentences are:υ Sentences (or predicates),υ The negation operator applied to a sentence is a sentence, andυ A binary Boolean operator applied to two sentences is a sentence.  
 Examples of Sentencesυ loves(John, Mary) ^ loves(Mary, John) υ parent(x,y) ^ parent(y,z) →grandparent(x,z) υ parent(x,father(x))υ witch(Glenda) v mortal(Glenda)  
 QuantificationAnother way to form sentences is by using quantification.In predicate calculus, there are two quantifiers, ∃ and ∀.∃ means “there exists” and ∀ means “for all.”Each quantifier is followed by a variable and then a sentence, e.g., ∀ x P(x). The meaning is that “for all x, P(x) is true.For example, ∀ x loves(x, father(x)) means “every x loves x's father” or in English, “everyone loves his/her father.”  
 Quantification (cont'd)∃ x loves(x, father(x)) means “someone loves his or her father.” Quantifiers may be nested, and the order is important.For example:υ ∀ x ∃ y greaterThan(y,x) means that for all x, there is a y greater than x (which is true for the reals), butυ ∃ y ∀ x greater(y,x) means that there is a (single) y greater than every x (which is not true for the reals).  
 Sentences (Definition)The following are ways to form sentences:υ An atomic sentence (a predicate symbol applied to the appropriate number of terms) is a sentenceυ Negation applied to a sentence is a sentenceυ A binary operator applied to two sentences is a sentenceυ A quantifier followed by a variable applied to a sentence is a sentenceThese are the only sentences.  
 ArityBoth function symbols and predicate symbols have a given arity, that is, that number of arguments that they take.This is similar to Java functions.Just like Java, we will try not to overload our symbols, that is, use the same name but different arities, but on occasion, we will.For example, loves(x,y) is different than loves(x,y,t) (where t is meant to be a time). Some books use subscripts to differentiate the symbols.  
 Practice SentencesWrite the following English sentences as predicate calculus sentences:υ Every body loves his/her mother.υ Every body loves somebody sometime.υ You can fool all of the people some of the time, and some of the people all of the time, but you can fool all of the people all of the time.υ Brown dogs are friendly.  
 Semantics of Predicate CalculusFor the propositional calculus, an interpretation was simply an assignment of truth values to the proposition letters of a formula.We could then evaluate whether or not the entire formula was true or false.In predicate calculus, we must consider the domain that is under discussion and this makes life more difficult.  
 Example of DomainFor example, consider the formula:∃ x ∀ y lessThanOrEqual(x,y)(there is an element less than or equal to all others)If the domain is the natural numbers, the formula is true (take x to be 0). If the domain is the reals, the formulas is false – there is no minimal element.  
 InterpretationsAny interpretation for predicate calculus must include the domain of discourse, or universe, D.That is, a non-empty set which contains the elements that the formulas will speak about.In propositional calculus we had to map each proposition symbol to a value, true or false.Since predicate symbols have arguments, we must map each to a Boolean function of the same number of arguments.  
 Mapping PredicatesA predicate symbol applied to terms, maps those terms into the values true or false. The interpretation for a predicate symbol must be a Boolean function that maps the same number of elements of D to true or false, i.e., a function from Dn to {true, false}.  
 ExampleFor example, if D is R (the reals), the predicate symbol lessThan could be mapped into the Boolean function < which maps two reals to true of false.If D is “the set of people in the world” then the predicate symbol loves could be mapped into the Boolean function loves(x,y) which is true when person x loves person y.  
 Constants and Function symbolsSimilarly, function symbols and constants must be interpreted.A function symbol maps a list of terms into another term.Since terms stand for objects in the domain of discourse, each function symbol must be mapped to a real-life function that maps a list of n elements of D into an element of D, that is, a function from Dn to D.A constant can be considered to be an 0-ary function, so each constant must be mapped to an element of D.  
 InterpretationsIn summary, an interpretation has three parts:A domain of discourse, D, which is a non-empty setEach n-ary function symbol must be mapped to a real-life function from Dn to D. Constants are mapped to elements of DEach n-ary predicate symbol is mapped to a Boolean function from Dn to {true, false}. The constants T and F are mapped to true and false, respectively.  
 Example∃ x ∀ y lessThanOrEqual(x,y) could have the following interpretation: υ D is the set of natural numbersυ lessThanOrEquals is the Boolean function ≤υ There are no function symbols or constants to interpret.Given this interpretation, the formula is true.  
 Important NoteFunction and predicate symbols are just that – symbols.Despite mnemonic names, they have no inherent meaning.We could just have well given an interpretation where lessThanOrEquals was interpreted as ≥, or as the first argument divided by the second has no remainder. All are possible interpretations.The truth value of the formula depends on the interpretation given.  
 Another ExampleConsider the formula:∀ x P(x) ^ E(x) → equals(x, two).The truth value of this formula depends on the interpretation.If the interpretation is that the domain is the integers, P(x) means that x is prime, E(x) means that x is even, two means 2, and equals is =, the formula is true.But if the interpretation is the same, but E(x) means that x > 0, the formula is false.  
 Evaluating FormulasIt's straightforward to evaluate a formula in predicate calculus if not for those pesky quantifiers:υ Replace constants by the corresponding elements in D (given the interpretation) υ Replace function symbols by their corresponding functionsυ Replace predicate symbols by their corresponding Boolean functionsThen recursively evaluate the result.  
 ExampleConsider the formula: P(a) ^ E(a) → equals(a,two), where the domain is the integers, a is 3, P means prime, E means even, two means 2, and equals is =.Then the formula is transformed to prime(3) ^ even(3) → 3 = 2, which evaluates to true. If a was 2, the formula still evaluates to true.  
 Evaluation with VariablesVariables are meant to stand for a range of values.To evaluate an expression (either a formula or term) which contains variables, we must know the element the variable represents at the moment.For this reason, we need to keep track of the current value of each variable used by what is called a binding list, symbol table, or variable assignment.Think of a symbol table in a program being executed and you won't go wrong.  
 Evaluation with a Binding ListTo evaluate an expression with quantified variables, we assume that we have an interpretation and a binding list (initially empty).The binding list records the current value of each variable, i.e., which element of the domain the variable maps to.We can now evaluate each expression recursively.  
 Evaluation with a Binding Listυ Constant: Get its value from the interpretation.υ Variable: Look up its current value in the binding list.υ Function term: Recursively evaluate the arguments, replace the function symbol by the corresponding function from the interpretation, and apply it to the arguments. υ Predicate term: Recursively evaluate the arguments, replace the predicate symbol by the corresponding function from the interpretation and apply it to the arguments.  
 Evaluation (cont'd)υ Complex predicate: Recursively evaluate the arguments and use the truth table for the operator.υ Quantified expression: To evaluate ∀ x P(x), for each element d in the domain D, add x → d to the binding list and recursively evaluate P(x).υ If binding x to every element yields true, the formula is true.υ If not, the formula is false. For ∃ x P(x), add x → d to the binding list for each d. υ If any of those assignments yields false, the formula is false.  
 Example∃ x ∀ y lessThanOrEqual(x,y) where D is the natural numbers, lessThanOrEqual is the Boolean function ≤.The main operation is the quantifier ∃ so we bind x to 0 and recursively evaluate the expression ∀ y lessThanOrEqual(x,y), then bind x to 1 and evaluate the expression, then bind x to 2, and evaluate the expression.If any binding yields true, the formula is true, else the formula is false.  
 Example (cont'd)Binding list: (x → 0).Evaluate ∀ y lessThanOrEqual(x,y).Since the main operation is ∀,we bind y to 0, and evaluate lessThanOrEqual(x,y), and then bind y to 1 and evaluate the formula, then y to 2, and evaluate, and so on.If all bindings yield true, the formula is true. If any yield false, the formula is false.  
 Example (cont'd)Binding list: (x → 0, y → 0)Evaluate lessThanOrEqual(x,y).Recursively evaluate the arguments: x and y are variables, so we look them up in the binding list. x becomes 0 as does y.The meaning of lessThanOrEqual is given by the interpretation.It is the Boolean function ≤.Thus we apply ≤ to (0,0), that is, ask is 0 ≤ 0?It is, so the formula is true.  
 Example (cont'd)Binding list: (x → 0, y → 1)Evaluate: lessThanOrEqual(x,y).Using the binding list to give the values of x and y, and the interpretation to get the meaning of lessThanOrEquals, this is 0 ≤ 1, which is true.Binding list: (x → 0, y → 2)Evaluate: lessThanOrEqual(x,y)This is also true, as is the result of binding y to any d.  
 Example (cont'd)So, the result of evaluating the expression∀ y lessThanOrEqual(x,y) with the binding list (x → 0) is true, since binding y to any value d of D yields true.Since the main operator was ∃ x, that's all we need.Binding x to one value of d (0), yields a true formula, so the whole expression is true. Note that binding x to 1, yields false (since ¬ (1 ≤ 0), but that doesn't matter.As long as binding x to one d makes the formula true, the whole expression is true.  
 Another ExampleConsider the formula:∀ x ∀ y ∃ z (lessThan(x,y)-> lessThan(x,z) ^ lessThan(z,y)).Give one interpretation that makes this formula true and one that makes it false. Evaluate the formula given one of those interpretations.  
 Satisfiability and ValidityIf a formula has no free variables, than an interpretation (or model) satisfies the formula if the formula evaluates to true given the interpretation and the (initially) empty binding list.A formula is satisfiable if there is at least one interpretation that satisfies it.A formula is valid if all interpretations satisfy it.A formula is unsatisfiable if no interpretations satisfy it.  