 Program VerificationOne way to check if a program works is to test it extensively.However, usually there are an infinite number of possible inputs, so exhaustive testing of all possible inputs is impossible.Testing can tell if you if the program won't work, but can only say that a program is likely to work.An alternative to testing is program verification.  
 Program Verification (cont'd)Program verification involves formally proving that a program works.In order to prove such a thing, we must first specify what it is that a program is supposed to do so.One way to provide a specification is to give input and output specifications. These are sentences in a formal logic (such as predicate calculus.)If the input to the program satisfies the input specification, then the output produced by the program should satisfy the output specification.  
 Program Verification (cont'd)Program verification is then proving (formally) exactly this – if the input satisfies the input specification, and the program runs (and halts in finite time), the the output satisfies the output specification.If the specifications accurately specify what the program is to do, then the program is proven correct.Proving program correctness is often difficult and may involve writing intermediate specifications for modules of the program.  
 Program Specification: ExampleSuppose we want to sort a list of numbers.The input specification is simply the the input is a list of numbers.What are the requirements on the output?First, the output should be a list of numbers that are in order (say increasing order). But that's not enough – suppose the input list is [10,7,3,5,2] and the output is [1,2,3,4,5]. The output is in order, but the program does not sort the input. The output should also be a permutation of the input.  
 Example (cont'd)Thus, the specification for a sorting program is that the output is a permutation of the input and that is in order. We can write this in a formal language, but first have to be able to represent lists.  
 List NotationIn our notation, one type of list is comma separated values, delimited by square brackets, i.e., [5,1,7,2,3].We may use variables to represent unknown quantities, i.e., [X,1,7,Y,3]. We use identifiers starting with uppercase letters for variables.We also use the notation [X|L] to indicate a list whose first element is X and the rest of the list, called the tail, is the list L. For example, if the list is [5,1,7,2,3], the first element is 5, and the tail of the list is [1,7,2,3].The empty list is written [].  
 Sorting Program SpecificationWe can now formally represent our specification of a sorting program. sort(L1,L2) means that L2 is the sorted version of L1. As we have noted, that means that L2 must be a permutation of L1, and L2 must be in order.We use perm(L1,L2) to mean the former, and inOrder(L2) to mean the latter. Thus, we can state that:perm(L1,L2) ^ inOrder(L2) → sort(L1,L2).  
 InOrder SpecificationNext, we must specify what it means for a list to be in order. Each element must be less than or equal to the element that follows it in the list. We could use iteration to specify this, but we will use recursion, for reasons that become apparent later.A recursive definition of inOrder(L) needs a base case. L could be the empty list, []. Thus, we haveinOrder([]). A one element list is also always in order, so we also have inOrder([X]).  
 InOrder Specification (cont'd)A list with two or more elements is in order if the first element is less than or equal to the second element, and then the rest of the list (including the second element) is also in order:X <= Y ^ inOrder([Y|L]) → inOrder([X,Y|L]).  
 Permutation SpecificationNext, we must specify what it means for one list to be a permutation of another list, perm(L,L1).Again, we provide a recursive specification. The base case is the empty list, so we have perm([],[]).What if the first list has at least one element, i.e.perm([X|L],L1)? Clearly X must be somewhere in L1, and the other elements of L1must be a permutation of L. So, we need another relation which says the X is in a list L1, and L2 is the same as L1, but with one instance of X removed. We call this relation contains(X,L1,L2).Thus we can write the recursive case for perm as:perm(L,L2) ^ contains(X,L1,L2)→ perm([X|L],L1).  
 Contains SpecificationFinally, we need to specify what contains means. Again, we use recursion. Here, the base case is that a list with at least one element contains its first element: contains(X, [X|L],L).If X isn't the first element, then it has to be one of the other elements of the list. Let Y be the first element of the list. The first element of the list must be in the new list (the old list without X). So,contains(X,L,L1) → contains(X,[Y|L],[Y|L1]).  
 Sorting Program Specificationperm(L,L1) ^ inOrder(L1) → sort(L,L1).inOrder([]).inOrder([X]).X <= Y ^ inOrder([Y|L]) → inOrder([X,Y|L]).perm([],[]).perm(L,L2) ^ contains(X,L1,L2)→ perm([X|L],L1).contains(X,[X|L],L).contains(X,L,L1) → contains(X,[Y|L],[Y|L1]).  
 Proving TheoremsWe can now consider a sentence such as sort([4,1,2,3],[1,2,3,4]) which means “is [1,2,3,4] a sorted version of [4,1,2,3]?” Or, more generally, sort([4,1,2,3],L) which means “is there a value of L which is sorted version of [4,1,2,3]?”We could then proceed to prove the theorem using the specification formulas as the hypotheses of the theorem and the new sentence as the conclusion. In the process of proving the second sentence we would need to exhibit a value of L, thus sorting the list.We note that the sentences in the specification are all Horn clauses.  
 PrologProlog (PROcedural LOGic) is a programming language whose lines are sentences. Prolog employs a resolution theorem prover to prove that a sentence (the goal) is entailed by the program. So, in Prolog, we could write the specification of the sort, and then ask if sort([4,1,2,3], [1,2,3,4]) is entailed by the specification. For that matter, we could ask if sort([4,1,2,3], L) is entailed. Prolog will prove that it is, and as a side-effect, find the value for L ([1,2,3,4]) that demonstrates it.  
 Prolog SyntaxIn Prolog:Sentences are written backwards, with a left arrow, e.g., head ← body.All sentences are terminated by a period (full stop).The characters “:-” are used for the left arrow (keyboard limitation).We use a comma for ^.Less than or equal is written =<, and not <=.If a sentence uses a variable only once, we don't name the variable, but use the anonymous variable, “_”, instead.  
 Sorting in Prolog - slowsortslowsort(L,L1) :- perm(L,L1), inOrder(L1).inOrder([]).inOrder([_]).inOrder([X,Y|L]) :- X =< Y, inOrder([Y|L]).perm([],[]).perm([X|L],L1) :- perm(L,L2), contains(X,L1,L2).contains(X,[X|L],L). contains(Y,[X|L],[X|L1]) :- contains(Y,L,L1).  
 Slowsort RunGNU Prolog 1.3.0By Daniel DiazCopyright (C) 1999-2007 Daniel Diaz| ?- [sort].[sort].compiling /home/simon/sort.pl for byte code.../home/simon/sort.pl compiled, 24 lines read - 3926 bytes written, 9 msyes| ?- slowsort([10,9,8,7,6,5,4,3,2,1],L). slowsort([10,9,8,7,6,5,4,3,2,1],L).L = [1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10] ?(2000 ms) yes |  
 Analysis of Sort ProgramThe Prolog program does sort a list of numbers, but not in an efficient manner. In fact, it recurses through all permutations of the first list, checks if they are in order, and then stops when it finds one that is. The running time is potentially n! if the list has n elements (exponential running time).There is no reason why we cannot write (specify) a more efficient sort in Prolog. Let's consider a Prolog specification for quicksort.  
 Quicksort in Prologqsort([],[]).qsort([X|L],L1) :- partition(X,L,L2,L3), qsort(L2,L4), qsort(L3,L5), app(L4,[X| L5],L1).partition(_,[],[],[]).partition(X,[Y|L],[Y|L1],L2) :- Y =<X, partition(X,L,L1,L2). partition(X,[Y|L],L1,[Y|L2]) :- Y > X, partition(X,L,L1,L2).app([],L,L).app([X|L],L1,[X|L2]) :- app(L,L1,L2).  
 Quicksort Runsimon@austin:~$ prologGNU Prolog 1.3.0By Daniel DiazCopyright (C) 1999-2007 Daniel Diaz | ?- [sort].[sort].compiling /home/simon/sort.pl for byte code.../home/simon/sort.pl compiled, 24 lines read - 3925 bytes written, 10 ms(4 ms) yes| ?- qsort([10,9,8,7,6,5,4,3,2,1],L). qsort([10,9,8,7,6,5,4,3,2,1],L).L = [1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10] ?  