 Bound and Free VariablesDefinition: In the formula ∀x P(x) (or ∃x P(x)), all occurrences of the variable x in the formula P(x) are said to be bound. P(x) (minus any of its subformulas of the form ∀x φ or ∃x φ) is said to be the scope of ∀x. All occurrences of a variable that is not bound by a quantifier are said to be free.Note that a variable may occur both free and bound in a formula: (∀x father(x,Fred)) ^ mother(x,Mary).  
 SubstitutionDefinition: Given a variable x, a term t, and a formula φ we define φ[t/x] to be the formula obtained by replacing each free occurrence of variable x in φ with t.Definition: Given a term t, a variable x, and a formula φ, we say that t is free for x in φ iff no free x in φ occurs in the scope of ∀y or ∃y for any variable y occurring in t.That is, if t contains a variable y, we don't want y to get captured by a quantifier (∀y) when we substitute t for x in φ. Example: φ: ∃y y > x, t: y+1, so, φ[t/x] is ∃y y > y +1.  
 Universal Rules ∀xe rule ∀xi rulet must be free for x in φ.x0 must be a “fresh” variable – one that does not occurs elsewhere in the proof.  
 Existential Rules ∃yi rule ∃ye rule where t is free for x in φ.  
 Resolution for Predicate CalculusAn alternative to natural deduction is the resolution procedure for predicate calculus. Resolution for predicate calculus is based on the resolution procedure for propositional logic, but involves variables, terms, and quantifiers.The three basic rules remain: marriage (resolution), murder (factoring), and cloning (retain a copy of each clause).Resolution for PC is a refutation procedure.  
 One Hitch - MatchingSuppose that we try to resolve the following two literals: father(John, Paul)~father(John, x).Can we resolve them?  
 One Hitch - MatchingSuppose that we try to resolve the following two literals: father(John, Paul)~father(John, x).Can we resolve them? Yes, by substituting Paul for x first. Then the literals become identical.  
 SubstitutionsIt will turn out that all variables are universally quantified, and since resolution is a refutation procedure, if we derive a contradiction after substitution, the original set of clauses was contradictory.  
 Some ComplexityBoth literals may have variables for which we can substitute terms. If there is a substitution that can be applied to both with the result being that the two literals become identical (both with different signs), then we can resolve them:P(g(x), x, z) and ~P(g(h(a)), w, f(w)).This is called unification.  
 The PlanTo prove a proposition in predicate calculus using resolution, we will: υ  Negate the conclusion and conjoin it with the hypotheses.υ  Put the resulting formula in clausal form.υ  Resolve until we derive a contradiction.  
￼Prenex Form‏)From Chang and Lee, Symbolic Logic and Mechanical Theorem Proving(Prenex form occurs when the quantifiers all occur to the left of the formula, that is a formula of the form (Q1 x1) (Q2 x2) (Q3 x3) (M), where Q1, Q2, Q3, ... are either ∀ or∃, and M is a quantifier-free formula, called the matrix.￼￼
‏)Prenex Form (cont'd￼To put a formula into prenex form, we do the following steps:1. Get rid of → and ↔ by using the equivalences F ↔G = (F → G) ^ (G → F) and F → G = ¬F v G.2. Push ¬ in to the atoms by using the equivalences ¬¬F = F, ¬(F v G) = ¬F ^ ¬G, ¬(F ^ G) = ¬F v ¬G, ¬∀xF = ∃x¬F, ¬∃xF = ∀x¬F.3. Rename bound variables if necessary.4. Move the quantifiers to the outside.￼￼
￼Moving Quantifiers to the OutsideWe use the following equivalences:υ (Q x) F(x) v G ≡ (Q x) (F(x) v G)‏, where Q is either ∀ or ∃ υ (Q x) F(x) ^ G ≡ (Q x) (F(x) ^ G‏))υ (∀ x) F(x) ^ (∀ x) H(x) ≡ (∀ x) (F(x) ^ H(x ‏))υ (∃ x) F(x) v (∃ x) H(x) ≡ (∃ x) (F(x) v H(xυ (Q1 x) F(x) v (Q2 x) H(x)‏))υ  ≡ (Q1 x) (Q2 z) (F(x) v H(zυ υ ‏))Q x)(Q z)(F(x)^H(z(≡ 12(Q x)F(x)^(Q x)H(x) 12￼￼
￼Prenex Form - Example‏))x) (∀ y) ((∃ z) (P(x,z) ^ P(y,z)) -> (∃ u) Q(x,y,u ∀(￼￼
￼Skolem Standard FormTo achieve Skolem Standard form, we do the following;υ Transform the formula into prenex normal form.υ Put the matrix into conjunctive normal form (CNF).υ Eliminate the existentially quantified variables by using Skolem functions (and ‏)constantsυ Drop the universal quantifiers as only universally quantified variables remain.￼￼
￼Skolem FunctionsConsider the formula (∀ x) (∃ y) x >= y.That is, for every x, there is some y less than x.If that's the case, we could create a function smaller(x) that, given an x, returns some number smaller than x.There are many such functions, but the formula guarantees that one exists.Consider the formula (∀ x) x >= smaller(x).These two formulas are not equivalent under an interpretation (why?) but one is ‏)?unsatisfiable iff the other is unsatisfiable (why￼￼
‏)Skolem Functions (cont'd￼We can replace each existentially quantified variable by a new Skolem function whose arguments are all the universally quantified variable to the left of its quantifier – as those are the values that the existentially quantified variable depends on.If there are no universally quantified variables to the left, we replace the variable by a function of no arguments, or a constant.Once we have no existentially quantified variables, we drop the ∀'s.￼￼
￼Skolem Normal Form - Example‏)x) (∀ y) (∀ z) (∃ u) (∀ v) (∃ w) P(x,y,z,u,w ∃(￼￼
 ExampleFor example, consider the proposition: ∃ x ∀ y y < x → ∀ y ∃ x y < x.1. Negate the theorem: ∃ x ∀ y y < x ^ ∃ y ∀ x ¬(y < x). 2a. No → to do.2b. Push the ¬ operators in. No change.3c. Rename variables if necessary:∃ x ∀ y y < x ^ ∃ u ∀ v ¬(u < v).3d. Move the quantifiers to the outside: First, we have∃ x ∃ u (∀ y y < x ^ ∀ v ¬(u < v)). Then we get∃ x ∃ u ∀ y ∀ v (y < x ^ ¬(u < v)).  
 Example (Cont'd)2e. Remove the quantifiers, first by Skolemizing the existentially quantified variables. As these have no universally quantified variables to their left, they are replaced by Skolem constants:∀ y ∀ v (y < a ^ ¬ (b < v)).Drop the universal quantifiers: y < a ^ ¬ (b < v). 2f. Put the matrix into CNF. No change.3. Write the formula in clausal form: {{y < a}, {¬(b < v)}}.  
 UnificationBefore we define the concept of a unifier we must extend our concept of substitution. A substitution can now be a set of pairs of variables and their replacements, written[t1/x1, t2/x2, ..., tn/xn].Applying a substitution to an expression (either a term or formula) means to simultaneously replace each variable (xi) with its corresponding term (ti). A substitution can never contain a pair of the form x/x.  
 Unification: ExampleFor example, if we have θ = [y/x, f(x)/y, c/z], the results of applying θ to the term P(x,y,z,w) ( θ(P(x,y,z,w))) is P(y,f(x),c,w).  
 Composition of SubstitutionsComposing two substitutions, say θ and λ, produces a new substitution, θ ∘ λ, which when applied to an expression, say P, results in the same expression as applying first θ and then λ to P. That is,(θ ∘ λ)(P) = λ(θ(P)).  
 Composition (cont'd)For example, if we think about first applying θ = [y/x, f(x)/y, c/z], then the substitution λ = [ d/x, e/y, f/w], we can see that any instance of variable x will first be replaced by y when θ is applied.This becomes e when λ is applied, so the net result is that x goes to d.The variable y would becomes f(x) which is changed to f(d) by λ, and z becomes c which is unchanged by λ.Furthermore, the variable w which is untouched by θ, is replaced by f when λ is applied. So the resulting composition θ ∘ λ = [ e/x, f(d)/y, c/z, f/w ].  
 Composition (cont'd)Formally, we can define composition of substitutions by saying that if we have θ = [t1/x1, t2/x2, ..., tn/xn].andλ = [s1/y1, s2/y2, ..., sm/ym],the composition is found by creating θ ∘ λ = [λ(t1)/x1, λ(t2)/x2, ..., λ(tn)/xn]U [si/yi | where 1 ≤ i ≤ m and yi does not occur as a variable in θ]and then removing any pairs of the form x/x.  
 UnifiersGiven a set of expressions, say E = {E1, E2, ..., En}, we say that a substitution, σ, unifies the set if the result of applying the substitution to each expression in the set yields exactly the same result:υ That is σ(E1) = σ(E2) = ... = σ(En).We call such a substitution a unifier and say that the set E is unifiable.For example:The set {R(x,y,z), R(w,w,x)} is unified by the substitution σ1 = [a/x, a/y, a/z, a/w].It is also unified by the substitution σ2 = [x/y, x/z, x/w].  
 Most General UnifierA substitution, σ, is a most general unifier (mgu) of a set of expressions E if it unifies E, and for any unifier, Ω, of E, there is a unifier, λ, such that Ω = σ ∘ λ.The idea is that σ is less specific than (technically, no more specific than) Ω, that is, we can substitute for some of the variables of σ and get Ω.There can be more than one most general unifier, but such substitutions are the same except for variable renaming.In the above example, σ2 is the mgu of the set of expressions. We can see that σ1 = σ2 ∘ [a/x].  
 MGU AlgorithmThere is a simple algorithm for finding the most general unifier of a set of expressions.First, we need to define the disagreement set of a set of expressions.This is found by (textually) finding the first symbol starting from the left that is not the same in every expression and extracting the subexpressions that begin with that symbol at that position in each expression of the set.The resulting set of subexpressions is the disagreement set.For example, the disagreement set for { P(x,y,a), P(x,f(g),b), P(x,f(g),x) } is {y, f(g)}.  
 MGU Algorithm (cont'd)The algorithm for finding the most general unifier for a set of expressions E is as follows:σ = [] (the empty substitution)while(E is not a singleton) {D = disagreement set of E;if(D contains a variable, say x, and a term, say t, that doesn't contain x) {E = [t/x](E); σ = σ ∘ [t/x]; }else return "Not unifiable"; }return σ;  
 ResolutionIf a clause, C, contains two or more literals that are unifiable by a substitution, say σ, then a factor of the clause is σ(C).If a clause, C1, contains a literal, L1, and a clause, C2, contains a literal, L2, such that L1 and ¬ L2 are unifiable by a substitution, say σ, then a binary resolution of C1 and C2 is the clause σ(C1)\{σ(L1)} U σ(C2)\{σ(L2)}.The literals, L1 and L2, are the literals resolved upon.  
 Resolution RuleA resolution of two clauses, C1 and C2, is a binary resolution of C1 or a factor of C1 and C2 or a factor of C2. The resulting clause is called the resolvent.As a simple example, consider the clause set we found previously: {{y < a}, {¬(b < v)}}. We can resolve the two clauses on their only literals with by using the mgu [ b/ y, a/v]. The result is ⊥.  
 Refinements and AdditionsThe set-of-support (SOS) strategy is based on the idea that the hypotheses of a proposed theorem are generally true (in some model), hence satisfiable.Any proof will have to make use of the literals generated by the conclusion. These clauses are referred to as the set of support.Formally, a set of support T is a subset of the clause set S where S \ T is satisfiable. Every resolution step must resolve upon at least one clause that is not from S \ T, i.e., one of the two clauses must either be from T or a derived clause.  
 Resolution StrategiesOne common strategy for applying resolution is called level saturation.Here you try to resolve every pair of clauses from the original set, thus generating a new set of clause.The next step is trying to resolve every new clause against every new clause and every original clause, generating another new set.Then try to resolve those new clauses against themselves and the previous clauses.  
 HyperrsolutionIn positive hyperresolution, one clause, called the nucleus is resolved against a group of clauses, called the electrons, or the satellites in Prover9, at each step.The nucleus must contain at least one negative literal, and electrons contain all positive literals.The result of the resolution step must contain only positive literals, i.e., all the negative literals of the nucleus must be resolved away.There is a dual strategy, called negative hyperresolution, where the nucleus must contain at least one positive literal, and the electrons contain only negative literals.  
 ParamodulationParamodulation is a way to build the equality axioms into the inference mechanism. If C1 is a clause of the form L(t) v D1 and C2 is a clause of the form r=s v D2 where t and r unify with mgu σ, we can resolve by paramodulation and obtain the resulting clause σ(L)(σ(s)) v σ(D1) v σ(D2) where σ(L)(σ(s)) means that one occurrence of σ(t) is replaced by σ(s) in L.  
￼Restrictions of ResolutionSeveral ways to restrict the possible resolutions are:υ Unit resolution – one of the two clauses resolved upon must be a unit clause (a single ‏)literalυ Input resolution – one of the two clauses resolved upon must be from the original set of clausesυ Linear resolution – after the first resolution step, one of the two clauses resolved upon must be the last clause generate.These restrictions are sound, but not complete. Why?￼￼
 SubsumptionOne strategy that is complete is subsumption.On clause subsumes another (in proposition calculus) if it is a subset of the other clause.As we are trying to obtain the empty clauses, smaller clauses are better.If a clause subsumes another clauses, that other clause may be eliminated.This works in both the forward direction (a new clause is subsumed by and old clause) and the backward direction (an old clause is subsumed by a new clause).  
 Deletion StrategyDelete any tautology or clause subsumed by another.  
￼Resolution Rule - Example‏))C1 = P(x) v P(f(y)) v R(g(y ‏)C2 = ~P(f(g(a))) v Q(b￼￼
 Resolution ProcedureResolution is sound and complete.Many of strategies used in propositional calculus resolution apply to predicate calculus (with modification).υ Level saturation is the same.υ A clause C1 subsumes a clause C2 iff there is a substitution σ such that σ(C1) ⊆ C2. The deletion strategy used this new definition of subsumption.υ Unit, input, and linear resolution are the same.  
 Other Strategies - DefinitionsDefinitions:υ A clause is called positive is it does not contain any negative literals. υ A clause is called negative if it does not contain any negative literals. υ A clause is called mixed if it is neither positive nor negative.  
 Positive HyperresolutionIn positive hyperresolution, a single step is a series of resolution steps between a nucleus, (a negative or mixed clause) and several electrons (positive clauses).The result must be a positive clause, i.e., the electrons must knock out all the negative literals in the nucleus.Example: R(x) v R(a), S(x), ~R(a) v ~S(a) -> □.  
 Negative HyperresolutionNegative Hyperresolution is just like positive hyperresolution except that the nucleus is positive or mixed and the electrons are negative clauses.  
 Set of Support ResolutionA subset T of a set of clauses S is called a set of support if S – T is satisfiable.For example, given a theorem with hypothesis and a conclusion, the hypotheses are normally satisfiable, so T could be the clauses formed by the conclusion.A set-of-support resolution is one in which both parent clauses are not from S – T. A set-of-support deduction is one where every resolution is a set-of-support resolution.  
 Automated Theorem Proversυ Otter – Argonne National Lab, McCune υ Prover9 - McCuneυ SETHEO – Technical University of Munich υ E-SETHEO - TUMυ Vampire- Manchester University, Voronkov  
 Users of Automated Thm. Provingυ Mathematical Proofυ Proof-checkingυ Program Verificationυ Question Answeringυ General Reasoningυ Combine with other Reasoning Modules  
 Horn ClausesA Horn clause is a restricted predicate calculus formula of formP1 ^P2 ^P3 ^...Pn ->Q or justQThe formulas Pi and Q must be positive literals.  
 QueriesGiven a set of Horn clauses (the hypotheses) and a query (the conclusion) , we caneasily check if the query is true.A ^ B ^ C -> DB -> CAEA ^ E -> B------------------------D  
 ProofOne systematic way is to keep a stack of goals yet to be proved. Begin by pushing the conclusion (D) on the stack.While the stack is not empty, pop the stack to get the current goal. If a fact (atomic clause) matches the goal, return T.If not, search for an implication whose right-hand side matches the goal, and then push all the conjuncts from the left-hand side onto the stack (if not already there).  
￼Example‏)D (conclusion‏)A B C (matches first clause‏)B C (A is a fact‏)A E C (matches fifth clause‏)E C (A is a fact‏)C (E is a fact‏)B (matches second clause‏)A E (matches fifth clause‏)E (A is a fact‏)E is a fact(￼￼
 ResolutionAlternatively we could use resolution. Written as a clause set (with the conclusionnegated) we have:~A v ~B v ~C v D~B v CAE~A v ~E v B ~DA restricted form of resolution called LUSH or SLD works fine for these sets.  
 ListsWe can add a list constructor to this language:[] means the empty list, and cons(x,y) means the list with first element x and the remainder is y (so x is added to the beginning of list y).We can use standard list notation as shorthand for our lists.The list cons(a, cons(b, cons(c, []))) would be written [a,b,c].We also use the vertical bar (|) with brackets to be shorthand for cons – [x|y] means cons (x,y).  
￼Statements about ListsWe can use this notation to define list operations:‏)]member(x, [x | y‏)]member(x, z) -> member(x, [y | zmeans that x is a member of a list which has x as its head, and if x is a member z, then x is a member of the list constructed by adding y to the head of z.￼￼
￼SortingWhat does it mean if one list is the sorted version of another list?For example, consider [3,1,4,2] and [1,2,3,4].They both must have the same members, and the second list must be in order.We assume that we have predicates for the usual mathematical relations such as <=. To state that a list is in order we could say:‏)]inOrder([y | z])^(x <= y)->inOrder([x, y | z‏)][(inOrder‏)]inOrder([x￼￼
￼Same ElementsTo check if two lists have exactly the same member is a little more complicated. Tostate this property, we use a three argument member predicate which removes themember of the list, i.e.,‏)member(x, y, zmeans that x is a member of y and that z is the result of removing (one instance of) x from y.member(3,[1,2,3,4],[1,2,4]) is true.￼￼
‏)Same Elements (cont'd￼‏)member(x, [x | y], y‏)]member(x, y, z) -> member(x, [w | y], [w | z‏)][ ,][(sameElementssameElements(y, z), member(x, w, z) ->‏)sameElements([x | y], w    ￼￼
￼Sorting‏)sameElements(x,y) ^ inOrder(y) -> sorted(x,y‏)][ ,][(sameElementssameElements(y, z), member(x, w, z) ->‏)sameElements([x | y], w    ‏)member(x, [x | y], y‏)]member(x, y, z) -> member(x, [w | y], [w | z‏)]inOrder([y | z])^(x <= y)->inOrder([x, y | z‏)][(inOrder‏)]inOrder([x￼￼
 Prologsorted(L1,L2) :- sameElements(L1,L2), inOrder(L2).inOrder([X,Y|L]) :- X =< Y, inOrder([Y|L]).inOrder([]).inOrder([_]).sameElements([],[]).sameElements([X|L1],L2) :- sameElements(L1,L3),member(X,L2,L3).member(X,[X|L],L).member(X,[Y|L],[Y|L1]) :- member(X,L,L1).  
‏)Prolog (cont'd￼Prolog is a language built on top of a resolution theorem prover.The specification of the program is (or can be) the executable program. We blur the distinction between the declarative and the procedural.￼￼