 Logical Equivalences(α ^ β) ≡ (β ^ α)(α v β) ≡ (β v α)((α ^ β) ^ γ) ≡ (α ^ (β ^ γ))((α v β) v γ) ≡ (α v (β v γ)) ¬(¬α)≡α(α→β)≡ (¬ β → ¬ α) (α→β)≡ (¬ α v β)(α↔β)≡ ((α → β) ^ (β → α)) ¬(α^β)≡ (¬ α v ¬ β) ¬(αvβ)≡ (¬ α ^ ¬ β)(α ^ (β v γ)) ≡ ((α ^ β) v (α ^ γ)) (α v (β ^ γ)) ≡ ((α v β) ^ (α v γ))commutativity of ^ commutativity of v associativity of ^ associativity of v double-negation elimination contrapositionimplication removal biconditional removal De Morgan's LawDe Morgan's Law distributivity of ^ over v distributivity of v over ^  
 Natural DeductionThere are twelve rules in this system:^i1:∨e1: →i:^i2: ^e:∨e2: ∨i:→e: ¬i: ¬e: ⊥e: ¬¬e:  
 Deduction Procedureυ We can use the standard search algorithms to find proofs using the system of natural deduction:υ  The initial state is just the set of hypotheses.υ  To create a new state, apply one of the twelve rules to lines and boxes that occur (previously) in the proof.υ  We need two additional moves:υ Open a box starting with formula P, i.e., assume P υ Close an open box (requires an open box)υ  A goal state is one where there are no open boxes and the last line is the proposition to be proved.  
 ComplexityIn the worst case, the time complexity is exponential in the size of the input – but that's true for every known inference procedure.  
 ResolutionResolution is a system of deduction that uses just a single rule. The rule is a generalization of the rule:  
 NotationA literal is a proposition symbol or its negation, e.g. P or ¬P.A positive literal is a proposition symbol, e.g., PA negative literal is a negated proposition symbol, e.g., ¬P.Two literals are complementary if they contain the same proposition symbol and one literal is positive and one is negative, e.g., P and ¬P.  
 Notation (cont'd)A clause is a set of literals, e.g. {P, Q, ¬R, S}.The meaning of a clause is the disjunction of the literals in the set, e.g., P v Q v ¬R v S.The empty clause, {}, is false.A clause set is a set of clauses, e.g., {{P, ¬Q, R}, {R, S}}.The meaning of a clause set is the conjunction of the clauses in the set, e.g., (P v ¬Q v R) ^ (R v S).A clause set which contains the empty clause, { {}, ...} is false.The empty clause set is true.  
 Resolution RuleThe full resolution rule is:where li and mj are complementary literals. Using clause notation, this rule is:  
 Conjunctive Normal Form (CNF)Every sentence of propositional logic is logically equivalent to a conjunction of clauses (a clause set).Procedure to find the CNF of a sentence:υ  Remove ↔, by replacing α ↔ β with (α → β) ^ (β → α).υ  Remove →, by replacing α → β with ¬ α v β.υ  Push ¬ inwards as much as possible by repeatedly using: ¬(¬ α) ≡ α, ¬(α ^ β) ≡ ¬ αv ¬ β, and ¬(α v β) ≡ (¬ α ^ ¬ β).υ  Distribute v over ^ whenever possible. υ  Optional: Write as a set of clause.  
 CNF: ExampleP ↔ (¬Q v S)≡ (P → (¬Q v S)) ^ ((¬Q v S) → P)≡ (¬P v ¬Q v S) ^ (¬(¬Q v S) v P)≡ (¬P v ¬Q v S) ^ ((¬(¬Q) ^ ¬S) v P) ≡ (¬P v ¬Q v S) ^ ((Q ^ ¬S) v P)≡ (¬P v ¬Q v S) ^ (Q v P) ^ (¬S v P){{¬P,¬Q,S}, {Q,P}, {¬S,P}}  
 Resolution ProcedureThe resolution procedure is a refutation procedure, that is, it proves a proposition by negating it and then finding a contradiction (proof by contradiction).Thus, if we want to show that KB ⊨ α, we show that KB ^ ¬α is unsatisfiable. The procedure is as follows:Put KB ^ ¬α into Conjunctive Normal Form (CNF).This creates an initial clause set.Find a pair of clauses in the set that contain complementary literals and use the resolution rule to derive a new clause (resolve the two clauses).  
 Resolution Procedure (cont'd)If the new clause is not already in the set of clauses, add it to the set. Continue until either:υ  No new clauses can be added to the set.υ  The resolution rule produces {}, the empty clause.In the first case, there is no refutation, so KB does not entail α.Recall that the empty clause is an empty disjunction which is false. Thus, a refutation is found andKB ⊨ α.  
 Resolution: ExampleKB=R2^R4 =(B1,1 ↔(P1,2 vP2,1))^¬B1,1 Α = ¬P2,1   
 Resolution Codefunction PL-Resolution(KB,α) returns true or false inputs: KB, the knowledge base, a sentence in PLα, the query, a sentence in PLclauses ← the set of clauses in the CNF representation of KB ^ ¬α new ← {}loop dofor each pair of clauses Ci, Cj in clauses doresolvents ← PL-Resolve(Ci, Cj)if resolvents contains the empty clause then return true new ← new U resolventsif new ⊆ clauses then return false clauses ← clauses U new  
 Soundness of ResolutionOne application of the resolution rule is sound, i.e., if the resolvent in a resolution step is false in a model then one (or both) of the clauses resolved upon must be false in the model.where li and mj are complementary literals.By induction, if the result of any number of resolution steps is false in a model, then one of the original clauses must be false in the model.  
 Soundness of Resolution (cont'd)Suppose we derive the empty clause, {}. Consider a model M:υ {} is false in M.By induction, one of the original clauses must be false in M.Since a clause set is a conjunction, the clause set must be false in M.Since {} is false in every model, the original clause set must be false in every model. If KB is true in a model, since KB ^ ¬α is unsatisfiable, KB ^ ¬α is false in that model.So α must be true in the model, and KB ⊨ α.  
 Completeness of ResolutionResolution is also complete.That is, if KB ⊨ α then the resolution procedure will eventually produce the empty clause, {}, given KB ^ ¬α.The proof is in the book.  
 Horn ClausesIn some situations, we only need to use certain restricted forms of clauses and inference is simpler.Definitions:υ  Definite clause: Clause (disjunction of literals) with exactly one positive literal. {P, ¬Q, ¬R}υ  Horn clause: Clause with at most one positive literal. {P, ¬Q, ¬R}, {¬Q, ¬R} υ  Goal clause: Clause with no positive literals.{¬Q, ¬R}  
 Horn Clauses (cont'd)Some KBs contain only positive clauses.A positive clause can be written as an implication where the premise is a conjunction of positive literals, and the conclusion is a single positive literal.{P, ¬Q, ¬R} ≡ Q ^ R → P.Such knowledge is easy to apply (because of the lack of disjunction).If Q is true, and R is true, we have that P is true.A sentence consisting of a single positive literal is called a fact, e.g., P  
 Horn Clause InferenceHorn clauses are closed under resolution.Inference with Horn clauses can be done through either forward-chaining or backward-chaining algorithms.Deciding entailment with Horn clauses can be done in time linear to the size of the KB.Horn clauses (and a resolution theorem prover) are the basis of the Prolog (PROcedural LOGic) programming language.In a Horn clause, the premise is called the body, and the conclusion is called the head.  
 And-Or Graph for Horn ClausesP→Q L^M→P B ^ L→ M A^P→L A^B→L AB   
 Backward-Chaining AlgorithmThe backward-chaining algorithm begins with the goal, the sentence to be proved, and works backward through the graph, to the facts of the KB.If a node is an Or-node, then one of its parents need to be proved, e.g., LIf a node is an And-node, all of its parents need to be proved, e.g. the unlabeled nodes below L.  
 And-Or Search Graph AlgorithmWe can use the And-Or Search Graph Algorithm from Chapter 4.The initial state is the one that contains the proposition to be proved.The goal states are the facts of the KB.To prove an Or-node, prove one of its parents.To prove an And-node, prove all of its parents.The Actions available to a state are the implications whose head matches the proposition in the state.The Results are the set of propositions in the body.  
 And-Or Search Graph Algorithmfunction And-Or-Graph-Search(problem) returns a conditional plan, or failure Or-Search(problem.Initial-State, problem, [])function Or-Search(state, problem, path) returns a conditional plan, or failure if problem.Goal-Test(state) then return the empty planif state is on path then return failurefor each action in problem.Actions(state) doplan ← And-Search(Results(state,action), problem, [state | path])if plan ≠ failure then return [action | plan] return failure  
 And-Or Search Graph Algorithmfunction And-Search(states, problem, path) returns a conditional plan, or failure for each si in states doplani ← Or-Search(si, problem, path)if plani = failure then return failurereturn [if si then plan1 else if s2 then plan2 else ... if sn-1 then plann-1 else plann]  
 And-Or Search Graph: ExampleQPL (M)A (P)A√ PxA (B) A√ B√MB (L) BL√ ...  
 Local Search AlgorithmsLocal search algorithms can be applied to the problem of satisfiability, i.e., is there a model that satisfies a given formula.They typically begin with a random model.The goal is to find a model that satisfies the formula. If the model doesn't satisfy the formula, then the model is changed by “flipping” one of the variables, i.e., changing true to false and vice versa.The measure used by the Min_Conflicts algorithm is useful, i.e., try to minimize the number of unsatisfied clauses.  
 WalkSatOne simple and effective produce is called WalkSat.WalkSat begins by picking a random model, M, for the formula.If the formula is not satisfied by M, WalkSat picks an unsatisfied clause, a variable of the clause, and then flips the variable.It either selects the variable randomly (random walk) or chooses the variable that minimizes the number of unsatisfied clauses (Min-Conflicts).It chooses the former method with probability p.The algorithm runs for max_flips iterations and fails if it doesn't find a model in that time.  
 WalkSat Algorithmfunction WalkSat(clauses, p, max_flips) returns a satisfying model or failure inputs: clauses a set of clauses in PLp, the probability of choosing to do a “random walk” move, typically around 0.5max_flips, the number of flips allowed before giving up model ← a random assignment of true/false to the symbols in clauses for i = 1 to max_flips doif model satisfies clauses then return modelclause ← a randomly selected clause from clauses that is false in modelwith probability p flip the value in model of a randomly selected symbol fromclauseelse flip whichever symbol in clause maximizes the number of satisfied clausesreturn failure  
 Davis-Putnam ProcedureThis is the modified Davis-Putnam procedure (Davis, Putnam, Logemann, and Loveland) for checking satisfiability.We note that if P is unsatisfiable, it's negation is valid.The procedure works by starting with an empty model (no assignments to the variables) and adds assignments.If a (partial) model satisfies the formula, the procedure halts early and returns true.  
 Davis-Putnam Procedure (cont'd)If a proposition letter always occurs as a positive (negative) literal, then it will be assigned the value true (false.)υ This is called a pure symbol.If a clause is a unit clause (contains a single literal), then, the symbol will be assigned a value to make the literal true.Note that as we make assignments, we can partially evaluate and simplify the formula, producing more pure literals and unit clauses.  
 Davis-Putnam Procedurefunction DPLL(clauses, symbols, model) returns true or false if every clause in clauses is true in model then return trueif some clause in clauses is false in model then return false P, value ← Find-Pure-Symbol(symbol, clauses, model)if P is non-null then return DPLL(clauses, symbols – P, model U { P = value }) P, value ← Find-Unit-Clause(clauses, model)if P is non-null then return DPLL(clauses, symbols – P, model U { P = value }) P ← First(symbols); rest ← rest(symbols)return DPLL(clauses, rest, model U { P = true }) or DPLL(clauses, rest, model U { P = false})  
 Agents Based on Prop. LogicWe have seen that we can represent aspects of the Wumpus world using propositional logic.However, there is a difficulty in representing the state of the agent. For example, which room is the agent in?The problem is that the agent's state changes over time. So we cannot merely assert that the agent is in square [1,1], L1,1, because that may not always be true.  
 TimeWe can assert that the agent is in square [1,1] at time 0, Lo1,1.The rules that apply to the agent's percepts and actions would also be superscripted with the time, and we need the rules pertaining to them to use the subscripted variables.The word fluent refers to aspects of the world that change.The term atemporal variables refers to variables that don't change over time.  
 Transition ModelThe transition model is represented by a set of formulas: υ  Atemporal Axioms: ¬P1,1, B1,1 ↔ (P1,2 v P2,1).υ  Percepts Axioms : Ltx,y → (Breezet ↔ Bx,y).υ  Effect Axioms: L01,1 ^ FacingEast0 ^ Forward0 → (L12,1 ^ ¬L11,1). υ  Frame Axioms: Forwardt → (HaveArrowt → HaveArrowt+1).  
 Frame ProblemThe frame axioms say that as the agent takes an action, and the world changes, many things in the world do not change (unless the agent explicitly changes them.)For example, if the agent doesn't fire an arrow, then the agent would still have the arrow (if the agent had the arrow before).Patient to doctor: Will I be able to play the piano?  
 Frame Problem (cont'd)For each fluent, we would need to write axioms that say:If the action changes the fluent, then the fluent (at the next time) is not changed.If the action doesn't change the fluent, then fluent (at the next time) stays the same.There may be many fluents, and many actions, so there may be many frame axioms.  
 Hybrid Agent (Wumpus World)We can combine condition-action rules, propositional reasoning, and problem-solving algorithms to form a hybrid agent.The hybrid agent maintains and updates a KB as well as a current plan.The initial KB contains the atemporal axioms.The agent constructs a plan based on a decreasing priority of goals (get gold, kill wumpus, stay alive, leave cave).Route planning is done with the A*-algorithm.The agent asks the database if a square is safe before moving.If no square is provably safe, the agent chooses a square that is not provably unsafe.  